<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exposition of the ten commandements of God vvherein the principall and most materiall doctrines are set downe; by Edvvard Elton, bachelor in diuinitie, and preacher of Gods word at Saint Marie Magdalens Barmondsey neare London.</title>
            <title>Plaine and easie exposition of sixe of the commandements of God in tables</title>
            <author>Elton, Edward, d. 1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 244 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 130 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69277</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7620.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113641</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848872</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848872</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13990</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69277)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13990)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 643:19 or 1727:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exposition of the ten commandements of God vvherein the principall and most materiall doctrines are set downe; by Edvvard Elton, bachelor in diuinitie, and preacher of Gods word at Saint Marie Magdalens Barmondsey neare London.</title>
                  <title>Plaine and easie exposition of sixe of the commandements of God in tables</title>
                  <author>Elton, Edward, d. 1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 257, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Mylbourne, and are to be sold at the great South-doore of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Another issue, with additions and cancel title page of Elton, Edward.  A plaine and easie exposition of sixe of the commandements of God in tables.</note>
                  <note>A1, title page, is a cancel; C8 and R4, probably blanks, lacking.--Folger Shakespeare Library catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Printed by R. Field. Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K⁸ L⁸(-L⁸) M-Q⁸ R³.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: item at reel 1727:21 has pages torn with some loss of print and t.p. defaced.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 7614a at reel 643:19.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 643 (Folger Shakespeare Library) and at reel 1727 (Harvard University. Library).</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Folger Shakespeare Library and G.B. Evans Collection, Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ten commandments --  Criticism, interpretation, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13990:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13990:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXPOSITION OF THE TEN COMMANDEMENTS OF GOD:</p>
            <p>Wherein the principall and moſt materiall doctrines are <hi>ſet downe;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By EDVVARD ELTON, Bachelor in Diuinitie, and Preacher of Gods word at Saint <hi>Marie Magailens Barmondſey</hi> neare <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Robert Mylbourne,</hi> and are to be ſold at the great South-doore of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1623.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="commandment">
            <pb facs="tcp:13990:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13990:2"/>
            <head>THE FIRST COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MANDEMENT, <hi>The Negatiue Part,</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T forbids,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Atheiſme or deniall of God:</p>
            <p>Secondly, all falſe opinions of God:</p>
            <p>Thirdly, confidence in creatures. Atheiſme or deniall of God:</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.1. 2 King. 6.33. 2 King. 7.2. Malac. 2.17. Malac. 3.14.</note> when a man doth ſay or at leaſt thinke there is no God at all; coming to this kind of Atheiſme by two ſteps:</p>
            <p>Firſt, by imagining God ſeeth not vs, or doth not regard vs, Pſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:13990:3"/>10.11. Zephan. 1.12.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by imagining that God is not ſo ſharpe and ſeuere in puniſhing ſinne,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.11.</note> as the Scriptures ſet him forth to be. Pſal. 50.16.17.18.19.20.21.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.12.</note> when a man hath a falſe God inſtead of the true God,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Either by placing and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping that which is not God, in the roome of the true God, Act. 19.27.35.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Or by thinking ſome other thing beſides the true God to be his chiefeſt good. Philip. 3.19. Coloſſ. 3.5.2. Cor. 4.4.</p>
            <p>All falſe opinions of God, as</p>
            <p>Firſt, when men ioyne others to God, and do not acknowledge him alone, and that three wayes:</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">2 King. 17.32 33.41.</note> by profeſſing more then one religion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by praying to others
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13990:3"/>beſide the true God. Deut. 6.13.
<note place="margin">Zephan. 1.5. Deut. 22.10.11. 1 King. 18.21.</note> Deut. 10.20. Mat. 4.10. Ier. 2.10. Act. 1.24. Exod. 22.20.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, by magicke or witchcraft; and that either by</p>
            <p n="1">1. Being Magicians or witches themſelues. Pſal. 58.5. Deut. 18.11.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Or by ſeeking to Magicians or witches, and vſing their helpe. 2. King. 1.3.16. Iſai. 8.9. Leuit. 20.6.</p>
            <p>Secondly when men do not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge God as he is, and as he hath reuealed himſelfe in his word, and herein men erre in miſconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of God, touching his eſſence, perſons of the Godhead, and attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes. Rom. 1.21.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 96.4.5. Iſay 37.19. Ierem. 14.22. 1 Cor. 8.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, his Eſſence,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In making a multiplicitie of gods, and thinking there be many gods.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In conceiuing God to be that which he is not, and thinking him
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13990:4"/>to be like to creatures, Act. 17.29.</p>
            <p>Secondly, his perſons of the Godhead:</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Gen 1.26. Mat. 3.16.17. Mat. 28.19. 2. Cor. 13.13. 1 Ioh. 5.7.</note> In denying the three perſons.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In holding not onely the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of the perſons, but the
<note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 10.30. 1 Ioh. 5.7.</note> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion alſo of the ſubſtance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In holding
<note n="*" place="margin">Eſai. 7.14. Eſai. 9.6. Mat. 1.23. Ioh. 1.1. Rom 9.5.</note> Chriſt the Sonne of God, not to be very God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In holding
<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 3.22 Mat. 28.19. 1. Iohn 5.7.</note> the three perſons of the Godhead, to be but three names and titles giuen to God in Scripture.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, his Attributes, eſpecially theſe fiue.</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Ezech. 8.12. Iob. 22.13.14.</note> Knowledge, and the miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of that brings forth <hi>hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Power, and the miſconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of that brings forth,</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note n="*" place="margin">2 Chron. 33 10 &amp; cap. 36.16. Iſai. 5.19. Iſai. 28.15.22, 2 Pet 3.34.</note> Contempt of God, ſhewed,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In contemning his threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:13990:4"/> 2.
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 28.22. Ierem. 5.3. Amos 4.6.7.8 9.10.11.12. Num. 14.1.2. Exod. 17.7. Pſal. 78.18.19 Mat. 4.6.7.</note> In taking no profite by his puniſhments.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A proud tempting of God, ſhewed,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In muttering againſt God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In ſeeking experience of his power.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In trying whether he be ſuch a
<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 5.9. Malac. 5.15.</note> powerfull God of vengeance as the Scriptures ſet him forth to be.</p>
            <p n="3">3
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 57.10. Num. 13.2.3. 2 Pet. 3.4.9.</note> Truth, and the miſconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of that brings forth,</p>
            <p n="1">1
<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 19.14. Pſal. 116.11. Num. 11.21.22 Rom. 4.20.</note> Incredulity, ſhewed in doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe and diffidence.</p>
            <p n="2">2
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 42.5. Heb. 10.38. Pro. 3.5. 2 King. 6.33 Iſai. 28.16. Hab 2.3.4.</note> Impatience, ſhewed in not waiting on God in time of triall for the accompliſhment of his promiſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4.
<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 18.25. Ierem. 51.56. Nahum. 1.2.3 2 Theſ. 1.6.7. Rom. 2.6.7.8.</note> Iuſtice, and the miſconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of that brings forth,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Carnall ſecurity, Ierem. 8.6. Mat. 24.38.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Spiritual ſlothfulnes, Reu. 3.15.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Raſh and inconſiderate zeale.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13990:5"/>Luke 9.54.</p>
            <p n="5">5.
<note place="margin">Exod. 34.67.2. Chron. 30.9 Iſai. 55.7. Iam. 5.11.</note> Mercy, and the miſconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of that brings forth</p>
            <p>Deſperation. 1. King. 19.4. Act. 16.27. Gen. 4.13.2. Cor. 2.7.</p>
            <p>Preſumption. 2. Sam. 4.5.7. Eccleſ. 11.6. Deut. 29.19.20. Iud. epiſt. v. 4.</p>
            <p>Impenitencie, and enuying of Gods grace and mercie, in others and to others. Rom. 2.4.5.</p>
            <p>Confidence in creatures. Pſal. 20.7. Iſai. 2.22.</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Pro. 28.26. Mat. 26.33.35 Act. 12.22.23.</note> As in themſelues; whence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes</p>
            <p n="1">1. Pride or arrogancie. Deut. 8.17.18. Dan. 4.27. Hab. 1.16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Vaine glorie or carnall boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting. Ioh. 5.44. Luke 10.20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In other men. Iſai. 36.6. Ier. 17.5.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In other things, as</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note n="*" place="margin">Iob. 31 24. 1 Tim. 6.17. Pſal. 62.10. Ierem. 49.16. Obad. v. 3.4. Pſal. 146.3.</note> Riches.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Strong holds.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:13990:5"/> 3. Honour, authoritie, high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the like.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The affirmatiue part of the firſt Commandement.</head>
               <p>It requires two things eſpecially.
<note place="margin">Iſai. 8.13. 1 Chron. 28.9. Ierem. 9.24. Ioh. 17.3. Pſal. 9.10. Hoze. 4.16. Coloſſ. 1.10.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That the mind and heart haue a due reſpect to God, acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging him to be ſuch a God as he hath reuealed himſelfe to be in his word and workes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Confidence in God, and that we reſt on him alone.</p>
               <p>The firſt is grounded on the true knowledg of God as he hath made himſelfe knowne in his word, both in his <hi>Eſſence, perſons, properties and workes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Expreſſed</p>
               <p n="1">1. In Faith,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.25. Heb. 11.6. Heb. 6.1.</note> whereof there be three ſorts:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Fundamentall faith, appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13990:6"/>the eſſence and being of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.2.</note> Faith of Miracles, apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the power of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">Iam. 2.19.</note> Faith of the hiſtorie, or hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall faith, apprehending the truth of God reuealed in his written word.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In hope,
<note place="margin">2. Chro. 20.1. Iſai. 8.17. Pſal. 27.14.</note> which brings forth ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall fortitude or courage, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in</p>
               <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.7. Rom. 8.24.25 Ioh. 1.6.7.8.9 Heb. 11.27. 2 Sam. 16.10.11.12. Iam. 5.11. Deut. 6.5. Luke 10.27. Act. 17.28. Iam 1.17. Mal. 3.16. Pſal. 119.55. 2 Tim. 4.8.</note> Spirituall ſecuritie. Pſal. 3.5.6.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Conſtancie in good things.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Patience in time of trouble and aduerſitie.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In loue to God, manifeſted,</p>
               <p n="1">1. In often thinking and ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of God to his glorie, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his preſence.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In louing his word and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In louing his children and ſeruants.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:13990:6"/> 4. In louing his glory,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 27.4. Pſal. 119.97.131. Pſal. 16.3. 1 Ioh. 5.21. Exod. 32.12.32. Ioh. 14.1. Gen. 18.27. Iſai. 8.13. Heb. 12.28.29</note> and being zealous for that aboue all things.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In doing his will cheerfully. Bringing forth effects,</p>
               <p>Properly reſpecting God, namely</p>
               <p n="1">1. An holy ſubmiſſion to the maieſtie of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The feare of God, which brings forth</p>
               <p n="1">1. An hatred of ſinne,
<note place="margin">Pro. 8.13. Iob 31.23. Gen. 20.11. Rom. 3.18. Heb. 12.28.</note> and a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full auoyding of the offence of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A care to approue our ſelues to God in all things</p>
               <p>Is of two ſorts</p>
               <p n="1">1. Childlike. Pſal. 130.4.1. Pet.
<note place="margin">Gen. 39.9.</note> 1.17.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Seruile. 1. Iohn 4.18. Rom. 13.5.</p>
               <p>Theſe two differing each from other in the <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Obiect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>More nearely reſpecting our ſelues.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.7. 2 Cor. 3.5.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:13990:7"/>
               <p> Deniall of our ſelues,
<note place="margin">Mat. 16.24. Luke 9.23. Pro. 3.7. 1 Cor. 3.18. Rom. 8.7.</note> expreſſed</p>
               <p n="1">1. In renouncing vtterly our owne reaſon, wil, and affections, as of themſelues enemies to God and all goodneſſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In ſubmitting our ſelues wholly to Gods wiſedome and will in all things,
<note place="margin">Gen. 12.1.4. Gen. 22.1.2.9. Heb. 11.8. Deut. 33.9. Mat. 4.20. Luke 5.10. Act 20.24. Gen. 32.10. 1 Chronic. 29 14.15.16. 1. Cor. 4.7. 1 Cor. 1.31. 1 Cor. 15.9. 1 Tim. 1.15. Rom. 12.10. 1. Cor. 4.6. 1 Pet. 5.5. Philip. 2.23. Phil. 4.11.12. 1 Cor. 12.7.</note> though neuer ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to our wils and deſires.</p>
               <p>Humilitie, making men</p>
               <p n="1">1 Thinke moſt baſely of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, in regard of their owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and ſins.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Eſteeme better of others then of themſelues, hauing the ſame good gifts that they haue; and to reſpect them accordingly.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Content with their particular places and conditions of life, not to preſume beyond that abilitie and ſtrength that is giuen them.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is grounded on due acknowledgement of Gods</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:13990:7"/> 1 Good prouidence and mercy.
<note place="margin">2 Chro. 20.20 Pſal. 37.3.5. Pſal. 27.1.2.3. 2 Tim. 1.12. Pſal. 33.18.19 Pſal. 84.11.12. Pſal. 91.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 Power.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Former experience of his power and prouidence towards our ſelues and others:</p>
               <p>Bringing forth</p>
               <p>A conuerſation void of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe and diſtruſtful care.</p>
               <p>Invocation or calling on the name of God,
<note place="margin">Pro. 16.3. Mat. 6.25. 1 Tim. 6.6.7.8.9.10. Dan. 9.7.18. Pſal. 50.15. Iam. 1.5.</note> ſtanding</p>
               <p>In Petition and thankeſgiuing.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="commandment">
            <head>The ſecond Commandement. The Negatiue part.</head>
            <p>The ſecond Commandement containes,</p>
            <p n="1">1 A precept or commandement.</p>
            <p n="2">2 A confirmation of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement by arguments perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the obedience of it.</p>
            <p>The precept or commandement forbids all manner of Idolatrie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13990:8"/>which is forbidden,
<note place="margin">Ezech. 14.3.4.7. Deut. 27.15. 1 Ioh. 5.21. Exod. 23.24. Deut. 7.25. Deut. 12.3.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Inward Idolatrie of the heart, which is when men miſconceiuing God, do worſhip him according to that miſconceit.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Outward Idolatry of the hand, which is when men make an image or ſimilitude, and erect and ſet it vp for religious vſe. And that is done two wayes,</p>
            <p n="1">1 By making and erecting an i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage repreſenting either ſome fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned god,
<note place="margin">Deut. 4.15.16 Iſay 40.18.25 Act. 17.29. Rom. 1.23. Hoze. 13.2. Deut. 7.25.26 1 King. 18.19. 1 Cor. 6.20. Deut. 7.2.3. Ezra. 9.2.12.14. 2 Chron. 19.2. Pſal. 106.35.36. Mal. 2.11. 2 Cor. 6.14.15.16.</note> or that which is not God.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By making and erecting an i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the true God and of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to worſhip it.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Approbation of Idolatrie by preſence, ſpeech, geſture, ſilence, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4 All vnneceſſarie dealing or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaritie with Idolaters.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Contempt of the outward worſhip of God, which is</p>
            <p n="1">1 Inward, when men in their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13990:8"/>hearts contemne the holy ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God,
<note place="margin">Ezech. 22.8. Mat. 22.5. Luke 14.18.19.20. Mal. 3.14. Iob. 2.15. 1 Cor. 1.18.21</note> and the duties and parts of his worſhip, and think baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of them; which brings forth ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</p>
            <p n="1">1 Neglect of them altogether.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or intermiſſion of the duties of Gods worſhip.
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 30.5</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Or an hypocriticall coming vnto them,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 29.13.</note> and a formall perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Outward,
<note place="margin">Num. 11.2.6. Act. 17.18.</note> when men openly manifeſt their contempt of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordinances of God, and the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and parts of his worſhip, either by word or deed, and that</p>
            <p n="1">1 Either in part contemning the Preaching of the word, &amp;c.
<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 5.20. 2 Chro. 30.10</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Or in wholl,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.4. Heb. 12.16. Compared with Gen. 25.34.</note> contemning all the holy ordinances of God, and all the holy duties of his worſhip, which is properly called <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:13990:9"/> 3 All humane deuiſes,
<note place="margin">Mark. 7.3.4.</note> or ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the worſhip of God, (that is) ſuch things in the worſhip of God, as are inuented by men; and are contrarie vnto the rule of Gods word; and ſuch things men do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe two waies,</p>
            <p n="1">1 By adding ſomething to the eſſentiall worſhip of God: and things added are,</p>
            <p n="1">1 Either, things meerely deuiſed by men, hauing no warrant at all in the word of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or things in themſelues indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent,
<note place="margin">Mar. 7.3.4.</note> made neceſſary parts of Gods eſſentiall worſhip.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By detracting ſomething from the worſhip of God, contrary to Gods word.</p>
            <p>And humane deuiſes are</p>
            <p n="1">1 Either ſuch as men take vp of themſelues vpon a bare and naked good intent,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 13.9.10 13.</note> thinking that thereby
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13990:9"/>they worſhip God,
<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2. vlt.</note> which is proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called wilwor-ſhip.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or they are ſuch as haue bene deuiſed by others,
<note place="margin">Ezech. 20.18. Mat. 15.2. Mar. 7.3.</note> and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from them, properly called tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the <hi>Elders.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The affirmatiue part of the ſecond Commandement.</head>
               <p>It requires that the true God be worſhipped with ſpiritual worſhip,
<note place="margin">Exod. 25.9. Deut. 12.32. Iſa. 1.12. Ioh. 4.23.24. Iſai. 1.13.14.15. Iſai. 66.3.</note> or after a ſpirituall manner. And that</p>
               <p n="1">1 Standing in two things</p>
               <p n="1">1 In worſhipping God in ſuch things as are agreable to his will.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In worſhipping God in things and duties commanded of God, in ſuch manner as is agreeable to the nature of God, in ſpirit and truth.
<note place="margin">Iohn 4.22. Micha. 6.6.7.8</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 Grounded on true and ſound knowledge of the expreſſe will of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13990:10"/>God,
<note place="margin">Mat. 15 9. Eccleſ. 4.17.</note> teaching all the parts of his worſhip, and the manner of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of them.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Is to be expreſſed in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe and performance of thoſe things that concerne the holy and ſolemne ſeruice of God, (namely) the true and ordinarie meanes of holineſſe, and the parts of Gods worſhip; which are eſpecially</p>
               <p n="1">1 Prayer,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 1.15. Pſal. 42.4. Iſai. 37.4. Lam. 3.41. 1. Cor. 2.4. 1. Cor. 14.24.25. Act. 26.2.5.</note> publike and priuate, ſtanding in petition, and thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The Miniſterie of the word of God. 1. Cor. 11.23. 1. Pet. 4.11.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The Sacraments. 1 Cor. 10.16</p>
               <p n="4">4 Is expreſſed in the vſing of the ordinarie meanes of holineſſe, and the parts of Gods worſhip, after an holy maner.
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.8. Rom. 14.17.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 Is helped forward and furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by ſuch things as do binde, and ſtirre vp men to the performance of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13990:10"/>holy duties; which things are
<list>
                     <item>1 Speciall vowes.</item>
                     <item>2 Religious faſting.</item>
                  </list> The confirmation of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement by Arguments per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading to the obedience of it, taken</p>
               <p n="1">1 Partly from the nature of God, in two Attributes; as that he is</p>
               <p n="1">1 Strong (that is) able to puniſh the diſobedient,
<note place="margin">Nahum. 1.3.4.5.6. Apocal. 18.8 Dan. 3.17. Dan. 6.20.21.22. Rom. 8.31. Hoze. 10.19.20. Ierem. 2.2. Ierem 3 1.2.6.7. Ezech 16.15.16.17. &amp;c.</note> and to maintaine &amp; defend all ſuch as truly worſhip him againſt all that oppoſe them.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Iealous (that is) louing his Church with exceeding great and ſuperabundant holy loue, being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly offended for Idolatrie, and executing his wrath moſt ſharply vpon Idolaters.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Partly, from the effects of his,</p>
               <p n="1">1 Anger,
<note place="margin">Exod. 20.5.</note> viſiting the iniquitie of the fathers vpon the children, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the third generation and vpon the fourth of them that hate me,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13990:11"/>(that is) taking notice of iniquitie, and puniſhing the iniquitie of the fathers vpon their children going on in their ſinnes, to the third and fourth generation.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Loue,
<note place="margin">Exod. 20.6.</note> ſhewing mercy vnto thouſands, to them that loue me &amp; keep my commandements, (that is) doing good to many generations of the faithful ſucceſſiuely, going on in the ſteps of their godly parents, and obeying God as they did.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="commandment">
            <head>The third Commandement. <hi>The Negatiue part.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The third Commandement con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,</p>
            <p>Firſt, a precept or commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Secondly, a commination or threatning denounced againſt the breakers of it.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:13990:11"/>
            <p> The precept forbids all manner of <hi>prophanation</hi> and abuſe of Gods name, ſtanding in the abuſe of his titles, hi attributes, his workes, and his word, and his holy <hi>ordinances.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, his titles are abuſed, when men take them into their mouthes and vſe them in their ſpeech vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently, and without due reſpect; and that either without an oath, or with an oath.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Without an oath, as when men mention any of Gods titles in their common talke raſhly,
<note place="margin">Deut. 28.58.</note> careleſly and vnreuerently; and that either</p>
            <p>In a fooliſh admiration vpon ſome ſudden accident or ſtrange re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, ſaying Good God, oh Lord, oh Ieſus. Philip 2.10.</p>
            <p>In idle wiſhes, and imprecations,
<note place="margin">Gen. 16.5.</note> as when men wiſh il to themſelues, or to others, and vſe the name of God in their wiſhes.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:13990:12"/>
            <p> In curſing, as when men ſay, Gods curſe light on ſuch, &amp;c. Iam. 3.9.10. 2. Sam. 16.7.8.</p>
            <p>In praiſing God for euill things, 1. Sam. 23.21.</p>
            <p n="2">2 With an oath, as when men ſweare by them in their ſpeech, lightly and <hi>prophanely,</hi> and that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</p>
            <p n="1">1 By God calling for a witneſſe of vaine and friuolous things,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 23.10. Hoze. 4.2. Mat. 5.37.</note> by vſuall ſwearing in their common talke.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By calling God for a witneſſe of their furious anger,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 14.34. 1. Sam. 25.34.</note> by paſſionate ſwearing.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By calling God for a witneſſe of an vntruth,
<note place="margin">Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch. 5.4. Leuit. 19.12.</note> by ſwearing falſly, or forſwearing themſelues; which is done</p>
            <p n="1">1 By ſwearing that which they know or thinke to be falſe,
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.72.</note> and that either directly againſt their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or deceitfully.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:13990:12"/> 2 By ſwearing to do that which they meane not to do. Pſal. 15.4.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By ſwearing to do a thing which they alſo meane to do,
<note place="margin">2. Chro. 36.13 Ezech. 17.13.14.15.</note> and is lawfull to be done, and yet after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards do it not; and this is periurie except in theſe two caſes,</p>
            <p n="1">1 If after the oath taken, God make the thing promiſed impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be done.</p>
            <p n="2">2 If the thing that men ſweare to do, be not ſimply required to be done, but either the doing of that thing or ſome other thing propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable vnto it.</p>
            <p>The higheſt degree of periurie is,
<note place="margin">Leuit. 24.11.15.16.</note> when men forſweare themſelues, in publike before a Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>The higheſt degree of vnreue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent vſing of Gods titles, is blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of them, by ſpeaking baſely, contumeliouſly, or reprochfully of any of them.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:13990:13"/>
            <p> Secondly, his Attributes are abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, when men thinke or ſpeake of them otherwiſe then beſeemes the perfect purity and holines of them, (namely) by thinking or ſpeaking of any of them raſhly and vnreuerent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or by peruerting any of them to a wrongfull vſe. And the Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes of God, that are moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly thus abuſed, are</p>
            <p n="1">1 His power, which is abuſed</p>
            <p n="1">1 Either,
<note place="margin">Exod. 5.2. Pſal. 12.4. 2. King. 18.30 34.35. 2. King. 7.2.</note> when men call the greatneſſe of it into queſtion.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or when men ſpeake of it car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, and careleſly, or contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly.</p>
            <p n="2">2 His prouidence, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, when men being vnder the hand of God, do fret and ſhew themſelues diſpleaſed, with the worke of his prouidence, and that</p>
            <p n="3">3 Either, by murmuring againſt it directly &amp; in plaine termes. Deut. 1.27.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:13990:13"/> 2 Or, by ſpeaking grudgingly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the worke of his prouidence, vnder other names, as vnder the name of <hi>Chance</hi> or <hi>Fortune.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 His iuſtice, which is abuſed,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.21. Mal. 3.13.14. Iob. 21.14.</note> when men either thinke or ſay, that God approues of ſinne or wicked ſinners.</p>
            <p n="4">4 His mercy, which is abuſed</p>
            <p n="1">1 Either, when men peruert it and miſapplie it, preſuming vpon it to harden their hearts in ſinning, Deut, 29.19.20.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or when men ſpeake baſely or contemptuouſly of Gods mercie.</p>
            <p n="5">5 His patience, which is abuſed, when on Gods patience and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance for a time to puniſh them for their ſins,
<note place="margin">Zephan. 1.12. Rom. 2.4.</note> men thinke or ſay that God will neither do good nor euill.</p>
            <p n="3">3 His works are abuſed, when men thinke or ſpeake of any of them, or vſe any of them vnreuerently and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13990:14"/>without due reſpect: and the works of God which are thus abuſed, are</p>
            <p n="1">1 Either, the wonderfull and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable workes of God, within himſelfe,
<note place="margin">Rom. 9.19.20 Rom. 11.33.</note> (namely) his eternall ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and reprobation, which are thought or ſpoken of vnreuerently, when men cauill againſt them, and ſeek to bring them within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of their ſhallow reaſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or, the outward works of God, which are thought or ſpoken of, or vſed vnreuerently, either when men ſee not God in his workes; or when they vſe them not as they ought to be vſed. And theſe workes of God that are thus abuſed, are</p>
            <p n="1">1 Either the workes of creation, the creatures of God which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed</p>
            <p n="1">1 When men thinke or ſpeake baſely of any of them,
<note place="margin">Num. 11.6. Pſal. 78.18.</note> and debaſe their goodneſſe and diſcommend them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:13990:14"/> 2 When men deride the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of God, in any of them,
<note place="margin">Gen. 21.9. 2 King. 2.23.</note> eſpecially in man or woman, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of ſome naturall defect, defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, or infirmitie of body or minde.</p>
            <p n="3">3 When men beholding any of Gods creatures,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.1. Pſal. 139.14.</note> giue not him the due praiſe and glorie of his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and power appearing in them.</p>
            <p n="4">4 When men peruert any of the creatures of God to a wrong vſe, either contrarie to, or differing from the good vſe for which God hath ordained them,
<note place="margin">Gen. 1.14. Iſai 47.13.</note> as to enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="5">5 When men ſweare by them,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 5.7.</note> eſpecially by the body of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the parts and members of his bleſſed body.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or the workes of Gods admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration &amp; prouidence; and thoſe are</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:13990:15"/> 1 Either the workes of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence that fall out and come to paſſe in the common courſe of this life,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.17.18.19. 2 Sam. 12.7.8.9.10. Iſa. 5.1.2.3.4. Mat. 21.33.34</note> which are abuſed when men haue ſuch an opinion of thoſe works which hath no ground for it either in the word of God, or in the courſe of nature; as that it is vnluckie to pul on the ſhooes awrie in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or the works of Gods mercie, his bleſſings; which are abuſed</p>
            <p n="1">1 When men receiue them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfully, and requite them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly.</p>
            <p n="2">2 When men ſweare by any worke of mercie, as by the death of <hi>Christ,</hi> or by any good gift of God, as by their faith, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The workes of Gods iuſtice, which are abuſed,
<note place="margin">Ioſh. 22.17. Luke 13.1.2.3</note> when men light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſe ouer the iudgements of God ſeene in the world.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:13990:15"/> 4 His word and his holy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, which are abuſed when men thinke or ſpeake of them or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part of them, or vſe any of them or any part of them, otherwiſe then beſeemes the holineſſe of them, and the excellent vſe of them; they being ſuch as do moſt clearely and familiarly make God himſelfe and all his goodneſſe knowne vnto vs. And this is done either generally, or particularly:</p>
            <p n="1">1 Generally.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">2. Chron. 36.16. Act. 2.13. Pſal. 5.16.17. 2. Tim. 3.7. Heb. 5.12. 2. Sam. 12.14. Ierem. 34.16. Rom. 2.24. Tit. 1.16.</note> when men vſe them vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently or ſcornfully.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when men vſe them fruitleſly, and are not bettered by them in knowledge, faith, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, when men make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of religion, and yet liue wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, when men ſhrinke in caſe of perill, and deny God the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13990:16"/>of their ſuffering for his truth.
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.33. Ioh. 12.42. Gal. 2.12.13. Mat. 7.6. Luke 22.67.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, when men profeſſe the truth of God, or ſpeake of good thing vnſeaſonably, or at times not conuenient.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Particularly, as</p>
            <p>Firſt, the word of God is abuſed, and that</p>
            <p n="1">1 When men take any part of it into their mouthes,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.11. Iſai. 22.12.13. 2 Pet. 3.4.</note> and vſe it in their ſpeech, either vnreuerently, idlely and vainly, or in mockage.</p>
            <p n="2">2 When men peruert it, or any part of it to a wrong vſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 When men vſe any part of it to curious and needleſſe queſtions.
<note place="margin">1. Tim 6.4. 1. Tim. 1.4. Tit. 1.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2
<note n="*" place="bottom">Mat. 5.39.</note> When men vſe any part of it to ieſting and prophane mirth.</p>
            <p n="3">3
<note n="*" place="bottom">Eccleſ. 3 4. 1. Tim. 5.8. Exod. 22.25. Deut. 23.19. Mark 3.5. Epheſ. 4 26. Pſal. 50.18.</note> When men vſe any part of it for the maintenance and defence of any error, hereſie, or ſinne.</p>
            <p n="4">4 When men turne any part of it to a charme or ſorcery.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:13990:16"/>
            <p> Secondly, the Sacraments, which are abuſed</p>
            <p n="1">1 By giuing that vnto them which belongs not vnto them, as</p>
            <p n="1">1 When men giue to them po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to conferre and giue grace by the verie worke wrought.
<note place="margin">Rom. 4.10.11. Epheſ. 5.26. 1. Pet. 3.21.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 When men giue to them an abſolute neceſſitie, and hold them abſolutely neceſſarie to ſaluation. Iohn 3.8.</p>
            <p n="3">3 When men giue to them ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as the Papiſts do, Mat. 4.10.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By peruerting of them and applying them to a wrong vſe, as namely to ſuch things or to ſuch vſes as God hath not appointed them, as <hi>Baptiſme</hi> to the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of bells, to driue away di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Prayer, which is abuſed</p>
            <p n="1">1 When men pray for ſuch things as are not agreable to the will of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13990:17"/>God, as for the dead, Iam. 4.3. Iohn 5.14.</p>
            <p n="2">2 When men vſe prayer to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull ends, as ſorcery, enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Hereunto is added the abuſe of the holy lot, which is an ordinance of God appointed for ſpeciall ends, &amp;c. which is abuſed</p>
            <p n="1">1 When men vſe it vnreuerent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<note place="margin">Pro. 16.33.</note> as in light and trifling matters, or in way of ſport.</p>
            <p n="2">2 When men peruert it,
<note place="margin">Pro. 18.18. 1. Sam. 10.21.</note> and vſe it to wrong ends; as to ſearch their fortune, and what ſucceſſe they ſhall haue in their affaires, by caſting a die.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The affirmatiue part of the third Commandement.</head>
               <p>It requireth a ſober,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.31.</note> religious and honorable vſage of Gods holy
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13990:17"/>name,
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.10. Num. 25.28. 1. King 19.10</note> and that in all things we giue him his due glorie, and that groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on a true zeale of Gods glorie; and ſtanding,</p>
               <p n="1">1 In yeelding due reuerence to the name of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In making a wiſe and holy confeſſion of the truth of God.</p>
               <p>Firſt, yeelding due reuerence to the name of God, and that either in ſpeech or action.</p>
               <p>In ſpeech, which is,
<note place="margin">Pro. 31.26. Pſal. 71.15.</note> when men hauing occaſion to vſe the name of God, do wiſely make mention of it, and reuerently, and to good vſe and edification; and that either without an oath, or in the lawfull vſe of an oath.</p>
               <p>Without an oath, which is to be expreſſed in ſpeaking of his holy ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles; which is,
<note place="margin">Deut. 28.58. Rom. 9.5.</note> when men vſe them in their ſpeech, onely in ſerious mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and with feare and trembling,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13990:18"/>and to the good of men, and praiſe of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Of his attributes,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.9.10. Pſal. 66.16. Pſal. 107.8.</note> when men break forth into ſuch a declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gods power, wiſedom, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp;c. as both themſelues and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are, or may be thereby ſtirred vp to magnifie thoſe holy attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, and more earneſtly to praiſe God for the ſame.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Of his word and the parts of his worſhip;
<note place="margin">Deut. 6.7. Pſal. 37.30.31 Pro. 10.21.</note> which is, when men ſpeake of them with ſuch care and reuerence as beſeems the holineſſe and excellency of them, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them onely to thoſe good vſes for which God hath ordained them.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Of his workes,
<note place="margin">Exod. 15.1. to 23. Pſal. 136. wholl. Pſal. 145.17.20.21.</note> which is, when men ſpeake of them, of what ſort or kind ſoeuer they be, with reuerence and with an approbation of the good and excellencie of them, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13990:18"/>do giue God the due praiſe of his wiſedome, power, and goodneſſe, appearing in the ſame.</p>
               <p>In the lawfull vſe of an oath, which is, when men ſweare by the name of God, hauing a lawfull cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thereunto, and do it lawfully.</p>
               <p>And men haue a lawfull calling to ſweare,</p>
               <p n="1">1 When the Magiſtrate vpon a iuſt occaſion doth require an oath by the order of iuſtice,
<note place="margin">Gen. 43.3. 1. Sam. 24.22.23.</note> and doth miniſter the ſame lawfully, ſo as it be not againſt pietie or charitie.</p>
               <p n="2">2 When their owne calling, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall or particular, neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires an oath; as (namely)</p>
               <p n="1">1 When the taking of an oath, may further Gods glorie and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<note place="margin">Gal. 1.20. 1. Theſſ. 2.5.</note> or may ſerue to proue ſome doctrine of ſaluation in whole or in part.</p>
               <p n="2">2 When the taking of an oath,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13990:19"/>ſerues to maintaine and further a mans owne or others ſaluation,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.23. Pſal. 119.106.</note> in ſoule or in body.</p>
               <p n="3">3 When the taking of an oath ſerues to further brotherly loue,
<note place="margin">Gen. 21.23.24 Gen. 31.53.</note> and to confirme lawful peace and ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie betweene party and partie, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and countrey.</p>
               <p n="4">4 When a man by an oath, and not otherwiſe,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1 9. 1. Theſſ. 2.10.</note> may maintaine his own good name, and life, or goods.</p>
               <p>And that men may ſweare law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,
<note place="margin">Gal. 1.20. 2. Cor. 1.23.</note> they muſt know that an oath is</p>
               <p>A calling of God to witneſſe for the neceſſarie confirmation, either of the vnknowne truth of their ſpeech touching things of great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, or the truth of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe they make to do ſome thing or things that are of weight likewiſe, and lawfull, and poſſible; and a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing God to puniſh them, if either they lye, or wittingly and willingly do otherwiſe then they promiſe:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13990:19"/>and it is either</p>
               <p>An affirming oath,</p>
               <p>Or a promiſing oath.</p>
               <p>And they muſt looke that they ſweare,</p>
               <p n="1">1 In truth,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 4.2.</note> which implyeth</p>
               <p n="1">1 That the thing they ſweare vnto, be a truth, and that they know it ſo to be, or at leaſt thinke it ſo, and be perſwaded in conſcience that it is a truth.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That they ſwere ſimply &amp; plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without fraud or deceit,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.4. Pſal. 24.4.</note> nor ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one thing, &amp; meaning another.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In iudgement, which is with deliberation and due conſideration of the nature and greatneſſe of an oath, and of the matter they ſweare vnto,
<note place="margin">Exod. 22.11. Deut. 6.13.</note> and of the particular circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, of time, place, and perſons, before whom they ſweare; and in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the oath, that they haue a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent care and feare of Gods Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:13990:20"/> 3 In righteouſneſſe, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth,</p>
               <p n="1">1 That the thing they ſweare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.22.</note> be iuſtand lawfull.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That their calling to ſweare be iuſt and warrantable.</p>
               <p n="3">3 That their ſwearing be dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to a right end, (namely) to Gods glory, and peace among men. Heb. 6.16.</p>
               <p>Here added, that an oath taken touching things certaine, lawfull, &amp; poſſible, bindeth the conſcience, though it be taken by creatures or by falſe gods; and againe, that an oath may lawfully be broken in ſixe caſes.</p>
               <p>Men yeeld due reuerence to the name of God in <hi>Action;</hi> which is when the actions of men tend to the glory of God,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.31. Coloſſ. 3.17.</note> and whatſoeuer they do, they do it to that end prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally that God may be glorified; &amp;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13990:20"/>that either in generall, or particular.</p>
               <p>In generall,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.16. 1. Pet. 2.12. Reuel. 2.13.</note> as (namely) when they liue ſo holily and ſo behaue themſelues, as that in their whole conuerſation they bring glorie to Gods name.</p>
               <p>Or in particular, and that</p>
               <p n="1">1 When the power and fruite of the word of God,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.105. Luk. 8.15.</note> and other meanes of ſaluation, is expreſſed in their particular actions as occaſion is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered.</p>
               <p n="2">2 When men do ſanctifie Gods bleſſings, chaſtiſements,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.5.</note> and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and the workes of their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, by the word of God, and prayer.</p>
               <p>By the word of God, by taking inſtruction from thence touching the lawfull vſe of them,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.24.</note> and how to vſe them after an holy manner.</p>
               <p>By prayer, (namely)</p>
               <p n="1">1 By petition, crauing aſſiſtance
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13990:21"/>of Gods grace,
<note place="margin">Gen. 24.12. 2. Chro. 16.12 Ioh. 6.11. Act. 27.35. Act. 21.5.</note> and his bleſſing in the lawful vſe of his bleſſings, &amp;c. as particular occaſion is offered.</p>
               <p n="2">2 By thankſegiuing, magnifying the name of the Lord,
<note place="margin">Gen. 24.27. Deut. 8.10. Exod. 18 10. 2. Sam. 22.</note> and retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thanks to him for his grace, ayde and bleſſing vouchſafed in the lawfull vſe of his bleſſings, &amp;c. as particular occaſion is likewiſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in making a wiſe and holy confeſſion of the truth of God,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 44.5. Mat. 10.32.33 Mar. 8.38.</note> which is to confeſſe the whole truth of God and his religion plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, boldly and religiouſly, when and whereſoeuer any iuſt occaſion is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered; and that either by word or practiſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.10. 1. Pet. 3.15.16</note> By word, (namely) by <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an apologie,</hi> which is, when men are ready to confeſſe the truth of God and his religion, and do indeed with feare and meekneſſe confeſſe it ſo
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13990:21"/>often as on iuſt cauſe they are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto required.</p>
               <p n="1">1
<note place="margin">Pſal. 22.22. 1. Theſſ. 5.11.</note> Either in publike by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, or in priuate by friends, pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceably and without violence.</p>
               <p n="2">2
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.18.19 Act. 5.27.28. Act. 26.</note> Or are thereunto drawne by violence of the enemies and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of the Church of God, and that before malicious enemies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereunto called, and ſeeing Gods glorie endangered, and his truth ſpoken againſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2 By practiſe, and that</p>
               <p n="1">1
<note place="margin">Dan. 6.10.11. Gen. 12.7.8. Gen. 21.33.</note> By ſhewing forth the truth of religion by practiſe, though it be with danger to loſe their liues for it.</p>
               <p n="2">2 By witneſſing and ſealing the doctrine of faith and truth of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<note place="margin">Act. 7.58.59. Act 22.20. Heb. 11.37. Reuel. 2.13.</note> by their cheerfull ſuffering, yea by ſhedding their bloud without feare or ſhrinking, being thereunto called; which is knowne</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:13990:22"/>
               <p> Firſt, by finding that God puts into them the ſpirit of courage, and giues them reſolution to abide and to ſtand out againſt the force of all the enemies of the truth.</p>
               <p>Secondly, if being in the hands of the Magiſtrate, and God cutting off all lawful means of eſcaping, the Magiſtrate do then inflict on them tortures and torments, and do take away their liues for the truths ſake, though vniuſtly.</p>
               <p>Thus much concerning the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue and affirmatiue parts of the Commandement; now followeth the commination or threatning.</p>
               <p>The commination or threatning denounced againſt the breakers of it,</p>
               <p>Including:</p>
               <p n="1">1 The greatneſſe of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that ſhall be inflicted on the offenders againſt this commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:13990:22"/> 2 The ineuitableneſſe of it.
<note place="margin">Nahum. 1.3.6. 1. Sam. 2.25.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And containing in effect thus much; that howſoeuer mans law for the moſt part takes not hold of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders againſt this commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.5.</note>
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 23.10. Zach. 5.3.4.</note> and they eſcape puniſhment amongſt men; yet God will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite them, nor ſuffer them to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape his iuſt and fearefull iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe his exact iuſtice can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not let ſo hainous a ſinne eſcape vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed, as is the prophanation of his name; which is moſt hainous,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 42.8. Iſai. 48.11.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 Becauſe Gods glorie is the laſt and principall, and for which all things were ordained, and is moſt deare to himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Becauſe in prophaning Gods name, men ſhew moſt inſolent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Becauſe God appointed in the iudiciall law, not onely the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer himſelfe to be puniſhed by
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13990:23"/>death,
<note place="margin">Leuit. 24.14. Leuit. 5.1.</note> but alſo euery perſon that ſhould heare blaſphemy or a falſe oath, and not reueale it.</p>
               <trailer>The end of the third Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="commandment">
            <head>The fourth Commandment. <hi>The affirmatiue part.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The fourth Commandement is partly ceremoniall, and partly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and perpetuall.</p>
            <p n="1">1 It is ceremoniall, and that in reſpect</p>
            <p n="1">1 Of the ſtrict reſt which the Iewes were commanded to keepe on the Sabbath,
<note place="margin">Exod. 31.13.</note> ſtanding in theſe things:</p>
            <p>That they might not prepare or dreſſe that which they ſhould eate.
<note place="margin">Exod. 16.23.29. Exod 35.3. Num. 15.32. &amp;c.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Not kindle a fire.</p>
            <p>Nor take a iourney any whither
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13990:23"/>for any matter or buſineſſe of their owne on the Sabbath.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Of this,
<note place="margin">Deut. 5.15.</note> that the Iewes were to keepe the Sabbath as a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of their deliuerance out of Egypt.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Of this,
<note place="margin">Deut. 5.14. Exod. 31.17. Num. 28.9.10</note> that the Iewes were to obſerue and keepe the ſeuenth day from the creation, and that with ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices and ceremonies proper to that day.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It is morall and perpetuall, and that in two reſpects, as</p>
            <p n="1">1
<note place="margin">Iſai. 58.13.</note> In that it requires a certaine ſeuenth day to be kept as a day of holy reſt for the preſeruation of the Miniſtery of the word.</p>
            <p n="2">2
<note place="margin">Exod. 23.12.</note> In that it freeth all from bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly labours, and eſpecially ſeruants and cattell.</p>
            <p>As it is morall it requireth an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſt vnto God on the ſeuenth day in euery weeke,
<note place="margin">Exod. 16.23. Exod. 35.2.</note> called the Sabbath
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13990:24"/>or the Lords day; &amp; to the keeping of that holy reſt we are to prepare our ſelues by thinking on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath before it come,
<note place="margin">Luke 23.54.</note> and ſo diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of our ſelues and affaires, that we may freely and duly attend on the duties of it when it is come; and by riſing early in the morning on the Sabbath, &amp; fitting our ſelues for the performance of publike duties, by taking account of our harts &amp; liues. And the keeping of that holy reſt vnto God, ſtandeth in doing the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Sabbath with reuerence,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 58.13. Deut. 33.3.</note> as before the Lord of heauen and earth, and with cheerefulneſſe and delight, both in publike and in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate: and the publike duties are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther workes of pietie, or workes of mercy.</p>
            <p>Workes of pietie (namely) ſuch ſpirituall workes as tend to the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne &amp; publike worſhip of God;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13990:24"/>which are,</p>
            <p n="1">1
<note place="margin">Nehem. 8.3.8 Luke. 4.16. to 22. Act. 13.14.15.16. Act. 20.7. Act. 2.42. Act. 16.13. Pſal. 92. in ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulo. 1. Cor. 14.15.16. Coloſſ. 3.16.</note> A reuerent and attentiue hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the word of God, purely and faithfully preached or read in the publike aſſembly.</p>
            <p n="2">2 A ioyning with the Miniſter and congregation publikely aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, with aſſent of minde and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent affection of heart, in publike prayer and calling on the name of the Lord, and in thankeſgiuing and ſinging of Pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A reuerent, and frequent and often communicating in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<note place="margin">Act. 20.7. 1. Cor. 11.20.</note> publikely adminiſtred by the Miniſters of the Church lawfully called.</p>
            <p>Works of mercy, which are theſe: Collection is to be made for the poore,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 16.1.2 Rom. 15.26. 2. Cor. 8.3.4.</note> and almes is to be giuen for the reliefe of the poore, whether they be ſuch as dwell among vs, or thoſe that be captiues and ſtrangers.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:13990:25"/>
            <p> The priuate duties to be done on the Sabbath, are alſo either workes of pietie, or works of mercie.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Workes of pietie, (namely) ſuch as tend to the further edifying and building vp of our ſelues and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in knowledge, and in grace, &amp; holineſſe; and they are</p>
            <p n="1">1
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.11.97. Luke 2.51.</note> A due and ſerious meditation on the word of God which we haue heard in publike, labouring to apply it in euery part of it particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to our ſelues.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Examination and holy confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
<note place="margin">Act. 17.11. Mar. 4.33.34. Deut. 6.7.</note> that we call to mind, and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine things deliuered in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like miniſtery of the word, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre of them with our families and others.</p>
            <p n="3">3
<note place="margin">Iohn 17.17. 1. Cor. 3.6.7. Iam. 1.5.</note> Priuate prayer, that we priuat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pray to the Lord and craue a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing on his ordinances we haue bene made partakers of, and giue
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:13990:25"/>him thankes for the good we haue receiued by them.
<note place="margin">Act. 16.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4
<note place="margin">Deu. 17.19. Ioh 5.39. Reuel. 1.3.</note> Priuate reading of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p n="5">5
<note place="margin">Iſai. 58.13. Exod. 15.12. Iam. 5.13.</note> Singing of Pſalmes to the praiſe of God, and to the ſtirring vp of ſpirituall ioy and chearefulneſſe in our hearts.</p>
            <p n="6">6
<note place="margin">Pſal. 92.4.5.6.</note> Meditation and due conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the workes of God, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally his workes of mercie.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Workes of mercie, (namely) ſuch duties of loue as concerne either,</p>
            <p n="1">1 The good of the ſoules of our brethren; as that we within com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of our callings, and according to the meaſure of grace and gifts,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.10. 1. Theſſ. 5.11.14.</note> do inſtruct, exhort, admoniſh, reproue and comfort thoſe that be about vs, and others, as iuſt occaſion is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The good of the bodies of our
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13990:26"/>brethren;
<note place="margin">Nehem. 8.12. Mar. 3.3.4.5. Luke 13.10. to 18. Ioh. 5.8.9. &amp; 9.14.</note> as that we viſite the ſicke, and do them what good we can, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the poore and needy, and ſuch as be in priſon, or in any other miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, according to our abilitie.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Or ſuch as concerne the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward peace of our brethren; as that we endeuour to preſerue the good name of our brethren,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.9. 1. Cor. 6.5.6.</note> and labour to reconcile ſuch as be at variance and diſcord among themſelues.</p>
            <p>The Negatiue part containes a prohibition, and the extent of the prohibition.</p>
            <p>A prohibition, which forbids the doing of ſuch things or workes as do any way hinder the keeping of an holy reſt vnto God on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath:
<note place="margin">Ierem. 17.24.</note> and thoſe workes are either workes of profite, or works of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>Workes of profite (namely) the common labours of our ordinarie
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13990:26"/>ſallings and courſe of life; and thoſe are,</p>
            <p n="1">1 Either ſuch as are vſuall in the ſixe dayes of the weeke.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or ſuch as are vſuall at certaine peciall times in the yeare or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth.</p>
            <p>Such as are vſuall in the ſixe dayes of the weeke, which hinder the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of an holy reſt vnto God on the Sabbath three wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1 When vpon the Sabbath our minds and hearts are taken vp with thoughts and cares about our ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie worldly works and buſineſſes,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 58.13. Luke. 8.14.</note> we are thinking of them, plotting and caſting how, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2 When on the Sabbath,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 58.13. Amos 8.4.5.</note> we are talking and ſpeaking of our ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry worldly works and buſineſſes, in making bargaines, reckening with ſeruants, with labourers, and worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:13990:27"/> 3 When on the Sabbath we do our ordinarie worldly workes and buſineſſes,
<note place="margin">Exod. 16.28.29. Exod. 31.14. Nehem. 13.15.17. Ierem. 17.22. Mar. 16.1.</note> in whole or in part, be it neuer ſo little a part of them, as ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forward any of our worldly workes againſt the day following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exception.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet ſome workes may be done on the Sabbath, and not hinder the keeping of an holy reſt vnto God on that day, (namely) theſe</p>
            <p n="1">1 Workes that concerne the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe &amp; performance of the publike duties on the Sabbath,
<note place="margin">Act. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. 2. King. 4.23. Mat. 12.5.</note> as (namely) ſuch as are neceſſarily to be done in and about the publike worſhip of God, and the actions of piety belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to that day, as</p>
            <p n="1">1 The Sabbath dayes iourney to heare or to Preach the word of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſounding of trumpets or bells and ſuch like, for the gathering
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13990:27"/>of the people together at a certaine time.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Workes of preſent neceſſitie,
<note place="margin">Act. 20.9.10.</note> (namely) ſuch workes as concerne the immediate preſeruation of the temporall life or liuelihood of man or beaſt, or that ſerue to the good eſtate of either of them; and that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ordinarie caſes, or in ſuch as fall out extraordinarily.</p>
            <p>And preſent neceſſitie is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That which men contract and draw on themſelues, as (namely) when men out of a couetous minde take on them more buſineſſe in their calling then they can diſpatch in the ſixe dayes of the weeke; or for want of wiſe and well ordering their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines, it being ſuch as if they would, might be done the day before, or the day following; or when through negligence or forgetfulneſſe, they
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:13990:28"/>bring on themſelues ſome ordinary buſineſſe; in this kinde of neceſſity men ought not to labour on the Sabbath.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That which is layd on them by the immediate hand and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, as (namely) when not through any neglect, ouerſight or other corruption of their owne, but by the immediat prouidence of God, ſome buſineſſe of their ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry calling is laid on them, which could not be done the day before, neither can be left vndone till the day after; in this kind of neceſſitie men may labour on the Sabbath, theſe cautions obſerued,</p>
            <p n="1">1 That their labour be with as little hinderance of them from pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like holy exerciſes, as poſſibly may be.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That in labouring, their minds be exerciſed in holy meditations.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:13990:28"/> 3 That they make not their work a work of gaine,
<note place="margin">1. King. 19.8. 1. King. 20.29. Mat. 12.7.</note> but a work of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, or tending to a work of mercie.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That it ſerue to the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate preſeruation of life, health, or goods.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Workes of Chriſtian libertie, (namely) ſuch workes as did belong to the ſtrict reſt which the Iewes were commanded to keepe on the Sabbath,
<note place="margin">Mar. 2.27. Mat. 12.1.2.3. Luk. 6.5.</note> and ſuch as they might not do, and yet we may do now vnder the new Teſtament, as the dreſſing of neceſſarie food, making of fiers, making of beds; which may be done on the Sabbath, and not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the keeping of an holy reſt, two rules obſerued.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That they be done without hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the doers of them at the leaſt ordinarily from the publike holy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, as when they are done in the time before, or after, or betweene
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13990:29"/>the publike exerciſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2 When the doers of them haue their minds exerciſed with holy and heauenly meditations.
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 23.15.16.17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Workes of pleaſure, which are either lawful in themſelues, and ſuch as at other times may be vſed: or ſimply in themſelues vnlawfull at all times.</p>
            <p>Workes of pleaſure lawfull in themſelues, and ſuch as at other times may be vſed, which are,</p>
            <p n="1">1 Either ſet &amp; ſolemne feaſting and banquetting,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 5.12. Luk. 21.34.36</note> as at mariages.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or ſome kinde of recreations and exerciſes of the body.</p>
            <p>Set and ſolemne feaſting and banquetting at mariages, which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the keeping of an holy reſt on the Sabbath:</p>
            <p>When they are vſed on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, &amp; thereby Cookes, and other officers are imployed in their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:13990:29"/>workes, and are toyled excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly; and thoſe that do feaſt and banquet, are hindered, &amp; haue their minds withdrawne from the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous performance of holy duties both publike and priuate.</p>
            <p>Some kinde of recreations and exerciſes of the body, (namely) ſuch moderate mouings of the body as be honeſt, and carrie with them an honeſt and delightſome exerciſe of the minde,
<note place="margin">Exod. 22.6.</note> and ſerue to the refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing both of body and minde, as ſhooting &amp;c. which hinder the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of an holy reſt on the Sabbath, when they are vſed on the Sabbath, eſpecially at the time of diuine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Becauſe labour in a mans law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full calling, which is more neceſſary and profitable, is forbidden on the Sabbath.</p>
            <p>Therefore recreation which is
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13990:30"/>for labour, and leſſe neceſſarie, though lawfull at other times, muſt then ceaſſe, when labour ceaſſeth.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Labour in a mans lawfull cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is forbidden on the Sabbath; becauſe it hinders the keeping of an holy reſt to God on the Sabbath: therefore recreation though lawfull at other times, is not to be vſed on the Sabbath, it being no leſſe but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more an hinderance to the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of an holy reſt vnto God on the Sabbath, then bodily labour.</p>
            <p>Workes of pleaſure, ſimply in themſelues vnlawful at all times, are either,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Knowne ſinnes, as ſurfetting, drunkenneſſe,
<note place="margin">Iſai 56.2. Ezech. 23.38.39. Rom. 13.13.</note> whore dome and ſuch like, which hinder the keeping of the holy reſt on the Sabbath when they are done on the Sabbath; for then to commit any knowne ſin is to keepe an holy day to the diuell,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:13990:30"/>and not to God.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or ſuch as go vnder the name of ſports and recreations, as (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) ſuch delights as haue a manifeſt defiling of good manners in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or in the beholding, hauing in them allurement and prouocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The extent of the prohibition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is extended to all men and women of yeares and diſcretion,
<note place="margin">Deut. 5.14.</note> of what place, calling or condition ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in the world; and to all other things that may be ſet on worke by them;
<note place="margin">Deut. 22.4.</note> eſpecially the charge is layd on ſuch as be ſuperiours and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, whether in priuate or in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, as namely,</p>
            <p n="1">1 A maiſter or gouernour of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily is bound to ceaſſe from doing ſuch things and works as do hinder the keeping of an holy reſt to God on the Sabbath, not onely in his
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:13990:31"/>owne perſon, but in all that be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him; he is to looke to all others that be vnder his charge, yea euen to ſtrangers and gueſts that on the Sabbath be within his libertie and power.</p>
            <p n="2">2 A gouernor in publike, a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate is bound to ceaſſe from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch things and works as do hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the keeping of an holy reſt to God on the Sabbath, not onely in his owne perſon, but in all that be vnder his gouernment: he muſt looke to all others, yea to ſtrangers that be within his libertie and iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction on the Sabbath, that they alſo ceaſſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And maiſters and Magiſtrates muſt reſtraine ſuch as be vnder them, or ſtrangers being within their libertie on the Sabbath, from works of profite, and works of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, by</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:13990:31"/>
            <p> Commandement, admonition, reproof, if theſe will ſerue the turne; if not, by correction and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A child alſo of yeares and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion,
<note place="margin">Exod. 35.2. Ezech. 20.20.21.</note> and a ſeruant is bound on the Sabbath to ceaſſe from workes of pleaſure altogether, and from workes of profite alſo altogether, both in reſpect of his owne profite, or the profite of his parents, or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours: vnleſſe it be in a caſe of preſent neceſſity coming by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate hand and prouidence of God; for then the child or ſeruant may worke, the cautions before na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med being obſerued.</p>
            <p>Here added,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 92.2.</note> that the Sabbath containes twentie-foure houres as well as any other naturall day.</p>
            <p>And that the Sabbath begins at midnight on Saturday, and endeth at midnight next following.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:13990:32"/>
            <p> Reaſons annexed to the fourth Commandment, perſwading to the obedience of it, are foure.</p>
            <p n="1">1 From the Lords liberall allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of ſixe dayes for our owne workes and buſineſſes,
<note place="margin">Exod. 20.9.</note> that in equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie we are bound to ceaſſe from our owne workes on the Sabbath, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord ſo largely imparteth ſixe dayes of the ſeuen to vs, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth but one to himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 From the Lords owne right, that the ſeuenth day is his day,
<note place="margin">Exod. 20.10.</note> and not ours, and that he hath ſet it apart to himſelfe and to his owne ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.</p>
            <p n="3">3 From the Lords owne exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and practiſe,
<note place="margin">Exod. 20.11.</note> that he himſelfe on the ſeuenth day reſted from his worke of creation.</p>
            <p n="4">4 From the hope of bleſſing, that the Lord hath ſet apart the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,
<note place="margin">Exod. 20.11.</note> not only as a day of ſeruice to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:13990:32"/>himſelfe, but alſo as a time and meanes of bleſſing to all that care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and conſcionably obſerue it.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="commandment">
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:13990:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The fift Commandment. <hi>The affirmatiue part.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The fift Commandement con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines a precept,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Honour thy father and thy mother;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And a confirmation of it, by a promiſe made to ſuch as yeeld obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to it, in theſe words,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That thy dayes may be long in the Land, which the Lord thy God giueth thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The precept requires all due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and all due cariage of inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours towards their ſuperiours; and by neceſſarie conſequence, of ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours alſo towards their inferiours, and of equalls among themſelues; and that either in generall or parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in generall, as of inferiours,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:13990:33"/>towards their ſuperiors, ſtanding in two things,</p>
            <p n="1">1 In yeelding to them reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In a care and endeuour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue well of them.</p>
            <p>In yeelding to them reuerence, and that inward and outward:</p>
            <p n="1">1 Inward reuerence,
<note place="margin">Leuit. 19.3. 1. Sam. 10.26. Rom. 13.1.2. Epheſ. 6.5.</note> (namely) a reuerent opinion and eſtimation of them; that they thinke and eſteeme of them reuerently in regard of Gods ordinance, in ſetting them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them, and becauſe they beare Gods image.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Outward reuerence,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 1.15. Leuit. 19.32. Gen. 18.2. Mar. 10.17. Exod. 18.13. 1. King. 2.19.</note> (namely) a manifeſtation of their inward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, both by word and deed, both by reuerent ſpeeches, and by reuerent behauiour; as by riſing vp before them, by baring the head, by bowing the knee, and ſuch like. In a care and endeuour to deſerue
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:13990:34"/>well of them, ſtanding in yeelding two things vnto them:
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Obedience.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Thankfulneſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Obedience, which is a willing ſubmitting of themſelues to their lawfull Commandements,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.13.14 Heb. 13.17. Pro. 15.5.</note> and counſells, and to their admonitions and reproofes, and corrections.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In thankefulneſſe, which is not onely a thankfull acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their goodneſſe towards them in word;
<note place="margin">Gen. 4.7.25. 1 Tim. 5.4.17</note> but an indeuour alſo to requite them by doing good to them; againe and that two waies,</p>
            <p n="1">1 By yeelding them their helpe in outward things, if they ſtand in need of it. Rom. 13.6.7. Galat. 6.6.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.1.2.</note> By praying for them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, of ſuperiours towards their inferiours, ſtanding</p>
            <p n="1">1 Either in yeelding that which is due from them, to all that are any
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:13990:34"/>way inferiour vnto them, in age, place or gifts. And the things that are due from them to ſuch inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, are,</p>
            <p n="1">1 To go before them in an holy conuerſation and good example,
<note place="margin">Iob. 29.7.8. Philip. 3.17. Tit. 2.7. 1. Pet. 5.3.</note> ſhewing forth all grauity according to their place, by their countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, geſtures, wordes and deeds.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In meekeneſſe of ſpirit,
<note place="margin">Deut. 17.20. 2. King. 5.13.14.</note> to yeeld to them in good things, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting them as their brethren.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Keeping and maintaining their ſtate and place:
<note place="margin">Iob. 31.13. Rom. 14.3.</note> to be afraid to wrong or deſpiſe the meaneſt or their inferiours.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or in yeelding that which is due from them towards ſuch as are inferiours to them, more eſpecially in reſpect of place, and are vnder their power and gouernment; and the things that are due from them to ſuch inferiours are.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:13990:35"/> 1 To rule them in the Lord, and to endeauour that God may be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by all that are vnder their gouernment.
<note place="margin">Deut. 17.19. 1. Sam. 2.30. 2. King. 23.1.2.3.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 To ſeeke their good, the good of their bodies,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.4. Iſai 49.23. Num. 11.12. Gen. 19.18. Gen. 9.26.27. Heb. 11.20.</note> and the good of their ſoules, by prouiding good things for them, by protecting and ſupporting them; by giuing them good inſtructions, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and counſells, by praying for them and bleſſing them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the power they receiue from God.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In wiſedome and diſcretion, to vſe their authority ouer them,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 101.6.7. Rom. 13.3.4.</note> to the fauouring, countenancing, and rewarding the good and ſuch as do well; and to the diſcountenancing and puniſhing the bad and euill do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, according to their faults and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Thirdly, of <hi>Equalls</hi> among
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:13990:35"/>themſelues, ſtanding in a modeſt preferring each other before them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, both in opinion and practiſe.
<note place="margin">Philip. 2.3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In particular, according to the relation of certaine perſons, either of ſuperioritie or of inferioritie: and that either in priuate, as in the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; or in publike, as in the <hi>Church or Common-wealth:</hi> of theſe ſeuerally.</p>
            <p>Priuate in the family, which is,</p>
            <p n="1">1 Either naturall betweene pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and children.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or by calling and condition, as betweene the husband and the wife, or betweene the maiſter and the ſeruant.</p>
            <p>The due reſpect and due carriage of children towards their parents ſtands in yeelding to them, 1 <hi>Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</hi> 2 <hi>Obedience.</hi> 3 <hi>Thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reuerence: Inward both in heart and minde, reuerencing them by
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:13990:36"/>thinking and eſteeming reuerently of them,
<note place="margin">Leuit. 19.3. Malac. 1.6. Heb. 12.9.</note> by louing them and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them, in regard of their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie ouer them, and of Gods image which they beare as they be parents be they neuer ſo meane or poore.</p>
            <p>Outward, declaring their inward reuerence of them, by their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward reuerent behauiour towards them, both in their wordes and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures.</p>
            <p>Obedience, (namely) a willing and hearty yeelding, ſo farre as they are able, to the voice and wil of their parents:</p>
            <p>Standing,</p>
            <p n="1">1 In a cheerfull yeelding ſo farre as they are able,
<note place="margin">Gen. 24.15. Pro. 1.8. Epheſ. 6.1. Coloſſ 3.20. 1. Sam. 2.25.</note> to theſe things which their parents teach or counſel or command, being things honeſt and lawful, though neuer ſo baſe or painfull.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In a quiet and patient ſuffering
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:13990:36"/>of that which their parents do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict and lay on them in word or deed, be it admonition, reproofe,
<note place="margin">Pro. 13.1. Pro. 15.5. Heb. 12.9.</note> or correction:</p>
            <p>Expreſſed in two things,</p>
            <p n="1">1 In the choice of a fit and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full calling,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 8.1. Mar. 6 3.</note> children are to be dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted therein at the diſcretion of their parents.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In being ordered and diſpoſed of by their parents in marriage. Deut. 7.3. Ierem. 29.6.1. Cor. 7.38. Gen. 21.21. Gen. 24.3.4. Iudg. 14.1.2.</p>
            <p>Thankefulneſſe ſtanding,</p>
            <p n="1">1 In yeelding a comfort to them by their honeſt and good carriage.
<note place="margin">Pro. 10.1. &amp; 15.20. Pro. 23.15.16 Gen. 47.12. Rut. 2.18.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 In ſuccouring and releeuing them in caſe of want.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In praying for them. 1. Tim. 1.2.</p>
            <p n="4">4 In comforting them as they are able in time of their ſickeneſſe,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:13990:37"/>and in committing their bodies to the graue being dead,
<note place="margin">Gen. 48.1. Gen. 25.9. Gen. 35.29. Gen. 50.12.13</note> after an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and ſeemely manner.</p>
            <p>The due reſpect and due carriage of parents towards their children,
<note place="margin">Parents.</note> ſtands in bringing vp their children, and in a wife diſpoſing of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought vp.</p>
            <p>And touching education, they are to be carefull that their children may liue; expreſſing that care,</p>
            <p n="1">1 In yeelding to them (according to their abilitie) ſuch competent food and cloathing,
<note place="margin">Mat. 7.9.10. 1. Tim. 5.8.10</note> and other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, as be fit for them, &amp; agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their age.</p>
            <p n="2">2 As God giueth them abilitie, by diligence in their callings, and a carefull vſe of all good and lawfull meanes,
<note place="margin">1. King. 21.3. Pro. 19.14. 2. Cor. 12.14.</note> and a wiſe ordering of their expences, in prouiding and laying vp ſome thing for the maintenance of their children in time to come; ſo
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:13990:37"/>as they pinch not themſelues in things neceſſarie, nor neglect the doing of that good they are bound to do, to the <hi>Church, Common-wealth or poore;</hi> and wiſely ordering and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of things prouided for the good of their children, by</p>
            <p>Diſpoſing them by wil,
<note place="margin">Gen. 25.5.6. Iſai. 38.1. Num. 28.7.8.</note> or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe as ſhall be thought fit, in their life time.</p>
            <p>And that children may liue wel, expreſſing that care,</p>
            <p n="1">1 In being carefull that their children newly borne may with all conuenient ſpeed and in due order be admitted into the true viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Church</hi> of God by Baptiſme,
<note place="margin">Gen. 21.3.4. Luk. 1.59.60.61. Luk. 2.21.</note> and haue fit names giuen to them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Not onely in teaching them ciuilitie and good manners,
<note place="margin">Deut. 4.10. Deut. 6.7.20.21. Deut. 11.19.</note> and in trayning them vp in learning and humane knowledge, and humane
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:13990:38"/>affaires,
<note place="margin">Pro. 22.6. Epheſ. 6.4. 2. Tim. 3.15.</note> but inſtructing them alſo in Religion, and endeuouring to ſow the ſeeds of godlines in their hearts, ſo ſoone as they are able to ſpeake and come to the vſe of reaſon and vnderſtanding, and endeauouring that as they grow in yeares, ſo they may grow and increaſe in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In checking and rebuking them when they do offend and do amiſſe,
<note place="margin">1. King. 1.6. Pro. 13.24. Pro. 19.18. Pro. 23.13.14. Heb. 12.7 9.</note> &amp; in words reprouing them diſcreetly, if that wil ſerue the turne; if not, in giuing them ſeaſonable, due and moderate correction.</p>
            <p n="4">4 In praying for their good,
<note place="margin">Gen. 28.1. Gen. 48.15.16 1. Chron. 29.19. Iob. 1.5. 2. Sam. 12.16.</note> and for the bleſſing of God on their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and on their ſoules.</p>
            <p>In a wiſe diſpoſing of them being brought vp, ſtanding,</p>
            <p n="1">1 In the choice of a fit and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full calling,
<note place="margin">Gen. 4.2. Gen. 46.34. Gen. 47.3.</note> and courſe of life for them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:13990:38"/> 2 Knowing them to be marriage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,
<note place="margin">Gen. 21.21. Gen. 24 3.4. Gen. 28.1.2. Gen. 38.6. Ierem. 29.6. 1. Cor. 7.36. Pro. 31.30. Eccleſ 7.13.</note> and not to haue the gift of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinencie, in vſing their beſt endeuor to prouide fit matches for them in time, or at leaſt aduiſing them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by themſelues or by their friends, and therein to haue a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all reſpect to wiſedome and pietie.</p>
            <p>The due reſpect and due carriage of the wife towards her husband, ſtandeth in yeelding to him <hi>ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, loyaltie,</hi> and <hi>faithfull loue, helpe</hi> and <hi>comfort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Subiection</hi> (namely) an humble ready and willing yeelding and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of her ſelfe to the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of her husband,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.16. Rom 7.2. Epheſ. 5.22.23.24. Coloſſ. 3.18.</note> ſtanding in yeelding to him reuerence inward and outward, and obedience.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Inward reuerence (namely) in carrying in her minde a reuerent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion &amp; eſtimation of him,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.23. 1. Pet. 3.2.</note> think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reuerently of him, and carrying
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:13990:39"/>in her heart a reuerent awe and feare to offend him in any thing, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging him as her head, though he be neuer ſo poore or meane in the world.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Outward reuerence, (namely) a manifeſtation of her inward reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
<note place="margin">Gen 18.12. 1. Pet. 3.6. 1. Tim. 2.6.10 11.12.</note> by outward meekneſſe and lowlineſſe, expreſſed in her ſpeech; giuing him reuerent titles &amp; terms, and in her countenance, and in all her behauiour towards him.</p>
            <p>Obedience, willingly yeelding her ſelfe to be commanded,
<note place="margin">Gen. 12.5. Gen. 13.1. Gen. 31.4. to 17. 2. King 4.22. 1. Pet. 3.6.</note> gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and directed by him in all things honeſt and lawfull, though they be neuer ſo croſſe and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to her owne minde; according to her abilitie doing what he giues in charge to be done, and forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to do that which he forbids.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Loyaltie, and faithfull loue, (namely) a conſtant keeping of the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:13990:39"/>marriage couenant made with him,
<note place="margin">Pro. 2.17. Pro. 31.12. Rom. 7.2. Tit. 2.4.</note> and a conſtant yeelding to him, all duties of loue that concerne her, ſo long as they liue together, with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to giue him all holy content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; expreſſing that</p>
            <p n="1">1 In her chaſtity, being chaſt and faithfull to him both in her mind and body,
<note place="margin">Pro. 31.11. Tit. 2.5. 1. Tim. 3.11.</note> and keeping her ſelfe to him onely.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In her ſecreſie, keeping ſecret his honeſt intents,
<note place="margin">Pro. 11.13. Pro. 12.4. Pro. 31.11.</note> ſayings and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which he would not haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered; and hiding and couering his faults from all, ſauing thoſe who may helpe to better him; and to pray to God for his amendment.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Helpe and comfort, and that</p>
            <p n="1">1 In reſpect of his body,
<note place="margin">Gen. 2.18. 1. Cor. 11.9.</note> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to her ability vſing her beſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to preſerue his body in health; and if it be ſicke, to tender it and to looke to it, with all careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:13990:40"/>and diligence.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In reſpect of his outward e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,
<note place="margin">Gen. 27.9. Pro. 31.15.23. Eccleſ. 49.10.</note> (as much as concernes her in her place) helping him in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the family, and as the Lord makes her able; being proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent for his eſtate by exerciſing her ſelfe in ſome profitable employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.14. Pro. 31.13. to 29.</note> by appointing her maydes their worke, and ouerſeeing them therein, and by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ordering of her children and ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ants, inſtructing them and admoniſhing them as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion is offered.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In reſpect of his ſoule, vſing her beſt endeuour to refreſh his heart with comfort in time of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe and ſorrow,
<note place="margin">Iob. 19.17. 2. King. 4 9.10 1. Tim. 2.12.</note> and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ir him vp, and to helpe him forward in good duties, &amp; to ioyne with him in the performance of them, and to pray for the good of his body and the good of his ſoule.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:13990:40"/>
            <p> The due reſpect and due carriage of the husband towards his wife,
<note place="margin">Husbands dutie.</note> ſtandeth in a wiſe and right vſage of his power and authoritie ouer his wife, in tender loue to her, and in giuing honour to her.</p>
            <p n="1">1 In a wiſe and right vſage of his power and authority ouer his wife, and that, ſtanding</p>
            <p n="1">1 In vſing it ſo as he maintaine his preheminence &amp; ſuperiority in all things,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.16. Epheſ. 5.23. 1. Cor. 11.13.</note> carrying himſelfe as head and gouernor ouer his wife.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In vſing it not as a tyrant ouer her after his owne luſt and pleaſure,
<note place="margin">Pro. 2.17. Epheſ. 5.23. Gen. 2.22. 1. Pet. 3.7.</note> but ſo as may be for her good in all things, and ſo as his gouernment be void of rigour and bitterneſſe, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſ. 3.19.</p>
            <p>In tender loue to her, ſtanding in cleauing to her as one with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by the bond of mariage,
<note place="margin">Gen. 2.24. Mat. 19.5.6.</note> in true loue and affection of his heart, in
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:13990:41"/>ſpeciall manner expreſſing that loue and affection to her,
<note place="margin">Mar. 10.7.8.</note> in loue to her body, and in loue to her ſoule.</p>
            <p>In loue to her body, expreſſing that,</p>
            <p n="1">1 In contenting himſelfe with the loue of his owne wife only,
<note place="margin">Gen. 24.67. Pro. 5.19.20. Malac. 2.14.15</note> and keeping himſelfe to her alone, both in his minde and body; manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting that,</p>
            <p>By being willing to haue his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode with her as much as may be,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.7. Gen. 29.8.9. Iſai. 62.5. Pro. 5.18.19.</note> and his calling will ſuffer him; and by liuing cheerefully with her, let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting her haue all comfortable fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity with him.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In regarding carefully the good of the body of his wife,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.3. Epheſ. 5.28.29.</note> as he regards the good of his owne body; manifeſting that,</p>
            <p>By prouiding as God makes him able,
<note place="margin">Gen. 30 30. Exod. 31.10. Pro. 27.27.</note> all things needfull and fitting for her maintenance, according to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:13990:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>his place and calling,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.8. Gen. 28.16.</note> both for the time of his life, and after his death, if he die before her; and ordering all things to the beſt, and by protecting her as much as he is able from all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries both at home and abroad.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In loue to her ſoule,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.7. Epheſ. 5.25.26 27. 1. Cor. 7.16. Pro. 2.17.</note> dwelling with her as a man of knowledge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carefull, and vſing his beſt ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour in wiſedome and diſcretion to do good to her ſoule; manifeſting that,</p>
            <p n="1">1 In going before her in good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In vſing his beſt endeuour ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to plant good things,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.35. 1. Sam. 1.8. 2. Sam. 12.24. Gen. 25.2. Gen. 30.2.</note> or to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe them being already implan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in her ſoule, by teaching and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing her, by giuing her good counſell, by encouraging and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting her, and by praying for her; and likewiſe in vſing his beſt ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to amend and cure the things
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:13990:42"/>that are amiſſe in her,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 6.21. Iob. 2.10.</note> &amp; to reclaime her when ſhe doth offend in word or deed, the offence being ſuch as lieth in his power to amend, by ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and louing admonition or reproofe, as occaſion is offered.</p>
            <p>In giuing honour to her, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</p>
            <p n="1">1 In making account of her as his companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; yoake-fellow,
<note place="margin">Gen. 2.18.19. Pro. 31.27. 1. Tim. 5.14.</note> &amp; fellow helper, allowing her to helpe him in the gouernment of the family; and leauing her (ſhe being able and faithfull) in ſome houſhold matters, to her owne will and to her owne indgment and diſcretion; &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning her authoritie and honour amongſt children, ſeruants, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the houſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In a wiſe and patient ſuffering and bearing with her naturall infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,
<note place="margin">Rom. 15.1. Gal. 6.2. 1. Pet. 3.7.</note> ſo farre forth as they are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to him.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:13990:42"/> 3 In ſuffering himſelfe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to be admoniſhed or aduiſed by his wife.
<note place="margin">Gen. 21.12. 1. Sam. 2.23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The dutie of ſeruants.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seruants.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The due reſpect and due carriage of ſeruants towards their maiſters, ſtandeth in yeelding to them,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reuerence, ſubiection, faithfulneſſe,</hi> and <hi>thankefulneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Reuerence,</hi> inward and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Inward reuerence,
<note place="margin">Malac. 1.6. Epheſ. 6.5.6.7 Coloſſ. 3.22.23.24. 1. Pet. 2.18.</note> (namely this) in thinking &amp; eſteeming reuerently of them, and carrying in their hearts a reuerent awe and feare of them, diſcerning Gods Image in them, and that they ſtand in <hi>Chriſt</hi> his ſtead vnto them, in regard of their power and authoritie ouer them as they be their maiſters, be they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo poore or meane in the world.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Outward reuerence (namely) a manifeſtation of their inward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:13990:43"/>by their reuerent behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our towardes them,
<note place="margin">2. King. 5.13.25. Pro. 28.18. Act. 10.7.</note> both in word and deed; as by giuing them reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t titles, by bowing to them, riſing vp before them, vnbaring the head, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Subiection (namely) an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<note place="margin">Tit. 2.9. 1. Pet. 2.18.</note> ready, and willing ſubmitting of themſelues to the exerciſe and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of that authority and power that their maiſters haue ouer them, ſtanding in yeelding obedience to the voice and will of their maiſters;
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.5. Coloſſ. 3.22.</note> and that ſtanding,</p>
            <p n="1">1 In ready and cheerfull yeelding (ſo farre as they are able) to thoſe things which their maiſters teach them,
<note place="margin">Gen. 24.2.3.4.9.10. 2. Sam. 7.8. Luke 7.8. Luke. 17.7.8.9.</note> or counſell them, whether they be things that pertaine to their honeſt and lawfull callings and be their ordinarie workes, or they be duties of pietie and religion: and a ready and cheerful doing as they are
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:13990:43"/>able, of things commanded by their maiſters, being things fitting &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt &amp; lawful, though they be neuer ſo baſe, and neuer ſo laborious and painfull.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In a meek and patient bearing of that checke,
<note place="margin">Cen. 16.6.8.9. 1. Gen. 2.18.20 Tit. 2 9.</note> rebuke or correction that is layd on them by their mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, yea though the correction be without iuſt cauſe, or vnreaſonable, and more then it ought to be.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Faithfulneſſe (namely) a yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſincere and ſingle hearted ſeruice to their maiſters,
<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.22.23. Tit. 2.10.</note> and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their beſt endeuour in euery thing, to anſwer that truſt that their maiſters do repoſe in them; expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that,</p>
            <p n="1">1 In diligence and painefulneſſe,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.5.6. Col. 3.22.23. Gen 24.33. Gen. 31.40.</note> in being diligent in doing that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe they are ſet about by their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, &amp; doing it with the vttermoſt ſtrength of their minds and bodies,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:13990:44"/>or both, according to the qualitie of the buſineſſe, and that as well in the abſence as in the preſence of their maiſters.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In truſtie ſeruice, in a care of their maiſters good and profite and lawfull aduantage at all times;
<note place="margin">Mat. 25.19. to 29. Tit. 2.10. Gen. 31.38.39 Gen. 39.6.7.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as carefull and thriftie for their maiſters and their families, as they would be for themſelues, and their owne families.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In ſecreſie and care of their maiſters good name,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.3. 2. King. 6.11. Micah 7.5.6.</note> keeping ſecret their honeſt intents, ſayings and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which they would not haue diſcouered; and as much as may be, hiding and couering their wants and infirmities, and not blazing them abroad.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Thankfulneſſe, (namely) not onely an acknowledgment in word of their maiſters care ouer them for their good, and of the good they
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:13990:44"/>receiue from them, their maiſter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carefull to do them good; but a care and endeuour alſo in ſeruants (ſo farre as they are able) to anſwer that care of their maiſters and that good they receiue from them, by doing good to them againe; ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</p>
            <p n="1">1 In yeelding comfort and in bringing credite to them,
<note place="margin">Gen. 39.8.9. Pſal. 101.6.7. Pro. 14.35.</note> by their honeſt and religious good behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and carriage.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In praying for their maiſters,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2 1. Gen. 24.12.</note> and for direction and good ſucceſſe in their buſineſſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In prayſing God for their good gifts,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.12. Gen. 24.27.</note> &amp; for their care they take with them for their good, and for the good ſucceſſe they find in their workes and buſineſſes.</p>
            <p>The due reſpect and due carriage of maiſters towards their ſeruants ſtandeth in two things:
<note place="margin">Maiſters.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:13990:45"/> 1 In a wiſe and right vſage and exerciſe of their power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie ouer their ſeruants.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In being helpfull vnto them for their good.</p>
            <p n="1">1 A wiſe and right vſage and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their power and authority ouer their ſeruants, ſtandeth</p>
            <p n="1">1 In dealing iuſtly with them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In doing that which is equall and conſcionable to them,
<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 4.1.</note> Coloſſ. 4.1.</p>
            <p>In dealing iuſtly with them, and that,</p>
            <p n="1">1 In requiring of them not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things lawfull and poſſible,
<note place="margin">Leuit. 25.46. Pro. 12.10.</note> but things alſo proportionable to their abilitie and ſtrength.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In yeelding to them meate,
<note place="margin">Deut. 24.14.15 Pro. 31.15. &amp; 21. Mat. 10.10. Leuit. 19.13. Iam. 5.4.</note> drinke, and apparel, fitting for them in regard of their ſeruice, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their order and degree, and their qualitie and condition in the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:13990:45"/>family; or competent wages to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the ſame, being carefull that they haue their meate and drinke, and their whole wages in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In yeelding to them iuſt cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and correction for their faults,
<note place="margin">Pro. 19.29. Pro. 29.19. Exod. 21.20.</note> not cenſuring or correcting them, without iuſt cauſe or exceſſiuly, but wiſely and diſcreetly, admoniſhing, checking and rebuking them when they do amiſſe, with wordes, if that will ſerue the turne; if not, giuing them ſeaſonable, due and moderate correction.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In doing that which is equall and conſcionable to them, and that</p>
            <p n="1">1 In yeelding to them moderate reſt from their labours,
<note place="margin">Exod. 23.12. Deut. 5.14. Pro. 12.10.</note> and lawfull and ſeaſonable recreation, without which they cannot continue with any cheerfulneſſe in their callings; and eſpecially allowing them liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie<pb n="88" facs="tcp:13990:46"/>to ſanctifie the Sabbath both in publike and priuate.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In being carefull for their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants when they fall ſicke in their ſeruice,
<note place="margin">Mat. 8.5.6. 1. Sam. 30.13.</note> prouiding according to their abilitie, things needfull for them in time of their ſickneſſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In yeelding to them according to their ability,
<note place="margin">Deut. 15.13.14</note> ſome further recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence ouer and aboue their wages when they depart from them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the good and faithfull ſeruice they haue done them, and according to the time they haue bene with them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In being helpefull to them for their good, and that in reſpect of their calling and religion.</p>
            <p n="1">1 In reſpect of their calling, (namely) in ſeeing them follow the workes of their calling,
<note place="margin">Pro. 29.21. Exod. 35.34. Pro. 31.27.</note> ouer-ſeeing them in their workes, and directing them in the doing of them, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:13990:46"/>ſo as may be for their owne pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent good and lawfull benefite, but ſo alſo as may be for the good of their ſeruants in time to come; teaching them wherein they are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilful and need teaching, eſpecially in their trade and myſterie, faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly opening that to them, and ſo as they may beſt and moſt eaſily learne it.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In reſpect of religion, and that firſt in being carefull that their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants keepe an holy reſt to God on the Sabath,
<note place="margin">Exod. 20.10. Pſal. 42.4. Act. 10.24.33.</note> endeuoring to fit them for publike exerciſes, and bringing them to the publike aſſemblies in due time, &amp; looking that there they behaue themſelues religiouſly the whole time; and after the publike exerciſes are ended, taking account of that which they haue heard, that they may profite in knowledge and holy obedience.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:13990:47"/>
            <p> Secondly,
<note place="margin">Gen. 18.19. Deut. 6.7. Ioſh. 24.15. Ierem. 10.25.</note> in inſtructing them carefully and diligently in priuate, in the holy Scriptures and in the grounds of religion, that they may grow in knowledge, and may reape benefite by the publike Miniſterie of the word; and in praying with them and for them, that the Lord would beſtow on them all needfull graces.</p>
            <p>The due reſpect and due carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of the people or flocke towards their Miniſter or Paſtor,
<note place="margin">The People or Flocke.</note> ſtands in yeelding to them, <hi>reuerence, ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, aſſiſtance</hi> and <hi>thankefulneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Reuerence, (namely) hauing him in reuerent account and eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<note place="margin">1. King. 17.18. 2. King. 4.16. 1. Cor. 4.1. 2. Cor. 5.20. 1. Theſſ. 2.13. Tit. 1.7.</note> eſteeming of him reuerently in their hearts, and expreſſing their reuerent eſtimation of him both in word and deed; and eſpecially in hearing him teach the truth of God with reuerence, euen as a meſſenger
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:13990:47"/>ſent to them of God, and as ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in <hi>Chriſt</hi> his ſtead, and as Gods ſteward and diſpoſer of his ſecrets to them, be he neuer ſo weake or poore.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Submiſſion, willingly yeelding themſelues to be taught and guided by him,
<note place="margin">Exod. 24.3.7. Ioh. 10.2.3.4.5.27. Heb. 13.17.</note> hearing and knowing his voice, and obeying his doctrine tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deliuered to them out of the word of God, and following him as the ſheepe of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his holy doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and conuerſation.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Aſſiſtance, and that two wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Aſſiſting him by their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and according to their abilitie,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 38.7.8.9. Rom. 16.4. 2. Tim. 4.16.</note> ſtanding for his defence againſt the wrongs and iniuries that are offered and done to him, by il diſpoſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Aſſiſting him by their prayers, praying for him that the Lord would giue him both abilitie and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:13990:48"/>libertie to execute and fulfill his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall office;
<note place="margin">Rom. 15.30.31. Epheſ. 6.19. Coloſſ. 4.3.4. 2. Theſſ. 3.1.2. Philem. v. 22. Heb. 13.18.</note> and that he would giue him ſtrength, courage and power to ſtand againſt men and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, that ſeeke by force and ſubtiltie to diſcourage him, and either to driue him away, or to hold him backe from the faithfull diſcharge of his dutie.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Thankefulneſſe not onely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging in word their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters care ouer them, and his paines taken with them for their good, he being wel qualified, and being faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and carefull and taking paines with them as he ought for their good; but a care and an endeuour alſo in the people, ſo far as they are able, to anſwer that care and that paines of their Miniſter &amp; the good they do or may receiue from him, by doing good to him againe; that ſtanding</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:13990:48"/> 1 In reioycing in him,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 52.7. Philip. 2.29.</note> and giuing thankes to God for him, prayſing God for his good gifts, and for his faithfull care ouer them, and paines taken with them for their good.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In yeelding him
<note n="*" place="bottom">1. Tim. 5.17.18. Deut. 19.12. Galat. 4.15. 1. Theſſ. 5.12.13. 1. Cor. 9.7. to 15. Galat. 6.6. The Miniſter or Paſtors dutie. Ezech 13.17. Ezech. 33.7. Iob 33.23.24. Act. 20.28.31. Heb. 13.17. 1. Pet. 5.2.</note> double ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that is, both ſingular loue for his workes ſake, and alſo ſufficient maintenance both in regard of his perſon and calling.</p>
            <p>The due reſpect &amp; due carriage of the Miniſter or Paſtor towards his people or flocke, ſtands in watching carefully &amp; faithfully ouer his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, diligently ouerſeeing them, and carefully endeuouring to do good to their ſoules, both to gaine &amp; call them to God that are not called, and alſo to preſerue and keepe them in <hi>Chriſt</hi> that are called; expreſſing that,</p>
            <p n="1">1 In vſing and applying his gifts for the beſt good of their ſoules.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:13990:49"/> 2 In going wiſely in and out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, in vſing and applying his giftes for the beſt good of their ſoules; and that</p>
            <p n="1">1 By diligent and faithfull preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the pure word of God to them,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 3.15. 1. Cor. 9.16. 2. Tim. 4.2.</note> in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, for the beſt good of their ſoules; and that</p>
            <p>By opening to his people the will of God reuealed in his word,
<note place="margin">Nehem. 8.8. Ierem. 23.16.28. Ezech. 13.3. to 10.</note> faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and truly expounding that to them that they may vnderſtand it, and deliuering vnto them ſound and wholeſome doctrine,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.4. Tit. 1.9. 2. Tim. 2.15.</note> and that in plainneſſe and power, to their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie and conſcience: and by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king right vſe and application of it to them, giuing euery one his por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as need ſhall require and as iuſt occaſion is offered;
<note place="margin">Heb. 5.12. 2. Tim. 2.25. 2. Tim. 4.2. Tit. 1.9.10.11.13. Act. 18.28.</note> inſtructing the ignorant, and endeuoring to build vp his people further in knowledge of the truth of God, refuting errors,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:13990:49"/>that either the whole flocke or any of them are tainted withall,
<note place="margin">Iſai 58.1. Tit. 2.1.6.15. Ierem. 23.14.17. Ezech. 13.10.11.18.22. 1. Cor. 14.3.</note> or may fall into; exhorting &amp; ſtirring them vp to pietie and all good duties, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhing them that are vnruly, and wiſely rebuking and reprouing them for their ſinnes, and that with meekeneſſe or ſharpeneſſe as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is offered; ſtrengthening the weake, and comforting ſuch as ſtand in need of comfort, and are iuſtly to be comforted.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By a wiſe and right diſpenſing of the Sacraments to them,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.1.2. Mat. 24.45. Pro. 27.23. Philip. 2.19. 1. Sam. 12.23. Philip. 1.9. Coloſſ. 1.3.9. 1. Theſſ. 1.2. 1. Theſſ. 3.13. 2. Theſſ. 1.3.11</note> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by praying for them, &amp; prayſing God on their behalfe, examining them, how fit they be to partake in the holy things of God, and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting them, &amp; endeuoring to make them fit to partake in them to their comfort, and praying for their ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall good, and prayſing God for the ſpirituall good that is beſtowed
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:13990:50"/>on them.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In going wiſely in and out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them,
<note place="margin">Exod. 28.30. Philip. 4.9. 1. Tim. 4.12.</note> that is, going before them in all holy example and being a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of holy life to them; and that,</p>
            <p>Both in doing good things,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.14.15.16. Tit. 2.7. 2. Tim. 2.3. 1. Tim. 3.4.5.7. 1. Cor. 9.19. to 25. Subiects.</note> and in the practiſe of euery good worke. And alſo in ſuffering.</p>
            <p>The due reſpect and due carriage of the ſubiects towards their Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, ſtandeth in yeelding to them <hi>reuerence, ſubmiſſion, fidelitie,</hi> and <hi>thankefulneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reuerence both inward and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Inward reuerence, (namely) thinking and eſteeming reuerently of them;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 82.1.6. Eccleſ. 10.20. Rom. 13.17.</note> and carrying in their hearts a reuerent awe and feare of them, acknowledging Gods image in them, and that they haue their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from God, and are ordained
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:13990:50"/>of God, and are his deputies, and ſtand in his ſtead as they be Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Outward reuerence,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.21. Dan. 4.16. Act. 26.25. Iude epiſt. v. 8. 2. Sam. 9.6.8. 1. King. 2.23. 2. King. 3.14. Act. 24.10.</note> (namely) a declaration of their inward reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, expreſſing their outward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent behauiour towards them, both in word and deed, by giuing them titles of honor and reuerence due to them, by bowing to them, by ſtanding bare in their preſence, by keeping ſilence in Courts of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment till they be called to ſpeake.</p>
            <p>Submiſſion, (namely) an humble ready and willing ſubmitting of themſelues to the exerciſe and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of that authority and power that their Magiſtrates haue ouer them,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.23.</note>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 3.1.</note> ſtanding in yeelding obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to them; expreſſing that</p>
            <p n="1">1 In yeelding willingly and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily ſo farre forth as they are able,
<note place="margin">Ioſh. 1.16.17. 1. Sam. 16.19.20.</note> to thoſe things that their Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:13990:51"/>do command,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.14.15. 1. King. 2.25. 2. King 10.25.</note> keeping and performing according to their abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, the expreſſe commandement of their Magiſtrates, in all things ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and lawfull.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In a quiet and patient bearing of the cenſures and puniſhments that their Magiſtrates lay on them for their offences in breaking their good and wholſome lawes,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 19.27.28. Pro. 24.21.22. Act. 25.11. Rom. 13.4.</note> though it be to the loſſe of their liues.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Fidelity, (namely) a loyall and ſound hearted loue to them,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 22.14. 2. Sam. 20.2.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly cleauing to them, and not ſhrinking from them when they haue need of them, nor deceiuing them at any time, nor in any thing wherein they ought to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>Expreſſing that:</p>
            <p n="1">1 In a tender care of their honour and dignitie,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 19.24.5.</note> endeuouring as much as they are able, within compaſſe
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:13990:51"/>of their place and calling,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 24.3.</note> to keepe their Magiſtrates from doing any thing that may blemiſh them in their place and office:
<note place="margin">Ierem. 36.25.</note> as being ſuch as may ſpeake to them, by ſpeaking plainly vnto them, yet reuerently and dutifully; and by diſſwading them as much as they may, from that which is amiſſe, when they ſee they are about to do any euill, and not flattering and ſoothing them vp in any euill courſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In ſtanding as much as they are able for the defence of their life and ſtate,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.21. 2. Sam. 18.3. 2. Sam. 21.17.</note> eſpecially in defending to their vttermoſt power the life of their Prince and ſupreame Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, though it be to the loſſe of their owne liues.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In keeping ſecret their honeſt intents, ſayings and doings,
<note place="margin">2. King. 6.11. 2. Sam. 17.15.16. Heſt, 2.21.22.</note> which they would not haue diſcouered; and in diſcouering of treaſons,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:13990:52"/>conſpiracies, practiſes and dangers, intended againſt their liues and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and eſpecially againſt the life and perſon of their Prince and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Thankefulneſſe, not onely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging in word, their care ouer them for their good, and the benefites they enioy vnder their wiſe and good gouernment (their Magiſtrates being carefull as they ought to be for their good,) but a care and an endeuour alſo in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects ſo farre as they are able, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that care and good they do or may receiue by their good gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by doing good to them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
            <p>And that,</p>
            <p n="1">1 In yeelding to them outward helpe and ſupport willingly and cheerfully,
<note place="margin">Mat. 22.21. Rom. 13.6.7.</note> paying to them ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, taxes and other payments ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:13990:52"/>for the maintenance of their eſtate, eſpecially the eſtate of the Prince, both in time of peace and in time of warre.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In praying for them, eſpecially for their Prince and ſupreame Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, for his perſon, ſtate,
<note place="margin">1. King. 1.39. Ierem. 29 7. 1. Tim. 2.1.2.</note> and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie gouernment.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In praiſing God for their good gifts, the right vſe of their authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 21. 1. Tim. 2.1.2.</note> and the bleſſing of God on their publicke actions that concerne the common good, the good of their ſubiects, both in peace and in warre.</p>
            <p>The due reſpect and due car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the Magiſtrate towards his ſubiects,
<note place="margin">Magiſtrates.</note> ſtands in a wiſe and right vſage of his good gifts, and of his power and authority ouer his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 49.23. Rom. 13.4. 2. Tim. 2.1.2.</note> in vſing and applying his gifts and authority in that place and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice he holdeth in the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, for the beſt good of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:13990:53"/>and of the common wealth; and that,</p>
            <p>By a carefull promoting and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancing of true religion and the pure worſhip of God,
<note place="margin">2. King. 18.4. 2. King. 13.3. to 21. 2. Chron 17.6 2. Chro. 34.31 1. Tim. 2.2.</note> and by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenancing and defacing of all vngodlineſſe, and all falſe and idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous worſhip, according to his place and power: the chiefe Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate according to his place and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and the inferiour Magiſtrate according to his. As the chiefe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate is to do it:
<note place="margin">Deut. 17.18.19 2. Sam. 6.14. 2. Chron. 19.3</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 In his owne perſon, (namely) by taking knowledge of true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion himſelfe, and by imbracing it and practiſing it in his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In thoſe that be vnder him: and that,</p>
            <p n="1">1 By making and eſtabliſhing in his kingdome,
<note place="margin">1. Chron. 23.</note> ſuch good and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome lawes and orders, as ſerue to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:13990:53"/>maintaine and vphold the truth of religion,
<note place="margin">2. Chron. 25.1. to 9. Iudge 17.6.</note> and to inhibite and to put downe all falſe religion, and to keep out of his kingdome and dominion all confuſed mixture of religion, and by ſeeing thoſe lawes and orders duly executed.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By prouiding as much as he may,
<note place="margin">2. King. 9.1. 2. King. 22.14 Iſai. 49.23. 2. Chron 19.8 9. 2. Chron. 31.2.</note> that his ſubiects may be taught the truth of religion, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the wayes of God, to that end planting and maintaining ſchooles of good learning and Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities in his dominions; and loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that able and ſufficient Paſtors be ſet ouer the ſeuerall Churches in his kingdome.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By taking order that Paſtors &amp; teachers do their dutie in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing true and ſound doctrine,
<note place="margin">2. King. 23.4. 2. Chron. 29.4 5.11.</note> and in other holy adminiſtrations; counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing the good and faithfull, and diſcountenancing the careleſſe and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:13990:54"/>negligent;
<note place="margin">1. King. 2.26.27.35. Exod. 22.20. Leuit. 24.6.</note> and remouing ſuch as be erroneous and ſcandalous, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue to be remoued; and by taking order that the people yeeld them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be taught and guided by their Paſtors, for the good of their ſoules; and that hereticks, idolaters, and blaſphemers, be puniſhed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their offences.</p>
            <p>The inferiour Magiſtrate is to do it,</p>
            <p n="1">1 In his owne perſon, by taking notice of true religion himſelfe,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.10.11.12. Pſal. 148.11.</note> and by embracing it, and practiſing it in his owne perſon according to his place and calling.</p>
            <p n="2">2 As much as he may, in all thoſe that be vnder his power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie; and that,</p>
            <p n="1">1 By a diligent and carefull ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing of his vnder officers (he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one that hath officers vnder him,) and by looking to them that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:13990:54"/>they performe their duty in promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting true religion and the pure wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God;
<note place="margin">Nehem. 13.10 11. Nehem. 13.17 25 28.</note> &amp; in diſcountenancing the contrarie, ſo farre as concernes them in their places and offices, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging the good and faithful, &amp; diſcountenancing, reprouing and cenſuring thoſe that be careleſſe and negligent, according to their faults and offences.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By executing duly and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially thoſe good lawes and orders,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 22.22.22. Ierem. 38.4.6. Mica. 3.2. Rom. 13.3.4.</note> that are eſtabliſhed for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; the pure wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, to his vttermoſt power &amp; ſo far as concerns him in his place and office, to the countenancing of good cauſes of religion and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons, whether Miniſters or others; and to the diſcountenancing and repreſſing of bad and wicked cauſes and perſons, as heretickes, i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:13990:55"/> 2 By a carefull prouiding for the peace and ſafety,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.4. 1. Tim. 2.2.</note> and quietneſſe and outward welfare of his ſubiects, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his place and power; the chiefe Magiſtrate according to his place and power, the inferior Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate according to his, as the chiefe Magiſtrate is to do it by vſing his power.</p>
            <p n="1">1 For the eſtabliſhing of peace and quietnes amongſt his ſubiects; and that,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 10 1.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 By making ſuch good and wholeſome lawes in his kingdome, as ſerue to ſettle vnity and concord, and equitie and iuſtice amongſt his ſubiects, and by ſeeing thoſe lawes duely executed,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 122.3.</note> that euery one of his ſubiects may (as much as is poſſible) haue his right, and that which in equitie and conſcience belongs to him; and that none of them be any way, in body, goods
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:13990:55"/>or name wronged or oppreſſed.
<note place="margin">Exod. 18.21.22. 2. Sam. 8.15.16. &amp;c. 2. Chron. 19.5.6.7.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 By a wiſe and carefull choice of his vnder gouernors, both in time of peace and in time of warre, that they be qualified as they ought to be, that they be men of courage, fearing God, dealing truly, and hating co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe.
<note place="margin">1. King. 1.52. Pro. 16.14.15, Pro. 20.26. Rom. 13.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 By pulling down the wicked &amp; enemies of peace, and by maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and defending the quiet, and peaceable, and innocent, that ſeeke to him for ſuccour and reliefe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 And for the keeping and maintaining of peace and quietnes, and for the preſeruing of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward welfare of his ſubiects; &amp; that,</p>
            <p n="1">1 By requiring onely ſo much outward helpe and ſupport from them as is meete and neceſſary for the maintenance of his eſtate,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 8.11.12. &amp;c. 1. King. 12.14.</note> either in time of peace or warre, not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing them with exactions and grieuances.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:13990:56"/> 2 By making lawfull leagues of friendſhip and peace with his neighbour Princes and Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours.
<note place="margin">1. King. 5.4.5.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 By ſtanding for the liberty of his kingdome and ſubiects if need be,
<note place="margin">Iudg. 4.14. 2. Sam. 20.6.7 2. King. 18.7.8</note> by force of armes, by figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for it, either for the defending of it againſt the ſeditious and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious within his kingdome and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, or againſt the common and forreine enemies of it, or for the recouering of it againe being loſt.</p>
            <p>The inferiour Magiſtrate is to do it,</p>
            <p n="1">1 By a carefull and diligent ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing of his vnder officers (he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a one as hath officers vnder him) looking to them that they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the duty that concernes them,
<note place="margin">Nehem. 5.1.2.3.4. &amp;c.</note> touching the peace, and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and quietneſſe, and outward
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:13990:56"/>welfare of men where they haue to do; that they deale iuſtly, and truly, and equally betweene man and man, and that they wrong no man in any cauſe or matter which they haue to deale withall: encouraging the good and faithfull, and diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing, reprouing, and cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſuch as be careleſſe and faulty, according to their offences.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By acquainting himſelfe with the good lawes and cuſtomes of the land and kingdome where he holds his office,
<note place="margin">Deut. 1.13.15. Num. 11.16. Act. 24.10.</note> and by being skilfull in all thoſe cauſes that ſhall come before him, that he may wiſely rule and gouerne all ſorts of men that he hath to deale withall, and may wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apply his knowledge to euery particular occaſion.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By admitting willingly all iuſt complaints, and taking notice of all aggreeuances that are brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:13990:57"/>him, throughly examining them by all due circumſtances,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.3.4. Pro. 18.17. Leuit. 19.15. Deut. 1.16.17. Deut. 16.18.19. Iudg. 19.30. 1. Sam. 8.3. Pro. 17.23. Iſai. 1.23. Hoſ. 4.18. Ioſh. 7.24. Rom. 13.4.</note> and hauing ſo examined them, by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting difference betweene good and bad cauſes and perſons, and deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thoſe cauſes ſo examined, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptly, giuing iuſt iudgement without partialitie or reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and without receiuing of bribes and gifts to peruert iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="4">4 By ſeeing or taking order, that due and ſeaſonable execution be done on offenders and malefactors, according to the iudgement and ſentence paſſed on them, Ioſh. 7.24. Rom. 13.4.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By a carefull procuring of ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill honeſtie, good manners, and good order amongſt his ſubiects, according to his place &amp; power; the chiefe Magiſtrate according to his place and power,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.2.</note> and the inferiour
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:13990:57"/>Magiſtrate according vnto his, as the chiefe Magiſtrate is to do it, thus:</p>
            <p>By making ſuch good lawes and orders in his kingdome,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.17. Philip. 4.8. Eccleſ. 5.8.</note> as ſerue to maintaine ciuil honeſty, good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and good order among his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects; and to inhibite and to put downe all things that are thereunto contrarie, and by ſeeing thoſe lawes and orders duly executed, looking to it as much as is poſſible, that his ſubiects walke orderly, being euery one imployed according to his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie in ſome honeſt and lawfull calling; and that al lewd perſons and practiſes, and all occaſions of luſt and vnthirftineſſe be remoued, as ſtewes, houſes of filthineſſe,
<note place="margin">1. King. 15.12</note> houſes of gaming, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>The inferiour Magiſtrate is to do it,</p>
            <p>By executing duly and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:13990:58"/>both by himſelf, and by ſuch as be in office vnder him, the good lawes and orders made for the maintaining of ciuill honeſty, and for the inhibiting &amp; putting downe of thoſe things that are thereunto contrarie: ſtanding</p>
            <p n="1">1 In ſetting ſuch poore perſons as be luſtie and ſtrong, to work, and not ſuffering them to be idle, and to make begging and wandring their trade of life; but puniſhing them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to law, if they be found ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and wandring:
<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 3.10.11.12. Iob. 30.5.6.7.8.</note> and in ſeeing that no maintenance or allowance be giuen to ſuch without puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, vnleſſe they will ſettle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to ſome honeſt labour and imployment.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In taking order that ſuch poore perſons as be aged or weake,
<note place="margin">Deut 15.7.8.9 10.11.12. Iob. 20.13.14.15.16.</note> or be blinde or lame, and not able to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; or ſuch as haue ſtrength of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:13990:58"/>and vſe it carefully and conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably, &amp; yet cannot earne ſo much as to maintaine themſelues and their families, be in ſome competent ſort helped and relieued, that they be not conſtrained to begge their bread.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In ſeeing,
<note place="margin">Leuit. 18.24.25.27.28. Deut. 23.17. 1. Sam. 2.22.</note> as much as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly he may, all lewde practiſes, and all occaſions of filthineſſe and vnthriftines be remoued, as ſtewes, houſes of filthineſſe, houſes of ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The due reſpect and due carriage of perſons younger in yeares,
<note place="margin">Perſons yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in yeares.</note> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thoſe that are more ancient in regard of their yeares, ſtandeth in yeelding to them</p>
            <p n="1">1 Reuerence both in heart, word,
<note place="margin">Leuit. 19.32. Iob. 30.1. Iſai. 3.5.</note> and deed, eſteeming reuerently of them in regard of their age, as a print of Gods eternitie, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth their reuerent opinion of
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:13990:59"/>them,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.1.2.</note> by giuing them titles of reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence due to them in their place, and by giuing them the vpper hand, by bowing to them, by riſing vp before them, and the like.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Modeſt behauiour towards them,
<note place="margin">Iob. 32.4.6.10 16.17. Tit. 2.6. 1. Pet. 5.5. Perſons more Ancient.</note> not preſuming to ſpeake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them in matters of weight, but keeping ſilence till they haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>The due reſpect and due carriage of perſons more ancient towards thoſe that are yonger in yeares, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in yeelding to them,</p>
            <p n="1">1 Good aduice,
<note place="margin">Iob. 32.7.9. 1. King. 12.6.7.8. Tit. 2.4.</note> counſell and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection as occaſion is offered, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aduiſing, counſelling and direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them in good things.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Good example, giuing them good example,
<note place="margin">Pro. 16.31. Iſai 62.20. Tit. 2.2.3.</note> and going before them in a wiſe, ſober, graue and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conuerſation.</p>
            <p>The due reſpect and due carriage of thoſe that want good gifts,
<note place="margin">Thoſe that want gifts.</note> or are
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:13990:59"/>inferiour to others in gifts, towards thoſe that haue good gifts, ſtandeth in yeelding to them,</p>
            <p n="1">1 An acknowledgement of their good gifts,
<note place="margin">Gen. 41.38.39 Dan. 4.6. Mat 3.11. 2. Pet. 3.15.</note> and a reuerent regard of them for the ſame, according to the meaſure of their good gifts, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the excellencie and kind of them; more reuerently reſpecting thoſe that haue good gifts of minde &amp; graces of Gods Spirit, then thoſe that haue onely good gifts of body, or outward good gifts, though they are alſo to be reſpected in regard of thoſe good gifts.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Imitation of their good gifts, and making a good vſe of them to themſelues,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 9.9. Ioh. 4.19.20. to 27. Philip. 4.9.</note> imitating the vertues and graces that are in others, and labouring for them in themſelues.</p>
            <p>The due reſpect and due carriage of thoſe that haue good gifts of minde or body,
<note place="margin">Thoſe that haue good gifts.</note> or outward good
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:13990:60"/>gifts, towards thoſe that want thoſe good gifts, or are inferiour to them in gifts, ſtandeth</p>
            <p>In vſing thoſe good gifts to the glory of God,
<note place="margin">Rom. 14 7. Rom. 15.1. 1. Cor. 12.7.</note> and to the greateſt good of thoſe that want them; not lifting vp themſelues aboue their brethren, but bending downe, and applying their gifts for the beſt good of others.</p>
            <p>The due reſpect and due carriage of thoſe that do or may receiue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit from others, toward thoſe that haue care, or ſhew forth their care for their good and benefite, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth</p>
            <p>In a kinde acceptance of the leaſt benefite,
<note place="margin">Gen. 40.23. 2. Chron. 24.21.22. Act. 22.3. Rom. 16 2.3.4</note> and a thankefull acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of it, and a louing remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of them for it, as any occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is offered, and in vſing it to Gods glory, and their owne beſt good.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:13990:60"/>
            <p> The due reſpect and due carriage of thoſe that haue care of others, or ſhew forth their care for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of others, towards thoſe that do or may receiue benefite from them, ſtandeth</p>
            <p>In taking the beſt and wiſeſt courſe that poſſibly they can,
<note place="margin">2 King. 2.9. Iob. 29.16. Act. 22.3.</note> that the benefite they intend or reach out to others, may be moſt profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to them that are or ſhall be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The negatiue part of the fifth Commandement.</head>
               <p>It forbids,</p>
               <p n="1">1 The want or neglect of the due reſpect and of the due carriage of inferiours towards their ſuperiours, and by conſequent, of ſuperiours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their inferiors, &amp; of equals a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:13990:61"/>themſelues, and ſo the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of any of thoſe duties that are required of inferiours, ſuperiors, or equalls, one towards another, whether generall, or particular.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whatſoeuer is contrarie to the due reſpect and due carriage of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours towards their ſuperiours, and of equalls among themſelues, and doth diminiſh or impeach the dignitie that God hath beſtowed on others; as</p>
               <p n="1">1 The things contrarie to the due reſpect and due carriage of infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours towards their ſuperiours, are</p>
               <p n="1">1 A light and baſe eſteeming, a deſpiſing and contemning of ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours,
<note place="margin">Leuit. 20.9. Deut. 27.16. Gen 9.22. Pro. 30.11.17. Iud. epiſt v. 8. Exod. 22.28. Eccleſ. 10.20.</note> as the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> do in their iudgement and opinion, ſhewing forth that light eſtimation and that contempt of them, by contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous words, geſtures, or deeds; as by wiſhing ill to them, by mocking and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:13990:61"/>ſcorning of them, by ſpeaking ill of them, and reuiling them, by ſmiting them, and the like.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Diſobedience to them,
<note place="margin">Deut. 21.18. Rom. 1.30.</note> ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornly refuſing to yeeld that obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience they owe vnto them; ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it forth</p>
               <p n="1">1 In reſiſting their lawfull autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,
<note place="margin">Gen. 28.8.9. 2 Sam. 15.10.11.12. Mat. 21.30. Tit. 2.15.</note> refuſing to be gouerned by them, &amp; in contemning their good counſells, and their iuſt and lawfull commandements.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In reſiſting them, when they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe their power ouer them,
<note place="margin">Gen. 16.8.9. Deut. 21.18. Pro. 13.1. Tit. 2.9.</note> in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhing, in reprouing, or in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting them, then murmuring or riſing vp againſt them, or flying from them.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The things contrarie to the due reſpect and due carriage of ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours towards their inferiours are,</p>
               <p n="1">1 A light, vaine, wicked and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemely carriage of themſelues in
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 6.20.</note>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:13990:62"/>the ſight of their inferiours;
<note place="margin">Zephan. 3.4. Rom. 2.17.18 to. 25.</note> when they carrie themſelues lightly, vainely, and wickedly, and vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming them in reſpect of their age, place, or gifts, before their inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, and thereby not onely bring diſhonour to God, in whoſe place and roome they ſtand as they be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours;
<note place="margin">Tit. 2.15.</note> but bring alſo iuſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace and contempt on their owne perſons, or on their places or gifts.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The abuſe of that authoritie and power that God hath put into their hands ouer their inferiours,
<note place="margin">Pro. 28 15. Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phan. 3 3. Coloſſ. 3.19. 1. Pet. 5.3.</note> when they peruert that authoritie and power God hath giuen them for the good of thoſe ouer whom they are ſet, to the hurt and wrong of thoſe that be vnder them; and that,</p>
               <p n="1">1 When they exerciſe it to the fauouring,
<note place="margin">1 King. 12.31. 2. Chron. 13.9</note> countenancing, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancing of the wicked and vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy;
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:13990:62"/>and to the diſcountenancing,
<note place="margin">Eccle. 10.5 6.7 Mica. 3.2. Ierem. 5.23. Ezech. 13.18.21.</note> diſgracing, and putting downe and keeping vnder of the godly and wel deſeruing.</p>
               <p n="2">2 When they exerciſe it either with too much lenitie, or with too much ſeueritie, 1. Sam. 2.22.23. Epheſ. 6.4.9. Coloſſ. 3.21.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The contrarie to the due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and due carriage of equals a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelues, is,</p>
               <p>The aduancing and preferring of themſelues one aboue another,
<note place="margin">Mat 20.24. Mat. 23.6.</note> either in opinion or practiſe, and ſo diſdaining one another.</p>
               <p>That inferiours, ſuperiours, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals, do things contrary to the due reſpect and due carriage that they owe one to another,
<note place="margin">Pride. Pro. 13.10. Num. 12.1.2. Ich. 19.10. Selfe-loue. 2. Tim. 3.2.3.4. Careleſneſſe.</note> proceeds ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of pride and arrogancy, or ſelfe-loue, or careleſneſſe to know their duty, or knowing it, to practiſe it; or curioſitie, men buſying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:13990:63"/>with the duties of others,
<note place="margin">Zach 11.16. Curioſitie. 1. Tim. 5.13. 1. Pet. 4.15.</note> and medling with things not appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to them.</p>
               <p>The confirmation or promiſe.</p>
               <p>It containes,</p>
               <p n="2">2 A confirmation of it by a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made to ſuch as yeeld obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to it, in theſe words,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That thy dayes may be long in the land which the Lord thy God giueth thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The bleſſing promiſed is length of dayes,
<note place="margin">Epheſ 6.3. Deut. 5.16.</note> long life, and proſperitie, and whatſoeuer belongs to a mans welfare and well being in this life.</p>
               <p>This bleſſing is promiſed rather then any other particular bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, becauſe parents are the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and meanes of this life; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it pleaſeth the Lord to make this promiſe, and to giue them long life for ableſſing, who dutifully, and reſpectiuely behaue themſelues
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:13990:63"/>towards their parents.</p>
               <p>And long life in this world is a bleſſing,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.4.5.6.10. Pſal. 6.5.6.</note> becauſe our temporarie life is giuen vs, that in it we may vſe all good meanes to attaine to life and ſaluation, and it is the time of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and the time of grace and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
               <p>The land ſpoken of in this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, is, in reſpect of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of the Lord for a poſſeſſion; but in reſpect of vs it is to be vnderſtood generally of any place, whereſoeuer we be in the world, that ſuch as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour their parents they haue right of dwelling in that place where they be, from the Lord,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 24.1. Epheſ. 6.3.</note> whoſe is the whole earth.</p>
               <p>Things to be gathered from this promiſe, are,</p>
               <p n="1">1 That due reſpect and due car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of inferiours, ſuperiours, and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:13990:64"/>equals one towards another, is greatly pleaſing to God.
<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.10.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 That the beſt courſe that pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents can take,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 13.14.28.29. 2. Sam. 15.</note> that it may go well with their children, is to inſtruct and nurture them in godlineſſe, and to bring them vp in the feare of the Lord; and that they that are care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and neglect this dutie, do, as much as in them is, ſhorten the dayes of their children,</p>
               <p n="3">3 That long life in this world cometh not by nature or good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the body,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.15. Eccleſ. 8.8.</note> but of the good pleaſure and prouidence of God, the Lord granting it, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the meanes to that purpoſe.</p>
               <trailer>The end of the fifth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="commandment">
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:13990:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The ſixth Commandement. <hi>The negatiue part.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>It forbids euery thing that ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the hurt or hinderance of the life of man, either the life of his body, or the life of his ſoule.</p>
            <p>The things hurting or hindering the life of the body of man, are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things of practiſe, or things of omiſſion.</p>
            <p>Things of practiſe; and thoſe are either inward in the heart, or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in word or deed.</p>
            <p>Things inward in the heart, and thoſe are foure eſpecially:</p>
            <p>Firſt, haſtie, raſh, vnaduiſed, vniuſt,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.22. Eccleſ. 7.11. Num. 24.10.</note> and ſinfull anger, (namely) ſuch as is either haſtily conceiued, without iuſt and ſufficient cauſe; or the cauſe
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:13990:65"/>being iuſt and weightie, ſuch as is directed amiſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, as either againſt the perſon,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.28. Epheſ 4.26. Gen. 49.6.7. Dan. 3.19.</note> or againſt the offence onely as it is an offence to men, as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie and wrong, bringing hurt and dammage to men, and not as an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to God; or ſuch as exceedeth either in time or in meaſure, and becomes hot fierie anger, furious and raging, troubling the minde, and making a man forget dutie to God and men.</p>
            <p>Secondly, malice or hatred, which is old anger,
<note place="margin">Gen. 45.8. Leuit. 19.17. 1. Ioh. 2.9.11. 1. Ioh. 3.15.</note> or continued wrath, and is anger or wrath kept cloſe in the heart, cloaked and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for a time, with purpoſe to do hurt, and waiting for opportunity to do miſchiefe.</p>
            <p>And the higheſt degree of it is ſuch a malicious affection as is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Sam. 24 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.19.20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sam. 26.21. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>al. 120.6.7.</note> and can neuer be appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but is fully ſet at all times, and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:13990:65"/>by all meanes to do miſchiefe. And</p>
            <p>The worſt kinde of it is,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.30. 1. Ioh. 3.12. Mat. 10.22. 1. King 22.8 Ioh. 7.7.</note> when men malice or hate others, either, for the good things they ſee in them, or for telling them of their faults, though they pretend other cauſes of their hatred.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, enuie, whereby men grieue &amp; repine at the good things that others haue,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.4.44. Gen. 30.1. Num. 11.28.29. Mat. 27.18.</note> which they would haue and cannot, whether they be good things of the minde or body, or outward good things; and do hate them for thoſe good things: for enuie is a compound of carnall griefe and hatred, and it comes</p>
            <p>Out of pride and abundance of ſelfe-loue.
<note place="margin">Galat. 5.2.6. 1. Tim. 6.4. 1. Cor. 13.4. Pro. 17.5. Pro. 24.17.18.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And it carries an enuious perſon both to a wiſhing of euill and hurt to another, and the fall of another; or to a reioycing in the hurt, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil, and fall that comes to another.</p>
            <pb n="128" facs="tcp:13990:66"/>
            <p> Fourthly, a deſire of reuenge, which is,
<note place="margin">Leuit 19.19. Luke 9.54.55</note> when men to ſatisfie their owne corrupt and troubled mindes, for wrong done, or ſuppoſed to be done to them, deſire to requite e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill for euil, and to right themſelues by extremitie and by puniſhment in ful proportion, according to their reuengefull minds.</p>
            <p>Outward things in word, and thoſe are fiue eſpecially:</p>
            <p>Firſt, bitter and curſed ſpeaking, hard,
<note place="margin">Pro. 12.18. Mat. 5.22. Rom. 3.14. 1. Cor. 6.10. Epheſ. 4.31. Coloſſ. 3.8. 2. King. 19 4. Act. 24.14. Mat. 5.11.</note> ſpitefull, venimous, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoking termes, brauling, rayling, &amp; reproachfull termes: and the worſt kind of rayling and reuiling, is, when men either rayle and ſpeake euill of religion it ſelfe, or do raile and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile religious perſons, becauſe they are religious and fearing God.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.14. Iudg. 8.1.2.3. Pro. 15.1.</note> wrangling and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious ſpeech betweene parties, diſagreeing either in matters of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:13990:66"/>or about worldly affaires.
<note place="margin">Philip. 2.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.31.</note> crying and vnſeemly lifting vp of the voice, when men or women, being at variance, in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate ſpeeches do, through choler and malice, lift vp their voices and ſpeake ſo loud that they may be heard afarre off.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, threatning ſpeeches, when as men or women from an inward diſlike and rage in their owne priuate cauſe,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 94.4. Act. 9.1.</note> do giue out threatning words againſt others.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, mocking, ſcoffing and deriding ſpeech,
<note place="margin">2. King. 2.23. Ioh. 19.2. Act. 2.13. 2. Sam. 6.20. Epheſ. 5.4.</note> when men or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men out of hatred and contempt of others, do either in plaine termes mocke and deride them, or do gird and taunt them, and ieſt on them by priuie and cloſe nips, thereby ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to diſgrace them, and to make themſelues and others merrie by grieuing of them; and the</p>
            <pb n="130" facs="tcp:13990:67"/>
            <p> Worſt kinde of it is, when men mocke and ſcoffe,
<note place="margin">Gen. 21.9. Galat. 4.29. 2. Chro. 39.16 Pſal. 69.11.12. Pſal. 119.51. Heb. 11 36.</note> and taunt others for well doing, and for refrayning from euill, for their pietie and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and for the vertues and graces that God hath giuen them.</p>
            <p>Outward things in deed, and thoſe are either in countenance, or in ſome geſture and carriage of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, &amp; ſome part of the body; or they be other acts and deeds. Outward things in deed, in countenance and in ſome geſture and carriage of the body, as (namely) all ſignes and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures of the body, that expreſſe raſh anger, contempt &amp; deſpite of heart towards another,
<note place="margin">Gen. 4.5. Gen. 31.2.5. 1. Sam. 25 17. Mat 9.24. Mat. 27.39.</note> or others: as low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, caſting downe of the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, diſdainful, froward and chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh behauiour, nodding or ſhaking the head in contempt, ſnuffing, tuſhing, geering, girning, flinging away in a chafe.</p>
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:13990:67"/>
            <p> Other acts and deeds, and thoſe are ſuch as either hurt or hinder a mans own life, or the life of another or others.</p>
            <p>Such as hurt and hinder a mans owne life, are either</p>
            <p>Preſent meanes of taking away of a mans own life,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.29.</note> and of ſelfe mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, (namely) ſuch as do preſently bereaue a man of his life, as when a man layes violent hands on himſelf by hanging, drowning, cutting his throate, and ſuch like: either</p>
            <p>Out of horrour of conſcience,
<note place="margin">Mat. 27.4.5. 1. Sam. 31.4. 2. Sam. 17.23.</note> and deſpaire of Gods mercie: or out of feare of worldly puniſhment or ſhame.</p>
            <p>Or out of monſtrous pride, or lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring meanes of the taking away of a mans owne life, and of ſelfe mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, (namely) ſuch euil things as fret and weaken the body, and impaire the health of it by degrees: and thoſe
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:13990:68"/>are foure eſpecially.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Pro. 23.29.30 Iſai. 5.11. Hozea. 7.5.</note> intemperancie in diet, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetting and drunkenneſſe, riot and exceſſe in eating and drinking.</p>
            <p>Secondly, idleneſſe and vnchaſtity, &amp; intemperate abuſing of the body by whoredome &amp; vncleannes,
<note place="margin">Pro. 20.4. Pro. 21.25. Pro. 2.18 19. 1. Cor. 6.18.</note> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by men or women bring grieuous and foule diſeaſes on their bodies.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">2. King. 20.7. 1. Tim. 5.23.</note> a careleſſe neglect or wilfull refuſing of the good meanes and helpes that ſerue to preſerue the life of the body, as wholeſome diet, cloathing, phyſicke, eſpecially in time of ſickneſſe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, a voluntarie ruſhing into danger, either certaine and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auoydable, or very likely, without any iuſt calling from God;
<note place="margin">Mat. 4.6.7.</note> as when men ruſh into houſes infected with the plague.</p>
            <p>Such things as hurt or hinder the life of another, or others, one or
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:13990:68"/>more; and thoſe are either proper onely to publike perſons, whether Magiſtrates or gouernors in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie; or common both to publike and priuate perſons.</p>
            <p>The things proper onely to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like perſons, whether Magiſtrates or gouernors in the familie; and thoſe are foure eſpecially:</p>
            <p n="1">1 Any wicked and vniuſt law,
<note place="margin">Exod. 1.15.16.22. Dan. 3.4.5.6. Dan. 6.6.7.8. Mat. 2.16.</note> ſtatute, ordinance, edict, charge or command, made or giuen by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like perſons and gouernours, tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly, to entrap or to deſtroy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The giuing of vniuſt and wrong iudgement,
<note place="margin">Amos 2.6. &amp; 6.12. 1. King. 21.11 12.13. Pro. 17.15.26. Luk. 23.24.25.</note> and the awar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſentence in cauſes iudiciall, contrarie to right and equitie, either to the condemning of the innocent, or to the iuſtifying and deliuering of the guiltie and euill doer.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The inflicting of vniuſt and
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:13990:69"/>vndue puniſhment on others,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 22.17.18.19. Act. 12.2. Iam. 5.6. Gen 16.6. Leuit. 25.43. Deut. 25.2.3.</note> as by puniſhing the innocent and ſuch as haue not offended, or by exerciſing tyrannous crueltie and extremity in puniſhing and correcting them that do offend.</p>
            <p>By cruell oppreſſing of others that be vnder them,
<note place="margin">Gen. 10.8.9. Ierem. 22.13.17. Micah. 3.1.2.3. Zephan. 3.3. Iam. 5 3.</note> by laying too heauie burdens on them, by getting what they can from them for their owne priuate gaine, by vſing their labours for little or no wages.</p>
            <p>The things common both to publike and priuate perſons: and thoſe are either ſuch as tend to the hurt of the body of another or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and yet for the preſent take not away the life; or ſuch as do hurt the body, and take away the life of another or others.</p>
            <p>Such things as tend to the hurt of the body of another or others, and yet for the preſent taken not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:13990:69"/>the life, are fiue eſpecially:</p>
            <p n="1">1 Hard and cruell dealing with others,
<note place="margin">1 King. 21.15.16. Pro. 11.26. Iſai. 5.8. Amos. 8.4.5.6. 1. Theſ. 4.6. 1. Cor. 6.8.10. Iam. 2.6. Exod. 22.21.22. Deut. 24.14.17. Ierem. 22.3. Zachar. 7.10. 2. King. 9.14.15. 2. King. 21.23.24. Ier. 11.19.21. Ier. 18.18. Pro. 1.11. Act. 23.12.13. Iud. epiſt. v. 9. &amp;c. 1. Sam. 18.25. Mat. 26.48. Act. 7.52. Mat. 10.21. Luk. 21.16.</note> oppreſſing and wringing them, either by incroaching on them by violent extortion, or by fraud and circumuention in bargai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or by troubling them with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt &amp; vndue courſes in law: and the</p>
            <p>Worſt kinde of oppreſſing and wringing others, is, when men op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and wring impotent, feeble, poore perſons, ſtrangers, fatherleſſe, orphanes or widdowes.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The combining with others &amp; conſpiring with them, and lying in waite for the killing, or for the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicuing of another or others.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The betraying of another or others into the hands of thoſe that vniuſtly ſeeke his or their life and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow, eſpecially the betraying of the Prince and chiefe magiſtrate, or of thoſe to whom men are bound by ſome neare and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:13990:70"/>bond.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The procuring and ſtirring vp of ſuch meanes and inſtruments,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 17.1.2.3. 2. Sam. 11.14.15. 2. Sam. 12.9. 2. Sam. 2.14.15.16.</note> as may take away the life of another or others, by counſell, by enticement, by writing, by hiring ſome to lye in waite to kill them; by ſtirring them vp either for pleaſure, or cruelty, to quarrell or fight one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Vniuſt violence with the hand in ſtriking,
<note place="margin">Exod. 2.13. Exod. 21.15. Leuit. 24.19. Deut. 27.29. Mat. 26 67. Act. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.2. 2. Cor. 11.24.25.</note> beating, wounding, or mayming of another or others; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in ſtriking, beating, woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or mayming of parents or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours.</p>
            <p>Or ſuch things as do hurt the body and take away the life of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or others: and thoſe are, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</p>
            <p>Such acts and deeds as by mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt violence ſhed the bloud, and take away the life of another or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:13990:70"/>as namely ſuch acts and deeds, whereby men do openly and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly take away the life of another or others, by ſword, dagger, knife,
<note place="margin">Gen. 4 8. 2 Sam. 3.27. 2. Sam. 4.6.7. Mat. 14.10.</note> rope, or gunne, or any like inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and meanes whatſoeuer: and this ſinne is more vile and odious when it is committed</p>
            <p>Without regard of place, calling,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 24.7.14. 1. Sam. 26.9.10.11. 1. King. 16.7.9. 2. Chro. 24.21 1. Theſſ. 2.15. Mat. 2.16.</note> and condition; as when a man open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and willingly, by ſword, dagger, knife, rope, gunne, and ſuch like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, ſheds the bloud, and takes away the life of his Prince, or other Magiſtrate ouer him, of his Paſtor, or of his maſter &amp;c. eſpecially when they are executing their office; or of an infant that cannot reſiſt him:
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.6.</note> or when a wife openly and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by ſword, dagger, knife, rope, gun, or any like inſtrument and meanes whatſoeuer, ſheds the bloud, and takes away the life of her husband;
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:13990:71"/>or the huſband by ſuch inſtruments and meanes doth take away the life of his wife.</p>
            <p>Without regard of nature,
<note place="margin">Gen. 4.8. Iudg. 9.5. 2. King. 3.27. 1. Tim. 3.9.</note> as when a brother openly and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by ſword, or other inſtruments and meanes whatſoeuer, ſheds the bloud and takes away the life of his brother or ſiſter; the father the life of the childe, and eſpecially the childe the life of the father or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Without regard of number and multitude,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 22.18.19. 2. King. 10.7. Act. 12.2.3. Gen. 34.25 &amp; 49.5.6.7.</note> as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is done on ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, by adding murder to murder; though they be ſtrangers.</p>
            <p>And this ſinne is committed, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</p>
            <p>With deliberation,
<note place="margin">Deut. 19.11.12. Gen. 4.5.8. 2. Sam. 3.27. 2. Sam. 20.9.10.</note> as when men do it out of hatred and for deſire of reuenge, and out of grudge carried in their hearts long before.</p>
            <p>Or on a ſudden, without delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:13990:71"/>as when they do it being thereunto carried,
<note place="margin">Gen. 4.23. Num. 25.16.17.18.24.25. 1. Sam. 20.30.33. 2. Sam. 2.22.23.</note> either by ſadden paſſion of anger, without all former malice, and they do it in their heat, rage and furie; or they do it in time of ſome vile and ſinful diſtemper, as in time of drunkenneſſe &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Or ſuch acts and deedes, as by ſome ſecret and cunning deuice, do ſhed the bloud, and take away the life of another or others; as namely, ſuch acts and deeds whereby men do willingly, yet vnder hand, and by meanes not preſently diſcerned, ſhed the bloud, and take away the life of another or others; which is done foure wayes:</p>
            <p n="1">1 By poyſoning another or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, wittingly and willingly,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 69.21. Mar. 36.18. Exod. 22.18. Reuel. 9.21.</note> and by poyſon killing them and berea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them of their liues.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By witch-craft, and by enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſorcery, as when men ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:13990:72"/>vſe the helpe of witches, ſorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and enchanters, and by their helpe do kill another or others. Or when witches, enchanters and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers, do of the owne accord by the helpe of the diuell, kill another or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By ſome ſubtill and craftie practiſe with others,
<note place="margin">1. King. 21.19. 2. Sam. 12.9. Act. 2.23.</note> thereby cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them to ſhed the bloud of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or others.</p>
            <p n="4">4 By conueying ſomething into the body of a woman with child,
<note place="margin">Exod. 21.22.</note> purpoſely to deſtroy it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by deſtroying the childe, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing an vntimely birth.</p>
            <p>Things of omiſſion, and thoſe are two eſpecially:</p>
            <p>The one inward in the heart, the other outward.</p>
            <p>The thing of omiſſion inward in the heart,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.30. Rom. 12.15.</note> namely, the want of pity and feeling compaſſion towards
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:13990:72"/>ſuch as are in any knowne miſery and diſtreſſe of body,
<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.12. Heb. 13.3. 1. Ioh. 3.17.</note> and are to be pitied; and men ſhew themſelues moſt wanting in pity towards ſuch as are in any knowne miſerie and diſtreſſe of body, and are to be pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied: when</p>
            <p>They inſult ouer them, and make themſelues merrie with their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 69.26. Iob. 19.21.22. Iob. 24.9.10.</note> and ſo adde to their diſtreſſe and miſerie.</p>
            <p>The outward thing of omiſſion,
<note place="margin">Pro. 21.13. Iſai. 58.7. Iob. 31.16.17 to 21.</note> namely, the omitting of the workes of mercy, that ought to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſuch as are in any knowne diſtreſſe of body; when men being able, and hauing power and means, do omit or refuſe to yeeld helpe to them, whom they ought to helpe, being any way diſtreſſed in body, &amp; knowne to them to ſtand in need of their helpe in reſpect of the body: and that is done two wayes,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:13990:73"/> 1 When men do not that good to their diſtreſſed bodies that they ought,
<note place="margin">Luke. 16.21. Mat. 25.41.42 43. Luke. 10.30.31.32. Iam. 2.15.16. 1. Sam. 20.34. &amp;c. 1. King. 18.4. Pro. 24.11.12.</note> according to their need, and according to their owne abilitie.</p>
            <p n="2">2 When they do not turne away that euill and that hurt from their bodies that they ought, being able to turne it away, either by their ſpeech, or by their hands and power any way.</p>
            <p>And the want of pitie towards ſuch as are to be pitied,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 30.11.12.13. Iob. 19.13.14. to 22. Rom. 12.20. Galat. 6.10.</note> being in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny knowne diſtreſſe of body, or the omitting of the workes of mercy, that ought to be performed to ſuch as are in any knowne diſtreſſe of body, is moſt vile and odious.</p>
            <p>When men either want pitie, or being able to yeeld helpe, do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the workes of mercy to ſuch as they are bound vnto by ſome neare and ſpeciall bond of place, calling or condition, or of nature, or grace.</p>
            <pb n="143" facs="tcp:13990:73"/>
            <p> The things hurting or hindering the life of the ſoule of man, are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</p>
            <p>Things that hurt and hinder the life of a mans owne ſoule, or the life of the ſoule of another or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, one or more.</p>
            <p>The things that hurt or hinder the life of a mans own ſoule, are two eſpecially:
<note place="margin">Pro. 6.32. &amp; 8.35. Ezec. 18.4.14 Rom. 2.5. Tit. 3.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 His ſinne againſt God, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially his liuing and continuing in any knowne ſin, wilfully and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately.</p>
            <p n="2">2 His careleſſe neglecting or wilfull reiecting,
<note place="margin">Zach. 7.11.12. Heb. 2.3. Reue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3.1.</note> of the meanes that God hath ordained to ſaluation, and for the beginning and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of ſpirituall life in the ſoule; as the word preached or read, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, prayer, and ſuch like. And this is done three wayes:</p>
            <p n="2">2 By not hearing the word
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:13990:74"/>preached ordinarily,
<note place="margin">Pro. 1.24. Pro. 28.9. Iſai. 66.4. Ierem 7.13. Act 13.46. 1. Cor. 11.26.</note> and by not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the word of God and other good bookes, and by not vſing the Sacraments, prayer, and other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordinances of God, when men may and ought to vſe them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By not yeelding to the word of God truly and faithfully prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to men,
<note place="margin">2. King. 17.13.14. Ierem. 25.4.5.6.7. Ier. 44.16.17. Ezech. 33.31. Act. 7.31. Act. 18.6. Ioh. 3.19. 2. Theſſ. 2.10.11. 2. Tim. 4.3.4. 2. Pet. 3.16.</note> and by reſiſting and withſtanding the Spirit of God in the miniſtery of his meſſengers ſent vnto them.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By giuing heed to fables and fancies, and not to the truth of the word of God in loue to it; and by corrupting, and peruerting, the word of God.</p>
            <p>The things that hurt or hinder the life of the ſoule of another or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, one or more, are theſe; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</p>
            <p>Things common to all perſons being of yeares and diſcretion, or
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:13990:74"/>proper to ſuperiours, eſpecially to Miniſters.</p>
            <p>Things common to all perſons being of yeares and diſcretion, are either</p>
            <p>Such things by which men hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der another or others, in the way of ſpirituall life and ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Or ſuch things by which men cauſe the fall or the damnation of another or others.</p>
            <p>Such things by which men hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der another or others, in the way of ſpirituall life and ſaluation are two.</p>
            <p>By giuing iuſt offence to another or others by word or deed;
<note place="margin">Mat. 16.23. Mat. 18.6.7.</note> which is done two wayes,</p>
            <p n="1">1 By leading an open wicked, ſinfull and ſcandalous life, which giueth the greateſt offence,
<note place="margin">Exod. 34.12. 2. Sam. 12.14. Pro. 29.12.</note> and doth the moſt hurt, when it is either to the iuſt offence of many:</p>
            <p>Or when a man that is of ſpeciall
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:13990:75"/>note for place,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.2. 1. Sam. 2.17. 2. Sam. 12.14.</note> calling, or for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of religion, liues wickedly, and ſcandalouſly.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By abuſing of <hi>Chriſtian libertie,</hi> in things indifferent,
<note place="margin">Mat. 17.27. Rom. 14.21. 1. Cor. 8.9.10. &amp;c. 1. Co. 10.28.29.</note> as when men vſe things indifferent, vnſeaſonably, not in fit time and place, and before fit perſons.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By daunting and diſcouraging another or others from a good and holy way,
<note place="margin">Pro. 12.18. Ezech. 13.22.</note> and from going on in the way of true holineſſe.</p>
            <p>Such things by which men cauſe the fall or damnation of another or others, are foure eſpecially:</p>
            <p n="1">1 By prouoking another or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers any way to ſinne,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.4. Ioh. 8.44. Num. 31.16. 2. Sam. 16.21. Pro. 1.10. to 14 Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 56.12. Mat 27.20. Iob. 8.20. 2. King. 3.14. Ier. 22.14.17. Ezech. 13.22.</note> as by bad counſel, by perſwaſion, or any other way by word or deed.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By encouraging and hearte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning another or others in ſinne, as by prayſing them, or countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing them when they do euill.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:13990:75"/> 3 By conſenting to another or others,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.18. Pro. 29.24. Iſai. 1.23.</note> and by partaking with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or others any way in ſinne and in doing of euill.</p>
            <p n="4">4 By ſowing diſſentions among men,
<note place="margin">Pro. 6.19. Pro. 10.12. Leuit. 19.16. Pro. 11.13. Pro. 25.9.10. Pro. 26.20. Ezech. 22.9.</note> and by ſtirring vp contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, brawles, and quarrels, between parties, eſpecially betweene ſuch as by the bond of nature or grace, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other neare bond, are ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; &amp; this is done eſpecially by carrying of tales betweene parties; and by diſcloſing both the ſecret intents, and the faults of the one to the other.</p>
            <p>Things proper to ſuperiours and eſpecially to Miniſters, are either things of omiſſion, or things of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe.</p>
            <p>Things of omiſſion, and thoſe are,</p>
            <p>Proper to ſuperiours that are not Miniſters; or to Miniſters, not as they are Miniſters, but as they are
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:13990:76"/>gouernours in their priuate families; as namely, ſuch good things omitted as ought to be performed by them to their inferiours for the good of their ſoules: which is done two wayes eſpecially,</p>
            <p n="1">1 When they vſe not the means by which their inferiours,
<note place="margin">Gen. 18.19. Deut. 6.7. Ioſh. 24.15. Epheſ. 6.4.</note> and ſuch as be any way vnder their charge, may be taught and inſtructed in the knowledge of God, and of good things that concerne their ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="2">2 When they do not hinder their inferiours and ſuch as be vnder their charge (as much as they may) from falling into ſinne;
<note place="margin">Num. 25.4. 1. Sam. 2.23.24. 1. Sam. 3.13. compared with 1. King. 20.42.</note> or do not ſeeke to reclaime them when they haue ſinned, by due reproofe, or due pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, according to their power; but rather do winke at their faults, or vſe too much lenitie in cenſuring of them.</p>
            <pb n="149" facs="tcp:13990:76"/>
            <p> Things of practiſe, and thoſe</p>
            <p>Proper to ſuperiours that are not Miniſters, or to Miniſters, not as they are Miniſters,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 101.2. Pro. 29.12. Pro. 11.29. Pro. 25.27.</note> but as they are gouernors in their priuate families, are ſuch euil things done by them as do miniſter matter of infection and poyſon to the ſoules of their inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours; as when they either teach them errors or lewd things, or elſe go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them in the practiſe of ſinne.</p>
            <p>Things of omiſſion proper to Miniſters as they be Miniſters, and haue the charge of the ſoules of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that do hurt or hinder the life of the ſoule of another or others, are two eſpecially; the one inward in the heart, and the other out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p>The inward thing in the heart, namely,
<note place="margin">Mat. 9.36. Mat. 6.34.</note> the want of pitie and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling compaſſion towards them, whoſe ſoules they haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> charge
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:13990:77"/>of, in regard of the miſeries and the wants of their ſoules; which comes from hence, becauſe they either do not ſee and take notice,
<note place="margin">Pro. 27.23.</note> or they wil not ſee and take notice, as they ought, of the miſeries and wants of the ſoules of their people, though they be told of them and made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with them.</p>
            <p>The outward thing, namely the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of ſuch good things which ought to be performed by them, to thoſe, whoſe ſoules they haue taken charge of, for the good of their ſoules: and this is done two wayes,</p>
            <p n="1">1 When through inſufficiencie,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 56.10. Ierem. 2.34. Pro. 29.18. Mat. 5.13. Mat. 15.14.</note> being Idoll paſtors, dumbe dogges, and blinde guides, they do not at all teach, and admoniſh their people of their ſinnes, and danger they are in by reaſon of their ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="2">2 When though they be able, yet either through ſloth or negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:13990:77"/>being preſent with their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; or by reaſon of their abſence,
<note place="margin">Ezec. 3.17.18 Ezec. 33.7.8. Ezech. 34.2.3 to 10. Zach. 11.15.16.17. Act. 20.26.27.28. Heb. 13.17.</note> they being not reſident and abiding among their people (as they ought) they do either not preach to their people, and admoniſh them of their ſinnes plainly and faithfully, or they preach to them very ſeldome.</p>
            <p>Things of practiſe proper to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters as they be Miniſters, and haue charge of the ſouls of others, that do hurt or hinder the life of the ſoule of another or others, are either things</p>
            <p>In their teaching; and they are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther flattering teaching,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 6.14. Ierem. 23.17.31.32. Ezech. 13.10.16. Rom. 16.18. Epheſ 4.13. 1. Tim. 3.4. Tit. 1.10. Mat. 15 4.5.6.9.</note> or corrupt teaching.</p>
            <p>Or in their manner of liuing, as namely, ſuch euill things done by them in the ſight of their people, as do miniſter matter of infection to their ſoules.</p>
            <p>As when Miniſters go on in the practiſe of ſinne openly, and do liue
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:13990:78"/>wickedly and looſely in the face of their people.
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.24. Ierem. 23.14. Galat. 2.13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It requires euery thing that ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the maintenance &amp; preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the life of man, and to the welfare and ſafety of his body and ſoule.</p>
            <p>And the things tending to the maintenance and preſeruation of the life of the body of man, and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his body are; either</p>
            <p>Such things as tend to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and preſeruation of the life of a mans owne body, and to the welfare and ſafety of his own body. Or ſuch things as tend to the maintenance and preſeruation of the life of the body of another, and to the welfare and ſafety of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of another or others.</p>
            <p>The things that tend to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and preſeruation of the life of a mans owne body, and to the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:13990:78"/>welfare and ſafety of his owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, are theſe two things:</p>
            <p n="1">1 The procuring and vſing of all good and lawfull meanes, within his power, and according to his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, that ſerue to keep and defend his body from violence, and from danger, and from hurt: and thoſe are foure eſpecially:</p>
            <p n="1">1 The turning away of vniuſt violence,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 21.8. Mat. 26.51.52 1. Pet. 2.20.</note> offered to his body by or from others, if he be able by his owne power and ſtrength, ſo farre as his place and calling will ſuffer him.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The auoyding of the hands of ſuch perſons as ſeeke by violence to hurt his body &amp; to ſhed his bloud;
<note place="margin">Gen. 27.42.43 Exod. 2.15. 1. King. 19.3. Mat. 2.13. Mat. 12.14.15 Ioh. 7.1. &amp; 8.59. Act. 14.5.6.</note> by flying from them, or by hiding himſelfe from them, he being not able to withſtand them in regard of their power and greatneſſe: if he be not hindered by his priuate or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:13990:79"/>calling.</p>
            <p n="1">1
<note n="*" place="bottom">1. King. 1.12 13.14. &amp;c. Pro. 16.15. Rom. 13.4.</note> The ſeeking and the vſing of the helpe of others, and eſpecially of the Magiſtrate as Gods lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to beepe his body from vniuſt violence.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The auoiding of ſuch things as may hurt his body,
<note place="margin">Gen. 12.10. &amp; 26.1. Ruth. 1.1. Gen. 7.7. Pro. 22.3. Luk. 21.20.21</note> as a generall famine, contagious ſickneſſe, ſword, flouds, fire, and ſuch like; by flying from them and by remouing of his body from one place to another, by ſhrowding himſelfe vnder ſome co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert, if he be not hindered by his place and calling, and ſo as it be not to the hinderance and to the hurt of another.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The procuring and vſing of all good and lawfull meanes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his abilitie and power, that are helpfull and profitable for the continuance of the health and ſtrength of his body, and for the
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:13990:79"/>preuenting of ſickneſſe and weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his body, and for the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of the health and ſtrength of his body when they are impaired; &amp; thoſe means are foure eſpecially.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Neceſſary and wholſome food,
<note place="margin">Gen. 28.20. Pro. 30.8. Mat. 6.11. 1. Tim. 5.23. Eccleſ. 10.16.17.</note> cloathing, and lodging, vſing them ſeaſonably and moderately.</p>
            <p>Honeſt and lawfull mirth, and reioycing in an holy manner, and ſometimes vſing the helpe of Muſicke,
<note place="margin">2. King. 3.15. Pro. 15.13. Pro. 17.22. Nehem. 8.10. Eccleſ. 3.4. Philip. 4.4. Exod. 21.19. 2. King. 20.7. Ierem. 8.22. Mat. 9.12. 2. Chro. 16.12</note> by ſinging or playing on an inſtrument of Muſick, or by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring others ſing or play; ſo as it be with moderation, and in due time and ſeaſon.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The helpe of <hi>Phyſicke</hi> and <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie</hi> as occaſion is giuen, vſing good and lawful medicines; and not truſting in them, as able to do any good of themſelues, but intreating the Lord for a bleſſing on them.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Honeſt and lawfull exerciſe,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:13990:80"/>mouing and ſtirring of his body,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.23. 2. Sam. 1.18. Gen. 27.3.</note> and that ſeaſonably and in fit time and place, without the iuſt offence of any; and that more or leſſe as the ſtate of his body requires, and as his calling will ſuffer him, as walking running, leaping, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>Such things as tend to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and preſeruation of the life of the body of another, and to the welfare and ſafetie of the body of another, are either,</p>
            <p>Inward in the heart, or outward things.</p>
            <p>Things inward in the heart,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.32. Galat 5.22. Coloſſ. 3.12.</note> are foure eſpecially.</p>
            <p n="1">1 A kinde and louing diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the heart, or kinde heartednes towards all, whereby men or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are tractable and eaſie to be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and to be employed for the good of others whoſoeuer they be, in any thing wherein they may do
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:13990:80"/>them good, as occaſion is offered, without hurt or wrong to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues or others.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Such a meeke quiet,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.11. Mat. 11.29. Epheſ. 4.2. Galat. 5.23. Coloſſ. 3.12. 1. Pet. 3 4. Num. 12.3. Pro. 14.29. Pro. 15.18. 1. Cor. 13.4. Galat. 5.22. Coloſſ. 3.13.</note> and calme diſpoſition of the heart, as is neither prone to prouoke, nor eaſily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked to anger, by iniuries or wrongs offered or done. The high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree whereof is long ſuffering, which is when men or women, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much or often prouoked by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurious words and deedes, do not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding quietly paſſe them ouer, and put them vp, and are ſtill quiet and calme, and not prouoked to anger: which meekeneſſe and long ſuffering is to be expreſſed;</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Galat. 6.2. Epheſ 4.2. Coloſſ. 3.13.</note> in a quiet bearing with the infirmities &amp; frailties of others, as their haſtineſſe, ſlowneſſe, raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſuch like: and with the paſſions and perturbations ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in their actions, ſo farre
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:13990:81"/>forth as they are troubleſome, grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and diſpleaſing to vs.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in a free remiſſion of reuenge,
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.12. Epheſ. 4.32. Coloſſ. 3.13.</note> neither carrying in our hearts any purpoſe of reuenge for wrongs done to vs, or ſuppoſed to be done to vs; or returning pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment and euill for euill, in way of requitall for them.</p>
            <p n="3">3 An inward fellow-feeling of that which befals others in reſpect of their bodies,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.15. 1. Cor. 12.25.26.</note> and that two wayes:</p>
            <p>Firſt, by reioycing with others that haue iuſt cauſe of reioycing,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 35.27. Luk. 1.58. Philip. 1.26.</note> for their outward good and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie ſeene or heard of.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 35.13.14 Epheſ. 4.32. Coloſſ. 3.13. Heb. 13.3. 1 Pet. 3.8.</note> by mourning and grieuing with others that haue iuſt cauſe of heauineſſe, mourning, and griefe, for their outward euill, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe and aduerſitie, ſeene or heard of; and by pitying them, and by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tender hearted to them.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:13990:81"/> 4 An heart diſpoſed to peace and quietneſſe,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.18. Galat. 5.22. Coloſſ. 3.15. 1. Theſſ. 4.11.</note> and a care and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to maintaine concord and good agreement amongſt men, as much as is poſſible &amp; in our power; which is to be expreſſed in three things e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially:</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Pro. 17.14. Pro. 19.11. Pro. 20.3. Iam. 3.17. Gen. 13.8.9. Mat. 17.27.</note> in paſſing by offences ſo farre as they concerne vs in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and may be paſſed ouer without hurt or wrong to our ſelues, or to others; and ſometimes for quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſake, in parting from our own right.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in conſtruing things in the beſt ſence,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 10.3. 1. Cor. 13.5.</note> and taking euery thing (if it be poſſible) in the beſt part.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in medling with our owne matters and buſineſſes,
<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 4.11. 1. Pet. 4.15.</note> and ſuch things as concerne vs in regard of our callings and conditions of life.</p>
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:13990:82"/>
            <p> Outward things are either ſuch as ſerue to auert and turne away e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, wrong, hurt, or danger from the body of another or others: Or, ſuch as ſerue for the good, the helpe and comfort of the body of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or others.</p>
            <p>Such as ſerue to auert and turne away euill, wrong, hurt, or danger from the body of another or others, are either, in ſpeech and in word: Or in act and deed.</p>
            <p>In ſpeech or in word, as namely, ſuch words and ſpeeches vttered,
<note place="margin">Pro. 12.6. Pro. 24.11.12</note> as are for the defence and helpe of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent perſons that are helpeleſſe, being either vnder the hands of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors, or followed and purſued by oppreſſors, ſeeking to hurt and to wrong them either in their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies or liues; and men are to ſpeake for the defence and helpe of ſuch perſons three wayes:</p>
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:13990:82"/>
            <p> Firſt, by ſpeaking for them as they are able,
<note place="margin">Gen 37.21.22 1 Sam. 20.32. Heſt. 7.3.4.5.6.</note> and according to their place and calling, in priuate to the face of the oppreſſor or oppreſſors, to diſſwade him or them from offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or doing wrong vnto them in reſpect of their bodies and liues.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by ſpeaking and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for them as they are able,
<note place="margin">Heſt. 4.8. Iob. 29.12.13 to 18. Ierem. 38.7.8 9. Luk. 23.13.14 to. 22.</note> and according to their place and calling, either as witneſſes, or as aduocates, or as Iudges publikely in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Court, for the freeing of them from wrong done or offered to be done to them, in reſpect of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies or liues; eſpecially they being poore, fatherleſſe, widdowes, or ſtrangers; or being religious, and yet ſuch as either cannot or dare not pleade for themſelues.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">Act 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.4.5. Rom. 15 30.31.</note> by ſpeaking to God for them as they are able, in prayer, by commending their caſe to the
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:13990:83"/>Lord,
<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 3.1.2</note> and calling on him in prayer for their ſuccour and reliefe.</p>
            <p>In act and deed, as namely, ſuch acts &amp; deeds done,
<note place="margin">Exod. 2.17.18.19. Iudg. 2.16. Iud. 3.9.15.31</note> as are for the help &amp; ſuccor of innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t perſons, that are helpleſſe, being either vnder oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and wrong, or purſued by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors, ſeeking to hurt or wrong them in their bodies or liues. And men are to do things, ſeruing for the helpe and ſuccour of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, either</p>
            <p>Againſt known euils and wrongs already done to them,
<note place="margin">Gen. 14 14.15.16. 1. Sam. 30.17.18. Iob. 29.12.17. Pro. 24.11.</note> and that as they are able, and according to their place and calling, by vſing their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and ſtrength for the reſcuing and deliuering them from vnder their oppreſſions and wrongs:</p>
            <p>Or againſt knowne euils and wrongs that are in doing, or inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be done to them, and that as they are able, by interpoſing their power and ſtrength to defend and
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:13990:83"/>to ſaue them from thoſe euils and wrongs. And that either,</p>
            <p>As priuate perſons, by vſing their hands, their purſes,
<note place="margin">Ioſh. 2.4.6. 1. King. 18.4. 2. Sam. 21.14.15.16. Rom. 16.14. 1. Ioh. 3.16.</note> and their paines, ſo farre as they are able to protect and to ſaue them from vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence or ſpoyle, eſpecially when the violence or ſpoyle intended, is ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and the Magiſtrate is abſent, &amp; it is dangerous to ſtay for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; &amp; ſometimes ſo far, as to the hazard of their owne liues, as when it is to the defending and ſauing of the bodies and liues of ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are ſpeciall inſtruments of Gods glory, and of common good, either in Church or Commonwealth:</p>
            <p>Or, as Magiſtrates, by drawing out and vſing the ſword according to their place and power,
<note place="margin">Exod. 18.21. Rom. 13.4. Exod. 2.11.12 Act. 7.24.</note> to protect and to ſaue them from violence or hurt, whether it be in doing, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be done, either by their
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:13990:84"/>owne ſubiects, or by forreiners.</p>
            <p>Such things as ſerue for the good, the helpe and comfort of the body of another or others, are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</p>
            <p>In ſpeech or word, or in act and deed.</p>
            <p>Things in ſpeech or word, as namely,
<note place="margin">Tit. 3.2. 1. Pet 3.16.</note> ſuch words &amp; ſuch ſpeeches vttered and ſpoken, as do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe meekneſſe, gentleneſſe, kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and loue to thoſe to whom they are vttered and ſpoken. And the words and ſpeeches wherein men are to expreſſe meekneſſe, gentleneſſe, kindneſſe and loue, are of three ſorts eſpecially:</p>
            <p n="1">1 Their ſalutations,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.38. &amp; 20.16. Iudg. 6.12. Ruth. 2.4. Luke. 1.28. &amp; 10.5. Ioh. 20.19.</note> when they meete with others, they are to ſalute them being their equals or inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, by their names or ſurnames; &amp; their ſuperiours, by names of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or office, giuing them ſuch
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:13990:84"/>tiles of reuerence, as of right belong to them, wiſhing them good health, proſperity or good ſucceſſe, and the like, as occaſion is offered.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Their anſwers; men are to giue to others ſoft anſwers,
<note place="margin">Iudg. 8.2.3. 1. Sam. 25.10 11.12.13. Pro 15.1. 2. King. 18.36 1. Sam. 1.15. Dan. 6.21.22. Ioh. 8.48.49. 1. Pet. 3.9. Gen. 13.8. Galat. 6.1.</note> ſuch as may neither kindle nor increaſe anger in them; and when they are rayled on, they are not to rayle againe, and when they are hardly ſpoken of, they are either to be ſilent, or onely to make a iuſt and manifeſt defence of their owne innocencie.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Their admonitions and iuſt reproofes, when men do admoniſh or iuſtly reproue their brethren for their faults committed of ignorance or of frailtie,</p>
            <p>Or in act and deed: and thoſe are either,</p>
            <p>In countenance and in ſome ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture and carriage of the body,
<note place="margin">Gen. 31.2.5. Gen. 30.10.</note> as namely, all ſuch lookes and geſtures
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:13990:85"/>of the body as do expreſſe meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.17. Pro. 16.15. Gen. 2.3.7.12</note> gentleneſſe, kindneſſe, and loue to another or others, without diſſimulation:</p>
            <p>Or other acts and deeds; and thoſe are of two ſorts:</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſuch acts and deeds done, as do expreſſe kindneſſe and loue to thoſe to whom they are done,
<note place="margin">Gen. 14 18.31 2. Sam. 19.28.31. 1. King. 10.10 13. Ierem. 40.5. Act. 20.38.</note> and are for the continuance of the health, welfare, comfort and good eſtate of the body of another, or the bodies of others; as the beſtowing of gifts and benefites, and good turnes on others.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſuch acts and deeds done as do expreſſe kindneſſe and loue,
<note place="margin">Iob. 31.16.17. to 21. Pro. 21.13. Pro. 31.20. Iſai. 58.7. Mat. 25.35.36.42.43.</note> and tender affection to thoſe to whom they are done, and are for the relieuing of another or others, being in any knowne want or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe of body. And men are to reach out their helping hands ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:13990:85"/>to their abilitie and means, for the reliefe of ſuch:</p>
            <p>Sometimes to the entertainment of them to bed, or board, or both,
<note place="margin">Iob. 31.32. Iud. 19.20.21. Rom. 12.13. Heb. 13.2. 1. Pet. 4.9.</note> eſpecially they being ſtrangers and harbourleſſe, &amp; for the Lords cauſe, and for a good conſcience perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.</p>
            <p>And eſpecially to ſuch as they are bound vnto,
<note place="margin">Iob. 19.13.14. to 22. Leuit. 25.35. Rom. 12.13. Galat. 6.10.</note> by ſome neare and ſpeciall bond of place, calling or condition, or of nature or grace.</p>
            <p>The dutie that belongs to the dead body of another,
<note place="margin">Gen. 23.19. Gen. 25.9. Gen. 50.13. Ierem. 22.19. Mat. 27.60. Act. 8.2. 1. Theſſ. 4.13.</note> is the buriall of it, in ſuch honeſt and ſeemly manner, as is agreable to the nature and credit, as well of thoſe which remaine aliue, as of the partie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſſed, with moderate mourning.</p>
            <p>The things tending to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and preſeruation of the life of the ſoule of man, and to the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and ſafetie of the ſoule, are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</p>
            <pb n="168" facs="tcp:13990:86"/>
            <p> Such things as tend to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and preſeruation of the life of a mans owne ſoule, and the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and ſafetie of his owne ſoule; or ſuch things as tend to the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and preſeruation of the life of the ſoule of another or others, and to the welfare and ſafetie of the ſoule of another or others.</p>
            <p>The things which tend to the maintenance and preſeruation of the life of a mans owne ſoule, and the welfare and ſafetie of his owne ſoule, are two things eſpecially:</p>
            <p>Firſt, a carefull auoyding of all ſuch things as tend to the deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his owne ſoule,
<note place="margin">Pro. 4.14.15. Pro. 5.8.11. Pro. 7.25.26.27. Pro. 11.19. Rom. 2.5. 1. Pet. 3.10.11.</note> as all ſorts of ſinnes, eſpecially known ſinnes, and the liuing and continuing in any knowne ſinne, willingly and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, and with delight.</p>
            <p>Secondly, a carefull vſe of the meanes that God hath ordained,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:13990:86"/>both for the beginning,
<note place="margin">Deut. 30.19.20. Rom. 10.14.17. 1. Pet. 2.2. Pro. 2.1.2.3. Pro. 4.20.21. Pro 7.1.2.3.4. Pro. 8.33. Iſai. 55.3. Coloſſ. 3.16. 1. Theſſ. 2.13 Pro. 16.14. Epheſ. 2.10. Philip. 2.12. 1. Pet. 1.5.6. to 12. Pſal. 92.14. 2. Pet. 3.18.</note> and for the continuance of grace and of ſpirituall life in the ſoule, both in publike and in priuate; as the word preached or read, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, prayer and ſuch like, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending on them diligently, and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them conſcionably, with care to profite by them, and a carefull walking in the way of life and of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, by diligence to finiſh his own ſaluation, by adding daily one meaſure of grace to another, and by making his owne calling and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection ſure by the fruites of faith.</p>
            <p>The things which tend to the maintenance and preſeruation of the life of the ſoule of another or others, and to the welfare and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the ſoule of another or others, are ſuch things as ſerue either for the procuring or helping forward of the ſpirituall life and ſaluation of
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:13990:87"/>another or others one,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.33. Pro. 11.30. Dan. 12.3. Rom. 15.2. Iam. 5.19.20.</note> or more; as by doing ſuch things as tend to the winning of their ſoules, &amp; to their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification and building vp in grace and goodneſſe: and the things that men are to do tending to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, are ſixe:</p>
            <p n="1">1 They are as they are able, and according to their place &amp; calling,
<note place="margin">Gen. 18.18.19 Deut. 6.7. Pro. 1.10. Pro. 31.1. Ioh. 1.35.36. to 45.</note> and as preſent occaſion is offered, to teach and to inſtruct others to know God and the good wayes of God, and to counſell and to aduiſe them in ſuch things as concerne their ſanctification and ſaluation, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſuch as be vnder their charge, they being ſuch as haue the gouernment of others,
<note place="margin">Act. 20.26.27 Coloſſ. 3.16.</note> and are ouer others in publike or in priuate, as Miniſters or gouernours in the familie.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, they are as they are able, and according to their place
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:13990:87"/>and calling, and as preſent occaſion is offered,
<note place="margin">Pro. 27.27. Heb. 10.24. 2. Chro. 19.9. 1. Chro. 20.20 2. Chro. 32.7. 1. Theſſ. 5.11. 1. Tim. 5.1.2. Heb. 3.13. Rom. 13.3. 1. Cor. 11.2.</note> to prouoke and to excite and ſtirre vp others to holineſſe and wel-doing, &amp; to harten and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them in wel-doing, eſpecially ſuch as be vnder their charge, they being ſuch as haue the gouernment of others; and that by perſwading &amp; exhorting them to good things, and by prayſing, commending and countenancing them when they do well.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Thirdly,
<note place="margin">Leuit. 19.17. Luke. 17.3. Coloſſ. 3.16. 1. Theſſ. 5.14. 2. Tim. 4.2. Tit. 2. Galat. 6.1 1. Tim. 5.1.2.</note> they are as they are able, and according to their place and calling, and as preſent occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is offered, to admoniſh and to reproue others, when they ſee or know them to offend, and to do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and ſinne; ſo as they do it fitly, fitting their reproofe to the qualitie of the perſon, whom they do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue, and the nature and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the offence, for which the
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:13990:88"/>perſon is reproued,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.1. Tit. 1.13. Nehem. 5.7. Iob. 2.10. Pro. 29.17.19</note> and ſo as they do it ſeaſonably, and in ſuch a time as their reproofe may do the moſt good. Iude epiſt. v. 22.23. 2. Cor. 13.2.</p>
            <p n="4">4 They are,
<note place="margin">Gen. 50.21. 1. Sam. 23.16. 2. Sam. 10.2. Iob. 6.14.15. Iſai. 40.1.2. Mat. 14 27. 1. Theſſ. 4.18. 1. Theſſ. 5.14. Iob. 16.2. Iob. 19.21. Iſai. 50.4.</note> as they are able, and according to their place &amp; calling; and as preſent occaſion is offered, to comfort others when they ſee or know them to ſtand in neede of comfort, in regard of their troubles and diſtreſſes, eſpecially in regard of troubles, afflictions and diſtreſſes of their mindes and conſciences for ſinne; ſo as they do it wiſely, with due conſideration of the qualitie of the perſon afflicted, and ſo as they do it in ſuch a time as comfort may do the partie afflicted moſt good.</p>
            <p n="5">5 They are, as they are able, and according to their place and calling,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 42.2.3 Gen. 43.29. Gen. 48.15.</note> and as preſent occaſion is offered, to pray for others ſtanding
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:13990:88"/>in need of their prayers,
<note place="margin">1 Chro. 22.12. Iames 5.15</note> for the good of their ſoules; eſpecially for ſuch as they are bound vnto by ſome neare and ſpeciall bond of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, place, calling or condition.</p>
            <p n="6">6 They are, as they are able, and according to place and calling,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.16. 2 Cor. 9.2. 1 Pet. 2.12. 1 Pet. 3.6.</note> and as preſent occaſion is offered, to giue good example to others, liuing in their ſight without giuing iuſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and walking before them in the practiſe of good things; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to ſuch as they are bound vnto by ſome neare and ſpeciall bond of nature, place, calling, or condition.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the ſixth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="commandment">
            <pb n="174" facs="tcp:13990:89"/>
            <head>The 7. Commandement. <hi>The Negatiue part.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>It forbids all manner of vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and fleſhly defilement, and all things that hurt or hinder chaſtitie in man or woman; and theſe things are either Inward or Outward.</p>
            <p>Inward, in the heart, as namely, filthie imaginations,
<note place="margin">Matt. 5.28.</note> and vnchaſte thoughts,
<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.5.</note> and inward luſts and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the heart, to vncleanneſſe, whereunto the heart doth giue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; or purpoſes and deſires of the heart to any act of vncleanneſſe and fleſhly defilement, which are then moſt vile and moſt odious, when they are ſo violent and ſtrong, as that they continually boyle and burne within, and giue a man or a
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:13990:89"/>woman no reſt, but are euer ſtirring and prouoking them to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of ſome filthie act of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe.</p>
            <p>Outward, and thoſe are either things going before the act of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe and fleſhly defilement, or the acts of vncleanneſſe and fleſhly pollution.</p>
            <p>Things going before the act of vncleanneſſe &amp; fleſhly defilement, are either further off, as prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues and prouocations to it, or nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to it, than preparatiues and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocations.</p>
            <p>Further off, as preparatiues and prouocations to it; and thoſe are either ſuch things as ſtirre vp filthie luſt, and make the bodie fit for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, or ſuch things as helpe forward the fitneſſe of the body for vncleanneſſe. Such things as ſtir vp filthy luſt, and make the bodie fit
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:13990:90"/>for vncleanneſſe,
<note place="margin">Ier. 5.8. Eze. 16.49. Rom. 13.13 Hoſea 7.6. Gen. 19.31, 33, 34, 35. Pro. 23.30, 31, 33. Iſay 5.11. Rom. 13.13 Epheſ. 5.18 Deut. 23.10</note> and thoſe are,</p>
            <p>Firſt, gluttony, or exceſſe in eating, and pampering of the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with meats.</p>
            <p>Secondly, drunkenneſſe, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in drinking.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, luſtfull dreames, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from ſurfetting and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, from whence come noctur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall pollutions.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Idleneſſe, as when men or women ſpend their ſtrength,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 11.1. Eze. 16.49. 1 Tim. 5.13</note> and the time God giues them, wherein they ought to be imployed in ſome honeſt labours of minde or bodie, in exceſſiue ſleeping, and in ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſhneſſe, in eaſe and in doing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but following their ſenſuall pleaſures.</p>
            <p>Such things as helpe forward the fitneſſe of the bodie for vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and thoſe are,</p>
            <p n="1">1 Any light,
<note place="margin">Ezec. 16.49</note> vaine, immodeſt
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:13990:90"/>either ſetting out of the bodie,
<note place="margin">Prou. 7.10. 1 Tim. 2.9, 10. 1 Pet. 3.3. 1 Cor. 11.14. 2 King. 9.30. Ier. 4.30. Iſai. 3.16, 17, 18, 19, &amp;c.</note> or carrying of the bodie in diuers particulars, as namely, by riotous, laſciuious, gariſh, diſguiſed, and new-fangled attire, long ſhagge haire, by platting, curling, frizling, or powdering the haire, or by wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring falſe haire, painting the face, laying out of the naked breſts, ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching out of the necke, tinckling with the feet, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The keeping company with laſciuious, wanton,
<note place="margin">Gen. 39.10 Pſal. 50.18. Prou. 5.8. &amp; 7.7, 8, 9, 10. Eph. 5.5.7.</note> and filthie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and the frequenting of lewd houſes, houſes of filthineſſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Immodeſt, vnchaſte, ribald and filthie ſpeaking, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4 20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.3, 4. Coloſſ. 3.8.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The reading of vnchaſte and filthie bookes, bookes of loue mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, of dalliance and filthineſſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.33. <hi>Act.</hi> 19.19.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Idle and curious looking of
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:13990:91"/>men vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> women, or of women vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on men, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 39.7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 34.1, 2.</p>
            <p n="6">6 The looking vpon laſciuious,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 11.2 Iob 31.1. 2 Pet. 2.14. Numb. 15.1, 2, 3. Ezech. 23.14, 15, 16. Eph. 5.3, 4.</note> filthie, and vnſeemely pictures, and the beholding of loue-matters, and the light behauiour of men or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, repreſented and ſet out, not only by ſpeech, but by geſture, and by conueyances and deuices in ſtage-playes and comedies.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Immodeſt and wanton dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing,
<note place="margin">Exod. 32.6. Iob 21.11, 12. Mark. 6.21, 22.</note> mixt dancing of men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men together in number and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure artificially, eſpecially after ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Feaſts, and at merrie mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings.</p>
            <p>Things nearer to it than prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues &amp; prouocations, &amp; thoſe are,</p>
            <p n="1">1 The wearing of apparell not fit for the ſex, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.5. <hi>Iob</hi> 24.15. <hi>Gen.</hi> 38.15.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Wanton kiſſing, and embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, &amp; vnchaſte touching and dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:13990:91"/>
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.12. <hi>Prou.</hi> 7.13. <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.11, 12.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The mouing, and entiſing, and perſwading to the very act of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe and fleſhly, pollution, <hi>Gen.</hi> 38.7, 10, 12. <hi>Prou.</hi> 7.14 to 21.</p>
            <p>The acts of vncleanneſſe and fleſhly pollution, which are either with ones ſelfe or with others.</p>
            <p>With ones ſelfe; and chaſtitie is hurt or hindered in man or woman with themſelues,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.9.</note> by effeminat wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, and by doing as <hi>Onan</hi> did, <hi>Gen.</hi> 38.9. when men or women a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe their owne bodies, and by any way or meanes prouoke and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure themſelues to doe as he did.</p>
            <p>With others, with one other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, or with many others.</p>
            <p>With one other alone, which is either by married perſons, man and wife betweene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, or by ſuch as are not maried one to another.</p>
            <pb n="180" facs="tcp:13990:92"/>
            <p> By maried perſons, man and wife betweene themſelues, and that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in reſpect of their entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mariage, or in regard of their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter proceeding and vſe of mariage.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of their entrance into mariage,
<note place="margin">Exo. 22.16, 17. Deut. 7.3. Ier. 29.6. 1 Cor. 7.38</note> which is, when they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany together and haue ſecret ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie one with another, as man and wife; and yet are either ſuch as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into that ſtate without due conſent of their parents, neither ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it at the time of their entrance, nor hauing gained it afterwards.</p>
            <p>Or they are ſuch as ought not to haue maried together, being within the degrees of conſanguinitie or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitie forbidden in the word of God, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 18, 6. to 18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.20, 21. <hi>Mark.</hi> 6.18. 1 Cor. 5.1.</p>
            <p>In regard of their after procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and vſe of mariage, and that two waies:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:13990:92"/> 1 When they vſe the mariage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed intemperately and immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, not for procreation, or for yeelding the due beneuolence or debt one to another, or for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoiding of fornication, but meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the ſatisfaction of their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridled pleaſures, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.4, 5. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.4.</p>
            <p n="2">2 When they vſe the mariage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed vnſeaſonably, and that is done two waies:</p>
            <p>Firſt, if they know each other carnally, whileſt it is with the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man after the manner of women, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.11. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 18.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.18. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18.6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22.10.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if they know each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther carnally in the time of publike humiliation, in the time of a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Faſt, taken vp and vſed in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of ſome grieuous calamitie, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther imminent or like to fall on the
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:13990:93"/>Church or Common-weale, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie vpon it, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.11. <hi>Ioel</hi> 2.16. <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.12. 1 Cor. 7.5.</p>
            <p>By ſuch as are not maried one to another, and that two waies:</p>
            <p n="1">1 When ſuch as are not maried one to another, doe commit ſome act of vncleanneſſe and fleſhly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filement one with another, which is vnnaturall, and againſt nature; and that is done three waies:</p>
            <p n="1">1 By Sodomitrie, which is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe and defilement of the bodie, committed betweene them that are of one and the ſame ſex, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 18.22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.26, 27. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By beaſtialitie, which is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe and defilement of the bodie, committed by man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with a bruit beaſt, <hi>Leuit,</hi> 18.23. and 20.15, 16.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By vncleanneſſe and defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:13990:93"/>of the bodie, committed by man or woman with the Deuill, as Witches doe, by their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.1.</p>
            <p n="2">2 When ſuch as are not maried one to another, doe commit ſome act of vncleanneſſe and defilement of the bodie one with another, which is naturall, and according to the courſe of nature corrupted; and that is done two waies:</p>
            <p n="1">1 By committing the ſinne of Inceſt, which is vncleanneſſe and defilement of the bodie, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted betweene man and woman that are neare in bloud, and of kindred one to another, either by conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinitie or affinitie, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.33. to 37. <hi>&amp;</hi> 35.22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 49.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 38.18. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.14. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 22.11. <hi>Mark.</hi> 6.18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By vncleanneſſe and defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the bodie, committed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:13990:94"/>man and woman that are not neare in bloud, nor of kindred one to another, either by conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinitie or affinitie; and that is done two waies:</p>
            <p n="1">1 By fornication, which is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe and defilement of the bodie, committed betweene man and woman, being both ſingle and vnmaried perſons, <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.8. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.4.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By adultery, which is vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or defilement of the bodie, committed betweene man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, being either both of them maried perſons, or one of them a maried perſon, or at leaſt contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.10. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 18.20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.10. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.4. <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.7.8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.22. And Inceſt, Fornication, or Adultery is moſt vile, and moſt odious, when it is committed by violence and
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:13990:94"/>force, which is called Rape, <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.2. <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.25. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.14.</p>
            <p>The acts of vncleanneſſe and fleſhly pollution of the body, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted with many others, and that two waies:</p>
            <p n="1">1 By vncleanneſſe and fleſhly defilement, committed by man or by woman with many others at large, as when a man commits fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe with many women, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they be; or when a woman doth proſtitute her bodie to many men, and commits filthineſſe with many men, whatſoeuer they be, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19.29 <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.17. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16.28, 29. <hi>Hozea</hi> 4.2.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By vncleanneſſe &amp; defilement of the body,
<note place="margin">Gen. 4.14. &amp; 2.14. Deut. 17.17 Mat. 19.5. Leu. 18.18. Malac. 2.15</note> committed by man or by woman, with many others, to whom they ſeeme to be bound by the bond of mariage; as when a man hath more than one wife at
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:13990:95"/>one and the ſame time, and hath carnall copulation with them: or when a woman hath more than one husband, at one and the ſame time, and hath carnall coniunction with them.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Affirmatiue part of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth Commandement.</head>
               <p>It requires in generall two things:</p>
               <p n="1">1 Chaſtity both inward and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, which is cleanneſſe and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie both of the ſoule and of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of man or woman, touching the matter of generation. And inward chaſtitie, and cleanneſſe, and purity of the ſoule of man or woman, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the matter of generation, ſtands in a freedome by grace from fleſhly concupiſcence,
<note place="margin">Matt. 5.28. &amp; 15.19. 1 Cor. 7.34 Coloſſ. 3.5.</note> the heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by grace free from filthie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:13990:95"/>and vnchaſte thoughts, and from inward filthie luſts, and from purpoſes and deſires to any act of vncleanneſſe and fleſhly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filement.</p>
               <p>And outward chaſtitie, and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and puritie of the bodie of man or woman touching the matter of generation,
<note place="margin">Gen. 39.8, 9, 10, 12. 1 Cor. 7.1. 1 Theſſ. 4.3, 4. 1 Tim. 4.12 Reuel. 14.4</note> ſtands in not putting in execution the concupiſcence of the fleſh in any act of vncleanneſſe and fleſhly defilement, in any kind whatſoeuer, either with themſelues or with others, be it with one other or with many others.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A carefull vſing of ſuch things as are helpes to preſerue chaſtitie, and doe tend to the preſeruation of cleanneſſe and puritie both inward and outward, both of the ſoule and of the body of man or woman, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the matter of generation, and thoſe are ſeuen things:</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="188" facs="tcp:13990:96"/> 1 The feare of God eſpecially, a feare of God in reſpect of his Word and Commandement, that forbids vncleanneſſe and fleſhly defilement both of ſoule and body, in any kind whatſoeuer, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 39.9. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.28.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A true delight in the word of God, and in his holy ordinances, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.9. <hi>Prou.</hi> 2.10.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.1, 2, 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.20. to 24.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Modeſtie or ſhamefaſtneſſe, which is an holy abhorring of all filthineſſe and fleſhly defilement, accompanied with a carefull obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of Chriſtian comlineſſe, and with a certaine griefe and feare, leſt any thing vncomely ſhould bee committed, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.3.4. which is to be expreſſed,</p>
               <p n="1">1 In the ſpeech and in the words of men and women, namely, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent talke and chaſte ſpeeches, they
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:13990:96"/>vſing as ſeemely words as may be choſen, when they are to mention things that may moue bluſhing, and vſing little and ſubmiſſe ſpeech, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Pſal</hi> 51. in the title, <hi>Prou.</hi> 10.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.11.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In countenance and geſture, and the carriage of the bodie and outward behauiour, men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſo looking and carrying their eies and countenances, as that they neither thereby expreſſe the filthie luſts of their owne hearts, nor giue iuſt occaſion to ſtirre vp the concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence of heart in others, and in grauitie in their carriage and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward behauiour, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.65. <hi>Iob</hi> 31.1. <hi>Prou.</hi> 6.25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.13. <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.3.7.</p>
               <p n="3">3 In apparell,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.9, 10. 1 Pet. 3.3, 4</note> men and women are to couer their bodies with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and comely apparell, and that decencie and comlineſſe in apparel
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:13990:97"/>ſtands in two things: Firſt, in coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the whole bodie with it, ſome parts excepted, as the hands and face, for neceſſities ſake, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.10.21. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.48. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16.7, 8. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, in being decent and come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the forme and faſhion of it, which is, when it is according to the ſexe, and according to the office and calling, order and degree, that men or women haue in the ſocieties of men, publike or priuate, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their abilitie, and framed according to the ancient cuſtome of the place and Countrie where they liue, and to the example of the graueſt, and the moſt godly, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber minded men and women of their owne place, order, degree and age, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.5. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.8. <hi>Zephan.</hi> 1.8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. <hi>Philip.</hi> 4.8. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.5.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Temperance or ſobriety, which
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:13990:97"/>is a moderate and ſober vſe of ſuch things as belong to the bodie,
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.23. 1 Tim. 3.2. Tit. 1.8. &amp; 2.12. 2 Pet. 1.6.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to time, place, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which is to be exerciſed and expreſſed,</p>
               <p n="1">1 In diet,
<note place="margin">Pro. 23.29. to 33. Eccle. 7.10. Luke 21.34 Ephe. 5.18. 1 Cor. 9.27 2 Cor. 6.6.</note> men and women vſing meats and drinkes, ſo farre forth as they may ſerue to refreſh nature, and to make them fit for the ſeruice of God and man, and ſometimes in conuenient abſtinence, abſtaining from the neceſſarie and ordinarie food of their bodies, for a time, as need doth require, and as their ſtrength may beare, without abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing and deſtroying nature.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In ſleepe, men and women ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſo much ſleepe as may make them better able to doe all the good duties that concerne them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and men;
<note place="margin">Pro. 20.13. 2 Cor. 6.6. &amp; 11.22.</note> ſometimes refraining from ſleep, and watching as need requires, and as they are
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:13990:98"/>able, ſo as it be not to the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of nature.</p>
               <p n="3">3 In lawfull pleaſures and honeſt delights, men and women vſing them only ſo farre forth as they be no prouocations to fleſhly luſt, nor hinderances to them in good du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties towards God or man, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.29, 30. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.13.</p>
               <p n="5">5 In diligence and painfulneſſe in good duties:
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 11.2, 3, 4. Ezech. 16.49. 1 Tim. 5.13</note> men and women are euer to be doing ſome good thing, either in their generall cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, as they be Chriſtians, or in their particular callings. And the beſt good thing wherein they are to be diligent and painfull, is prayer to God, that he would purifie and purge their hearts from filthie luſts, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7, 8.</p>
               <p n="6">6 In the ſingle eſtate, hauing not the gift of continencie, taking the benefit of holy mariage, when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:13990:98"/>meanes auaile not, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.2.9.36. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3.</p>
               <p n="7">7 In the ſtate of mariage, the huſbands affecting of his wife, and the wifes affecting of her huſband, as they ought to affect one the other, and alſo the doing of that one to the other that ought to be done, for the preſeruing of pure loue, and of ſound and heartie affection be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, and for the keeping of themſelues faithfull and conſtant one to the other: and they affect one the other as they ought,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 5.25.29. Col. 3.19. Tit. 2.4. Prou. 5.18, 19. Gen. 24.67</note> when they loue one another with a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent and pure loue, expreſſing that in delighting in the loue one of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other continually, and cheriſhing one the other as they are able. And they doe that one to the other that ought to be done, for the preſerving of pure loue and of ſound and heartie affection betweene them,
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:13990:99"/>and for the keeping of themſelues faithfull and conſtant one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther three waies:</p>
               <p n="1">1 By their quiet and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dwelling together in one place, with no longer abſence of either from other, than ſhall be either on neceſſary occaſion, or with mutuall conſent, <hi>Deut.</hi> 24.5. <hi>Prou.</hi> 7.20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10.12.13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7.</p>
               <p n="2">2 By ſo carrying themſelues one to the other, as that they giue no iuſt occaſion, either by word, deed or geſture, to ſuſpect one the other of lightneſſe or vnfaithfulneſſe, but ſo as they may haue good cauſe to repoſe truſt and confidence each in the other, whether preſent or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, <hi>Prou.</hi> 31.11.</p>
               <p n="3">3 By yeelding due beneuolence one to the other, in the right and lawfull vſe of the mariage bed; vſing it temperatly and ſeaſonably,
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:13990:99"/>and with prayer to God for a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vpon it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.3, 4, 5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.21. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.27. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="commandment">
            <head>The Table of the eighth Commandement. <hi>The Negatiue part.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>It forbids in generall euery thing whatſoeuer, that tends to the hurt or hinderance of the wealth and outward good eſtate of man; and thoſe things are either inward in the heart, or outward things.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Inward things in the heart, as inward longings and luſtings of the heart after another mans wealth, the heart giuing conſent vnto them. Or couetous deſires in the hearts of
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:13990:100"/>men or women of that wealth which is none of theirs, though they neuer ſeeke to get it wrongful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 7.21. <hi>Mica.</hi> 2.2. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.16.</p>
            <p>Thoſe longings, and luſtings, and couetous deſires are moſt vile, and moſt odious, when they are inſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and vex and diſquiet the heart with carking cares, and are ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and ſtrong, as they ſet a man or a woman forward to get ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans wealth againſt conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſenſe and reaſon, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times againſt the light of nature, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.4.19, 20. <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.14, 15, 16. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4.8. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9, 10.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Outward things, and thoſe are either</p>
            <p>Such as tend to the hurt or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance of a man or a womans own wealth and outward good eſtate:</p>
            <p>Or ſuch as tend to the hurt or
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:13990:100"/>hinderance of a man or a womans owne wealth, and outward good eſtate:</p>
            <p>Or ſuch as tend to the hurt or hinderance of the wealth and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward good eſtate of another, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, one or more.</p>
            <p>Such things as tend to the hurt or hinderance of a man or a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans owne wealth and outward good eſtate, are either</p>
            <p>Such things as doe waſte and conſume a man or a womans owne wealth and outward good eſtate, are three things eſpecially:</p>
            <p n="1">1 Idleneſſe, ſloth, and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, <hi>Prou.</hi> 6.6. to 12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.4. <hi>Prou.</hi> 20.4.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.30, 31, 32, 33, 34. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Vnthriftineſſe and careleſneſſe, either in ordering or ſpending a man or a womans goods, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.12.
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:13990:101"/>
               <hi>Prou.</hi> 21.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 23.21. <hi>Luke</hi> 15.13, 14, 15, 16.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Raſh, heedleſſe, and vnadui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſuretiſhip, <hi>Prou.</hi> 6.1, 2, 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.16. <hi>Prou.</hi> 22.26, 27.</p>
            <p>Or ſuch things as doe defraud a man or a woman of the right and comfortable vſe of their wealth, as namely, a baſe, couetous, needie, and an euill eye or niggardly ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, when there is iuſt and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie cauſe of ſpending, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.26. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 6.1, 2.</p>
            <p>Such things as tend to the hurt or hinderance of the wealth and outward good eſtate of another, or others, one or more.</p>
            <p>And thoſe are ſuch things as tend to the hurt or hinderance of the wealth and outward good eſtate,</p>
            <p>Either of the Church,</p>
            <p>Or Common-wealth,</p>
            <pb n="199" facs="tcp:13990:101"/>
            <p> Or ſome particular perſon or perſons, one or more.</p>
            <p>Thoſe things which tend to the hurt or hinderance of the outward good eſtate of the Church, are two things:</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.22.</note> Sacriledge or Church-rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Symonie.</p>
            <p>Sacriledge or Church-robbery is committed two waies:</p>
            <p>Firſt, by diminiſhing or by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing and taking to ones ſelfe in whole or in part, thoſe things that either by the commandement of God, or by the free and voluntarie gift of man, or by the law of man are appointed and ſet apart for reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious vſes, as for the maintaining of the Miniſter of the Word, or of Vniuerſities and Schooles of good learning,
<note place="margin">Ioſh. 7.21.</note> or for the maintenance &amp; releefe of the poore, as Hoſpitals,
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:13990:102"/>Almes-houſes and ſuch like,
<note place="margin">Pro. 20.25. Malac. 3.8, 9, 10.</note> or doe any way belong to the worſhip and ſeruice of God, as the place appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the publike worſhip and ſeruice of God, the Church com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſo called, or the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on table, Cups, Bookes, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">Ier. 23.1, 2. Ezech. 34.2, 3, 8. Phil. 2.21. Iudg. 9.4. Dan. 5.2, 3. Mat. 21.12, 13.</note> By imploying things appointed and ſet apart for religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vſes, to other ends and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and by abuſing them, eſpecially by ſuch as haue the benefit and vſe of them.</p>
            <p>Simonie, or buying and ſelling of Church-offices or places to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe thoſe offices in,
<note place="margin">Acts 8.18, 19. 2 King. 5.20, 21. Mat. 23.4.</note> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, buying and ſelling of the myſteries and Sacraments of the Church, and of ſpirituall things for priuate gaine, which is properly Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie.</p>
            <p>Thoſe things which tend to the
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:13990:102"/>hurt or hinderance of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, are three:</p>
            <p n="1">1 The robbing of the publike treaſurie,
<note place="margin">2 King. 12.18. Neh. 13.7.</note> and direct taking away from the common ſtock, and from the goods that belong either to the Crowne,
<note place="margin">12.13.</note> or to the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or to ſome Citie or corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The defrauding of ſuch gifts as are giuen for publike vſes, and are to be imployed for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good,
<note place="margin">Iohn 12.6.</note> as for the maintaining of common high-waies and ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The doing of ſuch things as bring damage and detriment to the Common-wealth, and do procure and cauſe a dearth and ſcarcitie of ſuch outward good things as are of neceſſary vſe in a Land and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, in a Citie, Towne, or Village, which is done three waies:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="202" facs="tcp:13990:103"/> 1 By hording vp and withhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſelling of corne,
<note place="margin">Pro. 11.26. Iames 5.1, 2, 3.</note> and of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſarie commodities which men or women haue of their owne, when they may ſpare them, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue need of them, in hope to raiſe the price of them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By getting vp all a commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie into ones hand,
<note place="margin">Mica 3.3.</note>
               <note place="margin">Amos 8.4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</note> either to carry out of the Land, or to ſell it as men liſt themſelues, euen the very refuſe, as by engroſſing commodities, foreſtalling markets, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By vncharitable encloſure,
<note place="margin">Iſay 3.14. Iſay 5.8.</note> as by diſpeopling houſes and townes, and by incloſing common fields to mens owne priuate benefit and gaine.</p>
            <p>Thoſe things that hurt or hinder the wealth and outward good eſtate of ſome particular perſon, or perſons, one or more, are things done either in matter of contract
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:13990:103"/>between perſon and perſon, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons one or more, or out of the matter of contract.</p>
            <p>Things that are done in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of contract, betweene perſon and perſon, or perſons one or more are either in buying and ſelling, and exchanging; Or in borrowing and lending; Or in hiring and letting; Or in pawning, and taking things to pawne.</p>
            <p>Things that are done in buying and exchanging, are either by the buyer or by the ſeller, or by the buyer and the ſeller.</p>
            <p>The things which are done by the buyer, are three.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The extenuating the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the things which the buyer cheapneth contrary to his owne knowledge either by himſelfe or by another.
<note place="margin">Pro. 20.14. Iſay 5.20.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2
<note place="margin">Gen. 23.9.13.</note> The taking aduantage of the
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:13990:104"/>ſellers either ſimplicitie or preſent neceſſitie,
<note place="margin">Leu. 25.14, 15, 16.</note> to buy his commoditie, for leſſe than it is worth.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The making of bad payment of the price agreed on betweene him and the ſeller.
<note place="margin">Gen. 23.16 Ier. 32.8, 9, 10. Gen. 43.12</note>
            </p>
            <p>The things which are done by the ſeller, are fiue:</p>
            <p n="1">1 The praiſing,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.2. Iſai. 5.20.</note> commending, and extolling the things he hath to ſell, and is about to ſell aboue the knowne goodneſſe, and worth of them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The taking aduantage of the buyers either ſimplicitie,
<note place="margin">Leu. 25.14, 15, 16. Amos 8.5. Gen. 23.15.</note> or preſent neceſſitie to ſell his commodity for more than it is worth.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The ſelling and deliuering of that which hee knowes to be bad ware, for good ware, at the price of good: which is done two wayes; firſt, by ſelling and deliuering that which he knowes to be bad in the
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:13990:104"/>matter and ſubſtance of it, for good,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 1.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Amos 8.6.</note> and in the ſtead of good, and at the price of good. Secondly, by ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and deliuering that which hee knowes is bad and ſaultie in the qualitie of it, for good,
<note place="margin">Luke 19.8. Rom. 1.29. 1 Theſſ. 4.6</note> and in the ſtead of good, at the price of good.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The deceiuing of the buyer,
<note place="margin">Deu. 19.35, 36. Deu. 25.13, 14, 15. Ezech. 45.10. Prou. 11.1. &amp; 20.10. Mica 6.10, 11. Pro. 11.10. Leu. 25.14, 15, 16. 1 Theſſ. 4.6</note> in the number, weight, or meaſure of the things ſold vnto him, by number, weight, or meaſure, and yet taking the full price agreed on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them.</p>
            <p n="5">5 The raiſing of the iuſt price of things, and the racking of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the things he hath to ſell, to the oppreſſion of the poore.</p>
            <p>The things that are done by the buyer, and by the ſeller,
<note place="margin">Iſay 55.12. Act. 19.24.</note> are the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſelling of things either vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable and hurtfull, as Cards, Dice, and ſuch like: or things that tend meerely to maintaine pride
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:13990:105"/>and vanitie, as painting and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>Thoſe things that are done to the hurt or hinderance of another, or others, one or more, in borrowing and lending, are either done by the borrower, or by the lender.</p>
            <p>Thoſe things which are done by the borrower, are two:</p>
            <p n="1">1 By not returning or not reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the thing borrowed to the len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as it ought to be returned or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, which is done three waies.</p>
            <p n="1">1 By not returning or not reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the thing borrowed,
<note place="margin">2 King. 6.5 Pſal. 37.21. Prou. 3.27. Rom. 13.8.</note> to the len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at all.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By not returning or not reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the thing borrowed,
<note place="margin">2 King. 4.1. Prou. 3.28.</note> to the len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in due time, and at the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, for the returning and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of it; but keeping it ouer and aboue that time, without the conſent of the lender.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="207" facs="tcp:13990:105"/> 3 By not returning or not reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againe to the lender the thing borrowed,
<note place="margin">Exo. 22.14.</note> which is ſpent in the vſe of it, both as much, and euery way as good as was lent in the ſame kinde; or by not returning, or not reſtoring the thing borowed, which is not ſpent in the vſe of it, whether it be a liuing thing, as a ſeruant, an horſe, or a Cow, and ſuch like; or a thing without life, both as much, and euery way as good as it was lent.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The borrowing of any thing, eſpecially money, either</p>
            <p>To ill ends and purpoſes, as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to maintaine himſelfe in pride, in riot, and ſuch like: or that by the thing borrowed, the borrower may hurt or wrong another, or others, one or more, in his or their wealth and outward good eſtate.</p>
            <p>Or after an vnlawfull manner,
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:13990:106"/>(namely) on vſurie, (that is) ſo as the borrower couenanteth with the lender, to returne to him not only the thing lent, in the full number, weight, meaſure, and quantitie, but ſomething ouer and aboue, only in liew and recompence of the len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it.</p>
            <p>Thoſe things that are done by the lender are three:</p>
            <p n="1">1 The lending to ſuch perſons as the lender knowes doe borrow to ill ends and purpoſes, as to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine themſelues in pride, riot, or ſuch like, or in any ſinfull courſe, or to hurt, wrong, vex or trouble an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, or others, one or more.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The lending after an vnlawful manner, namely, on vſury (that is) ſo as the lender will haue the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower to couenant with him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to him, not onely the thing lent in the full number, weight,
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:13990:106"/>meaſure, and the full ſumme and quantitie of it, but alſo an ouerplus and ſomething ouer and aboue, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in liew and recompence of his lending of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The requiring of the thing lent in ſuch manner as it ought not to be required, which is done two waies:</p>
            <p>Firſt, when the lender doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the thing lent too greedily, as either before the time appointed for the returning of it, hauing no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary need of it, but only out of his couetous minde, or at an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable time, as on the Sabbath, or the like.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when the lender re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the thing lent with rigour, and with extreme hard dealing, vſing crueltie towards the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower, though he doe humble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to him, as by caſting him into priſon, or the like.</p>
            <pb n="210" facs="tcp:13990:107"/>
            <p> Things in hiring and letting, are either done by the hirer or by the letter.</p>
            <p>Things done by the hirer are two:</p>
            <p n="1">1 The not returning of the thing hired, as it ought to be returned, which is done when the hirer either returnes not the thing that he hath hired at all, or not at the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the returne of it, but wittingly and purpoſely keepes it ouer and aboue that time, without the conſent of the letter, or not in the ſtate that he receiued it, but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hurt or ſpoiled through his owne default, without making due ſatisfaction for that hurt or ſpoile.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The not paying of the hire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on betweene him and the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for the thing hired, as it ought to be paid, whether it be a thing to be vſed, as houſe, ſhop, chamber,
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:13990:107"/>land, or the like, or a mans labour, but either withholding it, or chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging it, or not paying of it in due time.</p>
            <p>Things done by the letter, are three:</p>
            <p n="1">1 The letting of a thing to hire at an vnreaſonable rate, which is done either directly, as when it is let for more than can be raiſed and made of the vſe of it in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any that knowes it, and is able to iudge of it; or indirectly and vnder a colour, as when it is let for an indifferent rate, in reſpect of the vſe of the thing it ſelfe, yet ſo as the letter will not ſtand to the hazard of it, but makes the hirer couenant with him abſolutely, to make the thing hired good to him at all times without any allowance, in reſpect of any caſualtie that ſhall come, though the thing hired being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:13990:108"/>to many caſualties, doe periſh without his default.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The letting of a thing to hire of worſe quality than is pretended; as when the letter lets it to the hirer for his vſe, which hee knowes will not ſerue his turne.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The withholding from the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer the vſe of the thing he hath let to him to hire, either in whole or in part.</p>
            <p>Things that are done to the hurt or hinderance of another, or others, one or more, in pawning and in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king things to pawne, are things that are done by the pawner, or by the partie who takes things to pawne.</p>
            <p>Things done by the pawner are three.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The pawning of ſuch things as ought not to be laid to pawne, as ones life, his owne wearing cloths,
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:13990:108"/>which are for preſent vſe, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The pawning of things to ill ends and purpoſes, as for the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of ſome wicked purpoſe, or the like.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The not fetching home of his pawne at the time appointed, for the redeeming of it, by doing that which ought to be done for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of it being able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme it, but letting it ſtill lie in the hands of the partie to whom it is pawned to his loſſe or hinderance.</p>
            <p>Things done by the partie who takes things to pawne are three.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The taking of a thing to pawne that ought not to bee taken, as namely, things that are of neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and preſent vſe for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and preſeruation of the life of man.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The vſing of the thing paw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:13990:109"/>and taking profit and benefit of the vſe of it within the compaſſe of the time ſet and appointed for the redemption of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The not returning and not reſtoring the pawne at the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the returne of it, as it ought to be returned.</p>
            <p>Things that are done out of the matter of contract, to the hurt or hinderance of another, or others, one or more, are two:</p>
            <p>Firſt, the vniuſt taking away of that wealth, or any part of it, that belongs to another, or others, one or more.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the conſpiring with thoſe who vniuſtly take away that wealth, or any part of it, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to another, or others, one or more.</p>
            <p>The vniuſt taking away of that wealth, or any part of it, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:13990:109"/>to another, or others, one or more, is done three waies:</p>
            <p n="1">1 By open violence and force, which is exerciſed two waies: Firſt, by laying violent and ſtrong hands on that wealth which belongs to another, or others, one or more, or any part of it, whether by ſea or by land, and taking it to ones ſelfe as a prey. Secondly, by making ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocke and ſpoile of the wealth, which belongs to another, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, one or more, or any part of it. meerely of euill will, and of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, or of a meere delight in doing miſchiefe, without any profit or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to the ſpoiler.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By ſecret and priuie ſtealth, which is practiſed three waies:</p>
            <p>Firſt, by pilfering, conueying, and ſecret carrying away that wealth which belongs to another, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, one or more, or any part of it.</p>
            <pb n="216" facs="tcp:13990:110"/>
            <p> Secondly, by ſecret and vniuſt waſting and conſuming, and draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from that wealth which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to another, or others, one or more, or any part of it, being ſuch as one may come vnto without ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, by ſecret encroaching vpon another mans wealth or poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, which is moſt vile, when it is vpon the wealth or poſſeſſion of the fatherleſſe or helpleſſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By fraud and deceit, which is vſed either in reſpect of perſons or things.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of the perſons that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to another, or others, one or more, as by alluring, and by enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing away by word or deed, as by perſwaſion, or gifts, any perſon or perſons that belong to another, or others, one or more.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of the things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:13990:110"/>to another, or others, one or more, and that is done ſeuen waies.</p>
            <p n="1">1 By peruerting of the Law, or corrupting iudgement in caſes tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching lands or goods, which is moſt vile, when it is done vnder colour of equitie, conſcience, and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By vſing and practiſing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull Arts and courſes to get that wealth, or any part of it, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to another, or others, one or more, as iugling, charming, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By falſe dealing in matters of truſt, touching lands or goods.</p>
            <p n="4">4 By concealing things ſtrayed or found, and keeping them, and withholding them from the right owner, being knowne.</p>
            <p n="5">5 By pretending pouertie and want without iuſt cauſe, and by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king almes, when men or women
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:13990:111"/>haue no need, whereby they doe defraud the poore, and take that which belongs to ſuch as are truly poore.</p>
            <p n="6">6 By gaming for money and gaine, eſpecially at vnlawful games.</p>
            <p n="7">7 By vſing deuices and ſubtilties of wit, to get that wealth, or any part of it, that belongs to another, or others, one or more, as lying, vſing another mans name, he not knowing of it; pretending skill to doe another good by Phyſick, Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie, or ſuch like, when there is no skill; or any manner of coſenage, commonly called cony-catching, cheating, or ſuch like.</p>
            <p>The conſpiring with thoſe who vniuſtly take away that wealth, or any part of it, that belongs to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or others, one or more, which is done foure waies:</p>
            <p n="1">1 By counſelling, perſwading, or
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:13990:111"/>commanding, or by hiring, or any way plotting with another, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, one or more, to take away that wealth, or any part of it, that belongs to another, or others, one or more, by any vniuſt way or meanes.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By being preſent with others, when they doe vniuſtly take away that wealth which belongs to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or others, one or more, and conſenting to them by ſilence, and not reprouing them.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By receiuing and harbouring of thoſe, who haue vniuſtly taken away that wealth, or any part of it, that belongs to another, or others, one or more, and hiding and concealing of them, and pleading for them, and by receiuing, and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and concealing the things they haue vniuſtly taken away.</p>
            <p n="4">4 By fauouring &amp; by vpholding
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:13990:112"/>thoſe who vniuſtly take away that wealth, or any part of it, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to another, or others, one or more,
<note place="margin">Iſay 1.23. Rom. 1.31.</note> either by impunitie (hauing power to puniſh) or by feeding and cloathing of luſtie and ſtout rogues and beggers.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Affirmatiue part of the eighth Commandement.</head>
               <p>It requires in general euery thing whatſoeuer that tends to the helpe or furtherance of the wealth and outward good eſtate of man, and thoſe things are either inward in the heart, or outward things.</p>
               <p>Things inward in the heart, are two:</p>
               <p>Firſt, a ſtayedneſſe in the minde, and a ſetled purpoſe in the heart of man or woman, to ſeeke riches and
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:13990:112"/>outward good things, onely ſo far as they may in the vſe of lawfull meanes, and may look for the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God on their endeuours, and ſo far as the Lord ſhall be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to offer them matter, and to giue them iuſt occaſion ſo to doe, and no further.</p>
               <p>Secondly, a contentedneſſe of minde, with that part and portion of wealth, and of outward good things, whether it be little or much, which God hath allotted: the ground of which contentedneſſe of minde, is a reſting by faith on the promiſe of God, and a depending on his prouidence without diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full care.</p>
               <p>Outward good things, are either ſuch things as tend to the helpe or furtherance of a man or womans owne wealth, and outward good eſtate;</p>
               <pb n="222" facs="tcp:13990:113"/>
               <p> Or ſuch things as tend to the helpe or furtherance of the wealth and outward good eſtate of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or others, one or more.</p>
               <p>Such things as tend to the helpe or furtherance of a man or womans owne wealth and outward good eſtate, are either concerning the get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of wealth, the keeping of wealth, or the vſing of wealth.</p>
               <p>Things that concerne the getting of wealth, are two:</p>
               <p>Firſt, an honeſt and lawfull par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular calling, wherein euery one being of yeares, is to walke and to be imployed.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Diligence, and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and faithfull labour in that honeſt particular calling, wherein a man or a woman is ſet.</p>
               <p>Things that concerne the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of wealth, are two:</p>
               <p>Firſt, frugality or thriftineſſe, and a
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:13990:113"/>care to ſaue that wealth which God hath giuen.</p>
               <p>Secondly, peaceableneſſe, and a care to keepe and hold that wealth which God hath giuen, with peace, auoiding law and contention, as much as is poſſible.</p>
               <p>Things that concerne the vſing of wealth, are two:</p>
               <p>Firſt, a wiſe, conuenient, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable diſpenſing of the wealth which God hath giuen to any, to the honeſt maintenance of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and their families, if they haue any.</p>
               <p>Secondly, a moderation in ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that wealth which God hath giuen to any perſon, man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ordering and limiting their expences to the proportion of their meanes.</p>
               <p>Such things as tend to the helpe or furtherance of the wealth and
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:13990:114"/>outward good eſtate of another, or others, one or more, are foure.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Iuſt dealing with another, or others, one or more, in reſpect of wealth and outward good things.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Yeelding helpe to another, or others, in outward good things, ſtanding in need of helpe that way.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Procuring the wealth of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or others, one or more.</p>
               <p n="4">4 In reſtoring things vniuſtly gotten or taken away from another, or others, one or more.</p>
               <p>Iuſt dealing with another, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, one or more, in reſpect of wealth and outward good things, ſtandeth in foure things:</p>
               <p>Firſt, in a willing yeelding of that which is due, to euery one bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring office in the Church, or in the Common-wealth, as Tribute, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, Tithes, Tenths, &amp; ſuch like.</p>
               <pb n="225" facs="tcp:13990:114"/>
               <p> Secondly, in vſing truth, ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, and plainneſſe both in word and deed, in bargaining, in buying and ſelling, in hiring and letting.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, in keeping of all iuſt and lawfull couenants in matter of contract betweene perſon and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or perſons, one or more, as in buying, in ſelling, in borrowing, in lending, in hiring, in letting, in pawning, and in taking things to pawne.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, in a readie yeelding of that which is due, to any perſon or perſons, one or more, by way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall.</p>
               <p>In yeelding helpe to another, or others, one or more, in outward things, ſtanding in need of helpe that way, ſtandeth in two things:</p>
               <p n="1">1 In a readie and willing giuing.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In free lending.</p>
               <p>In a readie and willing giuing to
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:13990:115"/>another, or others, one or more, and communicating to their neceſſities in outward things, both to ſuch as are abſolutely poore, whether in common want, or extreme want, and alſo to thoſe, who for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, by reaſon of ſome ſudden ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, doe want and ſtand in need of releefe, though otherwiſe of good meanes: and this communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating to the neceſſities of others in outward things, muſt be with reſpect,</p>
               <p n="1">1 To the ſtate and condition of the parties that ſtand in need of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe; releeuing thoſe who are in great need, before thoſe whoſe wants are but common and ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; and thoſe that are in extreme neceſſitie, though enemies, before friends and acquaintance, not in like want; and amongſt ſuch as are in extreme neceſſitie, thoſe who
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:13990:115"/>are the firſt caſt vpon vs by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2 To the perſons that are to be releeued, the want and neceſſitie of the perſons being alike: firſt, relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thoſe, to whom we are bound by the bond of bloud, kindred, or alliance, and then others; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others, firſt, thoſe that are nearer to vs in habitation, and then thoſe that are further off; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe that are either nearer or further off, ſuch eſpecially as are of the houſhold of faith; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe muſt be giuen liberally accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our abilitie, and to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of the receiuers, as neare as we can.</p>
               <p>In free lending to another, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, one or more, as occaſion is offered; and if the partie to whom ſomething is lent, be decayed in his or her outward eſtate, by the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:13990:116"/>hand of God, or be brought to extreme pouertie in free forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the debt.</p>
               <p>The procuring the wealth of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, or others, one or more, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in three things:</p>
               <p>Firſt, in a wiſe and diſcreet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking and becomming ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for another, or others, one or more.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in dealing faithfully with the goods of another, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, one or more, being truſted with them.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, in auerting and turning away harmes from the goods of another, or others, one or more, as occaſion is offered.</p>
               <p>The reſtoring of things vniuſtly gotten or taken away from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or others, one or more, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth</p>
               <p>In making recompence and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:13990:116"/>for things vniuſtly gotten, or taken away from another, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, one or more, which is done by returning to them either the ſame things euery way as good as they were when they firſt had them, with an ouerplus anſwerable to the dammage they haue ſuſtained by the want of them; or elſe things of the ſame kinde, euery way as good as they were, both for the quantitie, and for the worth and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of them, with ſo much ouer and aboue, as they haue ſuſtained loſſe or hinderance by the want of them, for the time they haue wanted them.</p>
               <trailer>The end of the eighth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="commandment">
            <pb n="230" facs="tcp:13990:117"/>
            <head>The 9. Commandement. <hi>The Negatiue part.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>It forbids in generall whatſoeuer is contrary to the truth, and tends to the hurt or hinderance of the good name of man or woman; and thoſe things are,</p>
            <p>Either ſuch things as are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the truth, and tend to the hurt or hinderance of a man or womans owne good name:</p>
            <p>Or ſuch things as are contrarie to the truth, and tend to the hurt or hinderance of the good name of another, or others, one or more.</p>
            <p>Such things as are contrarie to the truth, and tend to the hurt or hinderance of a man or a womans owne good name, are either things
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:13990:117"/>inward in the heart, or expreſſed and vttered by the tongue.</p>
            <p>Things inward in the heart, are two things eſpecially.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſelfe-conceitedneſſe, and an ouer-weening of their owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie, when a man or a woman doe thinke themſelues either to be that which they are not, or are too highly conceited of the good things they haue.</p>
            <p>Secondly, too baſe and too mean a conceit, and an vnder-weening of the good things that be in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; when a man or a woman doe think that either they haue not that grace, and thoſe good things, or not that meaſure of grace, and of good things that indeed they haue.</p>
            <p>Things expreſſed and vttered by the tongue, are three things eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially:</p>
            <p n="1">1 Vain-glorious boaſting and
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:13990:118"/>bragging, which is moſt vile and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, when it is a boaſting and bragging of wickedneſſe and ſinne.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The leſſening and extenuating of their faults.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The vniuſt accuſing of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as by ſpeech, either denying, or extenuating and leſſening the graces and gifts God hath beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on them.</p>
            <p>Such things as are contrary to the truth, and tend to the hurt or hinderance of the good name of another, or others, one or more, are,</p>
            <p>Either things inward in the heart, or expreſſed and vttered by the tongue.</p>
            <p>Things inward in the heart, are foure things eſpecially.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Light and wrongfull ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and euill ſurmiſing and cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe miſdeeming of another, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:13990:118"/>one or more, which comes either from their weakneſſe of iudgement, or from their owne guiltineſſe of ſinne, or from ſome euill affection of enuie, hatred, or the like.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Raſh, vncharitable, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt iudging and condemning of another, or others, one or more, which is done two waies: Either in reſpect of their perſons, as when they thinke otherwiſe of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, than they ought to doe, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of ſome ſlips, infirmities, euill reports; or in regard of ſome croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or ſome ſtrange accident that befals them: Or in regard of their words or deeds, as when they thinke and iudge otherwiſe of their words and deeds, than they ought to doe, as when they thinke and iudge ill of their good ſpeeches or actions, or doe take their ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:13990:119"/>or actions that are indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in the worſt part, or doe thinke and iudge the things that are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or done amiſſe by them, worſe than they are.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Inward contemning and thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king baſely of another, or others, one or more, and diſdaining of them for worldly reſpects.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Admiring of others, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying of them in the inward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of the heart aboue their worth, which is moſt vile and odious, when it is for their errors and ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Things expreſſed and vttered by the tongue, are either things expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and vttered to another, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, one or more, or things ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed and vttered of another, or others, one or more.</p>
            <p>Things expreſſed and vttered by the tongue to another, or others, one or more, are either things vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:13990:119"/>vainly or falſly.</p>
            <p>Things vttered vainly, are either things vttered without reaſon, and out of ſeaſon, when a man or a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man are pratlers, and too full of words, and do keep nothing ſecret, but tell whatſoeuer they know, and doe needleſſely publiſh the ſecrets and infirmities of others, to their diſcredit.</p>
            <p>The things vttered falſly, are two eſpecially:</p>
            <p n="1">1 Lying, when a man or a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man doe willingly and wittingly ſpeake that which they know is falſe, with a minde and purpoſe to deceiue, which is moſt odious, when it is either to cloake and ſmooth ouer a ſinne alreadie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, or to make way for ſinne and the doing of ſome euil, or when it is to intrap another, or others, one or more, and to draw them into
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:13990:120"/>ſome errour or ſinne, or into ſome danger.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Such ſpeech as ſetteth either praiſe or diſpraiſe where it ſhould not, and a man or a woman doe praiſe others to their faces vniuſtly, by flattering of them, as when they doe to their faces praiſe, commend, and extoll either their perſons, or their gifts, or their actions, aboue that which they know or thinke, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to get fauour with them, or ſome way or other for their owne aduantage, which is moſt odious, when it is with hatred and malice in the heart, and that flattering is moſt hurtful and dangerous, which is vſed in things that concerne the ſtate of the ſoule.
<note place="margin">Iſai. 5.20. Iob 16.20. Iob 27.5, 6.</note> And they doe diſpraiſe others to their faces vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly, when in their ſpeech vttered to others, they doe contrarie to their knowledge, and out of enuie,
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:13990:120"/>diſpraiſe their perſons, or good gifts, or good actions, with a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe either to diſgrace or to diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them.</p>
            <p>Things expreſſed and vttered of another, or others, one or more, are either on the part of the ſpeaker, or on the part of the hearer.</p>
            <p>Things expreſſed and vttered on the part of the ſpeaker, which are ſpeeches vttered of others, either in priuate or in publike:</p>
            <p>In priuate, and thoſe are either,</p>
            <p>In the preſence of the partie or parties, one or more, of whom they are ſpoken, and thoſe are ſpeeches falſly charging ſome ill on another, or others, one or more, to their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, either contrary to knowledge, or on ſome light ſuſpicion.</p>
            <p>Or behind their backes, and out of their preſence, and thoſe are tale-bearing, back-biting and ſlandering
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:13990:121"/>ſpeeches, and malicious defamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and men doe carrie tales, back-bite and ſlander, and maliciouſly defame others, two waies:</p>
            <p n="1">1 By whiſpering ill of them, by rounding in the eare, or eares of ſuch as will heare them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By ſpeaking ill of them more openly. And the whiſpering or ſpeaking ill more openly of others behinde their backes, is moſt vile and odious; when the report of ill that is either whiſpered, or ſpoken more openly, is falſe, or when it is coloured ouer with faire pretences.</p>
            <p>In publike, and thoſe are either,</p>
            <p>In the abſence of the partie, or parties, one or more, of whom they are ſpoken, which are ſpeeches ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther falſly charging ſome ill on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers behinde their backes, and that either againſt knowledge, or on ſome light ſuſpicion, or truly char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:13990:121"/>ſome ill on them behinde their backes out of malice, or by ſome by-reſpect, by way of publike in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, without any calling thereunto.</p>
            <p>Or in the preſence of the partie, or parties, one or more, of whom they are ſpoken; and thoſe are ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches vttered in open place of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and iudgement, falſly char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ſome ill on others in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence:</p>
            <p>Either by</p>
            <p>The Iudge or Iudges, one or more, in giuing falſe ſentence and vniuſt iudgement againſt others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before them to bee examined and tried, touching ſome matter of crime.</p>
            <p>Or by Aduocates, Pleaders and Patrons of cauſes; as ſpeeches vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by them in their falſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt pleading againſt others, being
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:13990:122"/>in ſome open court to be examined and tried touching ſome matter of crime.</p>
            <p>Or by Iurors, as ſpeeches vttered by them, in giuing vp a falſe and vniuſt verdict againſt others, being in ſome open court to be examined touching ſome matter of crime.</p>
            <p>Or by accuſers, as ſpeeches vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by them, whereby they doe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly and wrongfully accuſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, being in ſome open court to be examined and tried touching ſome matter of crime.</p>
            <p>Or by witneſſes, as ſpeeches vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by them, whereby they doe vniuſtly teſtifie againſt others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſome open court to be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and tried touching ſome matter of crime, which is done three waies:</p>
            <p n="1">1 By affirming ſomething as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes againſt others, which they
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:13990:122"/>know is directly and maliciouſly falſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By denying or concealing of ſomething knowne to themſelues to be true, and which they ought to ſpeake.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By affirming ſomething againſt others, as witneſſes, craftily and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully.</p>
            <p>Things vttered and expreſſed of another, or others, one or more, on the part of the hearer, which are ſpeeches heard and willingly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and entertained by the hearer, or hearers, one or more, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the truth, and tend to the hurt or hinderance of the good name of others, of whom they are ſpoken, and this is done two waies.</p>
            <p n="1">1 By beleeuing and eaſily giuing credit to flying tales and ill reports that are made of others, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the thing, or things reported to
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:13990:123"/>be true, and thereupon iudging a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe of them, or hating them, or contemning them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By hearing of ill reports that are made of others, not knowing the thing or things reported to be true, yet ſuſpecting them to bee falſe, with patience and ſilence, and ſhewing no diſlike to them at all, either by countenance, or ſpeech, or turning away the body, or ſuch like.</p>
            <p>And both theſe are moſt odious, when the report of ill is againſt ſuch as are truly religious, and they are moſt pernicious, when the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of ill is beleeued, or heard, or receiued with patience, by Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and by ſuch as be in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="243" facs="tcp:13990:123"/>
               <head>The Affirmatiue part of the ninth Commandement.</head>
               <p>It requireth in generall whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is agreeable to the truth, and tends to the helpe or furtherance of the good name of man or woman, and thoſe things are,</p>
               <p>Either ſuch things as are agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the truth, and tend to the helpe or furtherance of a man or a womans owne good name:</p>
               <p>Or ſuch things as are agreeable to the truth, and tend to the helpe or furtherance of the good name of another, or others, one or more.</p>
               <p>Thoſe things that are agreeable to the truth, and tend to the helpe or furtherance of a man or a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans owne good name, are</p>
               <p>Either things inward in the heart:</p>
               <pb n="244" facs="tcp:13990:124"/>
               <p> Or things expreſſed and vttered by the tongue.</p>
               <p>Things inward in the heart, are two things eſpecially.</p>
               <p n="1">1 A right iudgement and eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of themſelues, and of their owne gifts, neither ouer-weening, nor vnder-weening of them.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A loue of their owne good name, and a care of their credit, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing that by all good ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to get a good name, and being gotten, to keepe it; and if at any time it be through ſinne impaired or loſt, to recouer it.</p>
               <p>And a man or a woman muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to get a good name, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing gotten it, to keepe it, by liuing religiouſly, embracing the truth of religion in loue to it, and practiſing in an holy life ſincerely, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſſimulation, keeping a narrow watch againſt euery ſinne, and with
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:13990:124"/>an honeſt and vpright heart, ſeeking Gods glory in euery thing.</p>
               <p>And a man or woman is to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a good name, it being impaired or loſt through ſinne, by true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and vnfained conuerſion and turning to God, &amp; by breaking off that ſin, and by teſtifying the ſame before men by amendment of life.</p>
               <p>Things expreſſed and vttered by the tongue are three things eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially.</p>
               <p n="1">1 A ſpeaking ſparingly, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyding vaine babling in ordinary communication.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A wiſe and diſcreet ſpeaking when they haue occaſion to menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on either their vertues and good things, or their faults &amp; euill things to men. And their wiſe and diſcreet ſpeaking hauing occaſion to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion their vertues and good things to men, ſtandeth in ſpeaking
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:13990:125"/>of them with modeſtie, ſo as their ſpeech incline rather to the defect than to the exceſſe, and ſo as they rather extenuate them than boaſt of them.</p>
               <p>And their wiſe and diſcreet ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, hauing occaſion to mention their faults and euill things to men, ſtandeth in ſpeaking of their knowne faults and corruptions to men, the vttermoſt they can againſt themſelues, yet ſo as they giue no ſuſpition of pride or hypocriſie, and ſo as they doe not diſgrace them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues too much, as they make themſelues able to doe leſſe good then otherwiſe they might, in ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of their ſecret faults and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions to men onely, when it is fit and meet for them ſo to doe, and that is onely in two caſes.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 In the caſe of ſecret offence and wrong done to others.</item>
                  <pb n="247" facs="tcp:13990:125"/>
                  <item>2 In caſe of trouble of minde and conſcience, ſo as it bee to ſuch as are able and willing to comfort and counſell them, and alſo faithfull.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="3">3 A ſpeaking in defence of their owne good name when need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, ſo as they doe it modeſtly and willingly.</p>
               <p>Such things as are agreeable to the truth, and tend to the helpe and furtherance of another or others, one or moe, are either things inward in the heart, or things expreſſed and vttered by the tongue.</p>
               <p>Things inward in the heart are three eſpecially.</p>
               <p n="1">1 A charitable opinion and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation of others, and a thinking the beſt of things ſaid or done by them, and a taking of them in good part, ſo farre as truth and reaſon will giue leaue.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="248" facs="tcp:13990:126"/> 2 A true loue, and an hearty wel-wiſhing to the good name of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or others, one or more, which may be knowne by two things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 By reioycing for their credit and good eſtimation, they knowing them on good grounds, to be in good credit, and in good eſtimation.</item>
                  <item>2 By grieuing when they know they deſerue diſcredit and diſgrace, and doe heare a true report of ſome ill ſpoken or done by them, whereby they are iuſtly blemiſhed, and their reputation iuſtly dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="3">3 A ſtayedneſſe of iudgement, touching ill reports that are made of others, not knowing the thing or things reported to be true.</p>
               <p>Things expreſſed and vttered by the tongue, are either things expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:13990:126"/>and vttered to another or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, one or more;</p>
               <p>Or of another or others one or more.</p>
               <p>Things expreſſed and vttered to another or others, one or more, are two things eſpecially:</p>
               <p n="1">1 A ſpeaking of the truth from the heart ſimply and plainely, and as it ought to bee ſpoke, with good affection, and with a louing heart, with an intent and deſire to doe good in the ſpeaking of it, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably, a man or a woman hauing a calling to ſpeake it.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A wiſe and diſcreet ſpeaking to others for their good, as iuſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion is offered, which ſtands in two things:</p>
               <p n="1">1 In giuing them whatſoeuer aduice and counſell in matters of doubt, and in directing them in the way of God, and exhorting and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:13990:127"/>them vp to walke therein in loue and wiſedome.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In giuing them ſound and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable admonition, and iuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe for their knowne faults and offences in loue and wiſedome.</p>
               <p>Things expreſſed and vttered of another or others, one or more, are:</p>
               <p>Either on the part of the ſpeaker,</p>
               <p>Or on the part of the hearer.</p>
               <p>Things expreſſed and vttered of another or others, one or more, on the part of the ſpeaker, are:</p>
               <p>Either in priuate.</p>
               <p>Or in publike.</p>
               <p>Things expreſſed or vttered of another or others in priuate, are two things eſpecially:</p>
               <p n="1">1 A free acknowledging of the good gifts of God in others, and of the good things ſaid or done by them, and a ſpeaking of them to
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:13990:127"/>their praiſe and commendation, ſo as it be in fit time and place, as ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their abſence than in their preſence, and in a right manner, and with moderation, giuing them onely due praiſe and commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo as they doe not thereby approue of the leaſt of their ſinnes.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A ſpeaking in defence of the good name of others, when they are in our hearing, and to our knowledge traduced and ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ill reported of vniuſtly, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially behinde their backs.</p>
               <p>Things expreſſed and vttered of another or others, one or more, in publike, are:</p>
               <p>Either by ſuch as ſit as Iudges in ſome open place:</p>
               <p>Or by ſuch as are Aduocates, or Iurors.</p>
               <p>By ſuch as ſit as Iudges in ſome open place of iuſtice and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:13990:128"/>and thoſe are two things e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The abſoluing and acquitting of ſuch as come before them, and after due examination and triall, touching ſome matter of crime laid againſt them, are found guiltleſſe, and the pronouncing of them inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and free from the crimes falſly obiected againſt them.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A due encouragement of ſuch as are before them and on ſome iuſt occaſion are made knowne to them to be honeſt and good, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue well, and a giuing of them due praiſe and commendation for their well doing.</p>
               <p>Or by ſuch as are lawfully called to ſpeake in ſome open place of iuſtice and iudgement, as Aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates, or as Iurors, or as Witneſſes, which are ſpeeches vttered by them in defence of the good name of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:13990:128"/>and for the clearing of their innocencie when they are in their hearing, and to their knowledge openly wronged and falſly accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of ſome crime.</p>
               <p>Things that are vttered and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by another, or others, on the part of the hearer, are two eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially:</p>
               <p>Firſt, a readie receiuing of the good report that is made of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or others, one or more, ſo farre as truth and reaſon will giue leaue.</p>
               <p>Secondly, a ſhewing diſlike of whiſperers and tale-bearers, either by countenance, or by ſpeech, or by geſture, and ſuch like; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by Magiſtrates and ſuch as be in any place of authoritie and ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioritie.</p>
               <trailer>The end of the ninth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="commandment">
            <pb n="254" facs="tcp:13990:129"/>
            <head>The 10. Commandement. <hi>The Negatiue part.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>It forbids in generall two things:</p>
            <p n="1">1 The proneneſſe and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our corrupt nature to euill, whereby a man or a woman is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally prone to thinke, will, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect any thing that is forbidden in the Law of God, and contrarie to the true loue of God or man: and this proneneſſe and inclination to euill, is in euery man and woman deſcended from <hi>Adam</hi> by naturall generation.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The effects and fruits of the proneneſſe and inclination of our corrupt nature to euill, which are inward in the ſoule, and thoſe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects are two eſpecially:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="255" facs="tcp:13990:129"/> 1 Euill and inordinate concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence, euery motion, euen the firſt motion, comming from the rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of nature, whereby wee are ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp to euil, and doe with delight thinke any thing contrarie to the true loue of God or man, though wee neuer giue conſent of will to commit that euill.</p>
            <p n="2">2 A ſuffering our ſelues to be infected with thoſe motions, that Satan or euill men doe put into our minds, contrarie to the true loue of God or man, by yeelding to them, and delighting in them, and hauing our hearts tickled with delight in them.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="256" facs="tcp:13990:130"/>
               <head>The Affirmatiue part of the tenth Commandement.</head>
               <p>It requires two things in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall:</p>
               <p n="1">1 Originall puritie in all the powers and faculties of the ſoule, and an holy diſpoſition and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the ſoule, whereby a man or woman is at all times diſpoſed to thinke, will, and affect that which the law of God requires, and is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the true and perfect loue of God and men.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The inward effects and fruits of originall puritie in the ſoule, and of an holy diſpoſition and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſoule of man, and thoſe effects are two:</p>
               <p n="1">1 Good and holy motions of the minde and will, whereby wee
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:13990:130"/>are ſtirred vp to good things, and doe with delight thinke and will that which is agreeable to the true loue God and man.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A ſuppreſſing of euil thoughts, and motions to euill, whether com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from the fleſh within, or from Satan and euill men without, and a keeping them from taking any place in our minds, by the leaſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to them, or the leaſt delight in them.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
